<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><opinion id="101691" path="/scotus/wei/hilary-halbert-jr-et-al-petitioners-v-the/" sha1="90645bbd9d535ad9d9533f8b9bd9f6e71b6f42fe" court="Supreme Court of the United States" download_url="http://bulk.resource.org/courts.gov/c/US/282/282.US.818.141.142.143.144.145.html" time_retrieved="2010-04-28 16:50:12+00:00" date_filed="1930-10-13" precedential_status="Published" local_path="" docket_number="141" federal_cite_one="282 U.S. 818" lexis_cite="" case_name="Hilary Halbert, Jr. v. The United States of America. Rich Halbert, a Minor, Etc. v. The United States of America. Vernon Sidney Halbert, a Minor, Etc. v. The United States of America. Sidney E. Halbert, a Minor, Etc. v. The United States of America. Rose Peers Pickernoll v. The United States of America. Lulu M. Elliott v. The United States of America. Mary Barichio Petit v. The United States of America. Dewey Barichio v. The United States of America. Edna May Elliott v. The United States of America. Chas. G. Elliott, Jr. v. The United States of America. Agnes Rubens v. The United States of America. Virginia Walkowsky v. The United States of America. Lizzie Rolfson v. The United States of America. Mary Francis Provoe v. The United States of America" judges="" nature_of_suit="" source="resource.org" blocked="False" date_blocked="None" extracted_by_ocr="False" cited_by="101776">&lt;p class="case_cite"&gt;&lt;span class="citation no-link"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;282&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;818&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="case_cite"&gt;51 S.Ct. 23&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="case_cite"&gt;75 L.Ed. 731&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="parties"&gt;Hilary HALBERT, Jr., et al., petitioners,&lt;br&gt;v.&lt;br&gt;The UNITED STATES of America.  Rich HALBERT, a minor, etc., petitioner,  v.  The UNITED STATES of America.  Vernon Sidney HALBERT, a minor, etc., petitioner,  v.  The UNITED STATES of America.  Sidney E. HALBERT, a minor, etc., petitioner,  v.  The UNITED STATES of America.  Rose Peers PICKERNOLL et al., petitioners,  v.  The UNITED STATES of America.  Lulu M. ELLIOTT et al. petitioners,  v.  The UNITED STATES of America.  Mary Barichio PETIT et al., petitioners,  v.  The UNITED STATES of America.  Dewey BARICHIO et al., petitioners,  v.  The UNITED STATES of America.  Edna May ELLIOTT et al., petitioners,  v.  The UNITED STATES of America.  Chas. G. ELLIOTT, Jr., et al., petitioners,  v.  The UNITED STATES of America.  Agnes RUBENS et al., petitioners,  v.  The UNITED STATES of America.  Virginia WALKOWSKY et al., petitioners,  v.  The UNITED STATES of America.  Lizzie ROLFSON et al., petitioners,  v.  The UNITED STATES of America.  Mary Francis PROVOE et al., petitioners,  v.  The UNITED STATES of America.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="docket"&gt;No. 141.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="docket"&gt;No. 142.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="docket"&gt;No. 143.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="docket"&gt;No. 144.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="docket"&gt;No. 145.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="docket"&gt;No. 146.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="docket"&gt;No. 147.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="docket"&gt;No. 148.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="docket"&gt;No. 149.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="docket"&gt;No. 150.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="docket"&gt;No. 151.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="docket"&gt;No. 152.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="docket"&gt;No. 153.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="docket"&gt;No. 154.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="court"&gt;Supreme Court of the United States&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="date"&gt;October 13, 1930&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;div class="prelims"&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;Mr. Overton G. Ellis, of Tacoma, Wash., for petitioners.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="num" id="p1"&gt;
      &lt;span class="num"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;Petition for writs of certiorari to the United States Circuit Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit granted.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    </opinion>