<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><opinion id="105183" path="/scotus/xgv/superior-films-inc-appellant-v-department-of/" sha1="ee0ebbd2924057fab16afcde05feeea63edab917" court="Supreme Court of the United States" download_URL="http://bulk.resource.org/courts.gov/c/US/346/346.US.587.217.274.html" time_retrieved="2010-04-28 16:55:22+00:00" date_filed="1953-10-12" precedential_status="Published" local_path="" docket_number="Nos. 217, 274" federal_cite_one="346 U.S. 587" lexis_cite="" case_name="Superior Films, Inc. v. Department of Education of State of Ohio, Division of Film Censorship, Clyde Hissong, Supt. Commercial Pictures Corporation v. Regents of University of State of New York" judges="" nature_of_suit="" source="resource.org" blocked="False" date_blocked="None" extracted_by_ocr="False" cited_by="246428,245007,243369,236279,109159,108838,107871,107167,106987,106877,106267,106162,106142,105937">&lt;p class="case_cite"&gt;&lt;span class="citation no-link"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;346&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;587&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="case_cite"&gt;74 S.Ct. 286&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="case_cite"&gt;98 L.Ed. 329&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="parties"&gt;SUPERIOR FILMS, Inc., Appellant,&lt;br&gt;v.&lt;br&gt;DEPARTMENT OF EDUCATION OF STATE OF OHIO, DIVISION OF  FILM CENSORSHIP, Clyde Hissong, Supt.  COMMERCIAL PICTURES CORPORATION, Appellant,  v.  REGENTS OF UNIVERSITY OF STATE OF NEW YORK.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="docket"&gt;Nos. 217, 274.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="court"&gt;Supreme Court of the United States&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="date"&gt;January 18, 1954&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;div class="prelims"&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;PER CURIAM.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="num" id="p1"&gt;
      &lt;span class="num"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;The judgments are reversed. Joseph Burstyn, Inc. v. Wilson, &lt;span class="citation"&gt;&lt;a href="/scotus/xdA/joseph-burstyn-inc-v-wilson/"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;343&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;495&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, 72 S.Ct. 777, 96 L.Ed. 1098.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="num" id="p2"&gt;
      &lt;span class="num"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;Mr. Justice DOUGLAS, with whom Mr. Justice BLACK agrees, concurring.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="num" id="p3"&gt;
      &lt;span class="num"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;The argument of Ohio and New York that the government may establish censorship over moving pictures is one I cannot accept. In 1925 Minnesota passed a law aimed at suppressing before publication any 'malicious, scandalous and defamatory newspaper'.&lt;a class="footnote" href="#fn1" id="fn1_ref"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt; The Court, speaking through Chief Justice Hughes, struck down that law as violating the Fourteenth Amendment, which has made the First Amendment applicable to the States. Near v. State of Minnesota, &lt;span class="citation"&gt;&lt;a href="/scotus/wfH/near-v-minnesota-ex-rel-olson/"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;283&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;697&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, 51 S.Ct. 625, 626, 75 L.Ed. 1357. The 'chief purpose' of the constitutional guaranty of liberty of the press, said the Court, was 'to prevent previous restraints upon publication.' 283 US. at page 713, 51 S.Ct. at page 630.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="num" id="p4"&gt;
      &lt;span class="num"&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;The history of censorship is so well known it need not be summarized here. Certainly a system, still in force in some nations, which required a newspaper to submit to a board its news items, editorials, and cartoons before it published them could not be sustained. Nor could book publishers be required to submit their novels, poems, and tracts to censors for clearance before publication. Any such scheme of censorship would be in irreconciable conflict with the language and purpose of the First Amendment.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="num" id="p5"&gt;
      &lt;span class="num"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;Nor is it conceivable to me that producers of plays for the legitimate theatre or for television could be required to submit their manuscripts to censors on pain of penalty for producing them without approval. Certainly the spoken word is as freely protected against prior restraints as that which is written. Such indeed is the force of our decision in Thomas v. Collins, &lt;span class="citation"&gt;&lt;a href="/scotus/wWa/thomas-v-collins/"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;323&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;516&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, 540, 65 S.Ct. 315, 327, 89 L.Ed. 430. The freedom of the platform which it espouses carries with it freedom of the stage.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="num" id="p6"&gt;
      &lt;span class="num"&gt;6&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;The same result in the case of motion pictures necessarily follows as a consequence of our holding in Joseph Burstyn, Inc. v. Wilson, &lt;span class="citation"&gt;&lt;a href="/scotus/xdA/joseph-burstyn-inc-v-wilson/"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;343&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;495&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, 502, 72 S.Ct. 777, 780, 781, 96 L.Ed. 1098, that motion pictures are 'within the free speech and free press guaranty of the First and Fourteenth Amendments.'&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="num" id="p7"&gt;
      &lt;span class="num"&gt;7&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;Motion pictures are of course a different medium of expression than the public speech, the radio, the stage, the novel, or the magazine. But the First Amendment draws no distinction between the various methods of communicating ideas. On occasion one may be more powerful or effective than another. The movie, like the public speech, radio, or television is transitory here now and gone in an instant. The novel, the short story, the poem in printed form are permanently at hand to reenact the drama or to retell the story over and again. Which medium will give the most excitement and have the most enduring effect will vary with the theme and the actors. It is not for the censor to determine in any case. The First and the Fourteenth Amendments say that Congress and the States shall make 'no law' which abridges freedom of speech or of the press. In order to sanction a system of censorship I would have to say that 'no law' does not mean what it says, that 'no law' is qualified to mean 'some' laws. I cannot take that step.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="num" id="p8"&gt;
      &lt;span class="num"&gt;8&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;In this Nation every writer, actor, or producer, no matter what medium of expression he may use, should be freed from the censor.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="footnotes"&gt;
      &lt;div class="footnote" id="fn1"&gt;
        &lt;a class="footnote" href="#fn1_ref"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;p&gt; Laws 1925 Minn. c. 285, &amp;#167; 1(b).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    </opinion>