<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><opinion id="105379" path="/scotus/xjT/missouri-pacific-railroad-company-5-14-secured/" sha1="36f7cf731ec1abfc2f43d3db5acf509caf2eb9b4" court="Supreme Court of the United States" download_URL="http://bulk.resource.org/courts.gov/c/US/350/350.US.959.568.html" time_retrieved="2010-04-28 16:55:29+00:00" date_filed="1956-01-30" precedential_status="Published" local_path="" docket_number="568" federal_cite_one="350 U.S. 959" lexis_cite="" case_name="Missouri Pacific Railroad Company 5 1/4% Secured Serial Bondholders Committee v. Guy A. Thompson, Trustee, Missouri Pacific Railroad Company, Debtor" judges="" nature_of_suit="" source="resource.org" blocked="False" date_blocked="None" extracted_by_ocr="False">&lt;p class="case_cite"&gt;&lt;span class="citation no-link"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;350&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;959&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="case_cite"&gt;76 S.Ct. 347&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="case_cite"&gt;100 L.Ed. 833&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="parties"&gt;MISSOURI PACIFIC RAILROAD COMPANY 5 1/4% SECURED SERIAL  BONDHOLDERS COMMITTEE et al., petitioners,&lt;br&gt;v.&lt;br&gt;Guy A. THOMPSON, Trustee, Missouri Pacific Railroad  Company, Debtor, et al.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="docket"&gt;No. 568.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="court"&gt;Supreme Court of the United States&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="date"&gt;January 30, 1956&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;div class="prelims"&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;Mr. William H. Biggs, for petitioner Missouri Pacific Railroad Company 5 1/4% Secured Serial Bondholders Committee.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;Mr. Frederick M. Myers, for petitioners Huston and others.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;Messrs. Russell L. Dearmont and Thos. T. Railey, for Thompson and others.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;Messrs. Clair B. Hughes and Allan S. Kuller, for Manufacturers Trust Co.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;Messrs. DeLancey C. Smith, Henry I. Stimson and Forrest P. Tralles, for Protective Committee for Secured Serial 5 1/4% Gold Bonds of Missouri Pacific Railroad Co. and others.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;Messrs. David M. Potts and Abraham Wilson, for Empire Trust Co.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;Mr. Douglas B. Steimle, for Bondholders Protective Committee for Missouri Pacific Railroad Company General Mortgage Bonds.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;Messrs. William P. Palmer and James I. Wyer, for Bankers Trust Co.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;Messrs. Robert H. McRoberts and Thomas S. McPheeters, Jr., for St. Louis Union Trust Co.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;Mr. John M. MacGregor, for Protective Committee for Holders of Preferred Stock of Missouri Pacific Railroad Co.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;Messrs. Harold C. McCollom and G. Carroll Stribling, for Irving Trust Co.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;Messrs. Leonard D. Adkins and S. Mayner Wallace, for Savings Bank Trust Co.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;Messrs. Hugh L. M. Cole and William G. Pettus, Jr., for City Bank Farmers Trust Co.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;Messrs. Edward F. Colladay and Everett Paul Griffin, for Wright and others.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;Messrs. Walter H. Brown, Jr., and Allan F. Conwill, for New York Trust Co.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;Mr. Abraham K. Weber, for Rosenberger and others.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;Messrs. Felix A. Fishman and Lyonel E. Zunz for Oscar Gruss &amp;amp; Son.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;Messrs. Burton K. Wheeler, Edward K. Wheeler, and Eldon S. Olson, for Missouri Pacific Railroad Co.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;Mr. Percival E. Jackson, for Jackson and others.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;Mr. Emmet McCaffery, for Chemical Corn Exchange Bank.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;Mr. John L. J. Hart, for Alleghany Corporation.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;Petition for writ of certiorari to the United States Court of Appeals for the Eighth Circuit.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="num" id="p1"&gt;
      &lt;span class="num"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;Denied.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="num" id="p2"&gt;
      &lt;span class="num"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;Mr. Justice HARLAN took no part in the consideration or decision of this application.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    </opinion>