<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><opinion id="106637" path="/scotus/xGz/jones-chairman-of-navajo-tribal-council-of-navajo-/" sha1="e3f51534aecdc21f373ee637fe5d4584c03d8611" court="Supreme Court of the United States" time_retrieved="2010-04-28 17:10:45+00:00" date_filed="1963-06-03" precedential_status="Published" local_path="" docket_number="Nos. 985 and 1050" federal_cite_one="373 U.S. 758" case_name="Jones, Chairman of Navajo Tribal Council of Navajo Indian Tribe v. Healing, Chairman of Hopi Council of Hopi Indian Tribe" judges="Per Curiam" nature_of_suit="" source="lawbox merged with resource.org" blocked="False" date_blocked="None" extracted_by_ocr="False" cited_by="743644,704021,687689,566062,547651,525654,510168,468723,440415,431946,426036,425960,380394,377095,363150,355446,340101,321949,302111,300668,265973,182527">&lt;div&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span class="citation no-link"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;373&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;758&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; (1963)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h1&gt;JONES, CHAIRMAN OF NAVAJO TRIBAL COUNCIL OF NAVAJO INDIAN TRIBE,&lt;br&gt;
v.&lt;br&gt;
HEALING, CHAIRMAN OF HOPI COUNCIL OF HOPI INDIAN TRIBE, ET AL.&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;No. 985.&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Supreme Court of United States.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;Decided June 3, 1963.&lt;sup&gt;[*]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
APPEAL FROM THE UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT FOR THE DISTRICT OF ARIZONA.
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Norman M. Littell&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Frederick Bernays Wiener&lt;/i&gt; for appellant in No. 985 and for appellee Jones in No. 1050.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;John S. Boyden, Allen H. Tibbals&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Bryant H. Croft&lt;/i&gt; for appellants in No. 1050 and for appellee Healing in No. 985.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PER CURIAM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The motion to substitute Raymond Nakai in the place of Paul Jones as the party appellant in No. 985 and as a party appellee in No. 1050 is granted. The motion to substitute Abbott Sekaquaptewa in the place of Dewey Healing as a party appellee in No. 985 and as a party appellant in No. 1050 is granted. The motion to affirm in No. 985 is granted and the judgment which is common to both cases is affirmed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MR. JUSTICE DOUGLAS is of the opinion that probable jurisdiction should be noted and would decide the cases only after argument.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;NOTES&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[*]  Together with No. 1050, &lt;i&gt;Healing, Chairman of Hopi Tribal Council of Hopi Indian Tribe, et al.&lt;/i&gt; v. &lt;i&gt;Jones, Chairman of Navajo Tribal Council of Navajo Indian Tribe, et al.,&lt;/i&gt; on appeal from the same Court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;</opinion>