<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><opinion id="108022" path="/scotus/y7s/new-york-v-united-states/" sha1="69d34ad4f4d34ad4ec3fb82d0fe8e33e691d0e47" court="Supreme Court of the United States" time_retrieved="2010-04-28 17:11:20+00:00" date_filed="1970-01-19" precedential_status="Published" local_path="" docket_number="100" federal_cite_one="396 U.S. 281" case_name="New York v. United States" judges="Per Curiam" nature_of_suit="" source="lawbox merged with resource.org" blocked="False" date_blocked="None" extracted_by_ocr="False" cited_by="663074,588892,507089,157391,690297,354168,326979,312208,310947,197588">&lt;div&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span class="citation no-link"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;396&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;281&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; (1970)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h1&gt;NEW YORK&lt;br&gt;
v.&lt;br&gt;
UNITED STATES ET AL.&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;No. 100.&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Supreme Court of United States.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;Decided January 12, 1970.&lt;sup&gt;[*]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
APPEAL FROM THE UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT FOR THE NORTHERN DISTRICT OF NEW YORK.
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Louis J. Lefkowitz,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of New York, &lt;i&gt;Dunton F. Tynan,&lt;/i&gt; Assistant Solicitor General, and &lt;i&gt;Walter J. Myskowiski&lt;/i&gt; for appellant in No. 100. &lt;i&gt;Gordon P. MacDougall, William G. Mahoney,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;C. C. Sheldon,&lt;/i&gt; Assistant Attorney General of Nebraska, for appellants in No. 520.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Solicitor General Griswold, Assistant Attorney General McLaren, Robert W. Ginnane,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Jerome Nelson&lt;/i&gt; for the United States et al. in No. 100. &lt;i&gt;Solicitor General Griswold, Assistant Attorney General McLaren,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Fritz R. Kahn&lt;/i&gt; for the United States et al. in No. 520. &lt;i&gt;Wallace R. Steffen&lt;/i&gt; for Erie Lackawanna Railway Co., appellee in No. 100. &lt;i&gt;George G. Coughlin&lt;/i&gt; for Broome County Chamber of Commerce, appellee in No. 100, supporting the position of the appellant. &lt;i&gt;Howard J. Trienens&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Richard T. Cubbage&lt;/i&gt; for Chicago, Burlington &amp;amp; Quincy Railroad Co., appellee in No. 520.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PER CURIAM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The motions to affirm are granted and the judgments are affirmed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;NOTES&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[*]  Together with No. 520, &lt;i&gt;City of Sheridan et al.&lt;/i&gt; v. &lt;i&gt;United States et al.,&lt;/i&gt; on appeal from the United States District Court for the District of Wyoming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;</opinion>