<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><opinion id="108320" path="/scotus/ycA/moore-v-charlotte-mecklenburg-bd-of-ed/" sha1="b6d94eca232f3bfff2df24397509863093f7c553" court="Supreme Court of the United States" time_retrieved="2010-04-28 17:11:28+00:00" date_filed="1971-04-20" precedential_status="Published" local_path="" docket_number="444" federal_cite_one="402 U.S. 47" case_name="Moore v. Charlotte-Mecklenburg Bd. of Ed." judges="Per Curiam" nature_of_suit="" source="lawbox merged with resource.org" blocked="False" date_blocked="None" extracted_by_ocr="False" cited_by="2477354,880011,598971,567718,560436,458552,419627,402107,393163,392996,390354,365467,349552,333670,305616,297604,297605,297514,194512,177518,110227,110141,108587,108316,78179,78027">&lt;div&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span class="citation no-link"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;402&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;47&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; (1971)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h1&gt;MOORE ET AL.&lt;br&gt;
v.&lt;br&gt;
CHARLOTTE-MECKLENBURG BOARD OF EDUCATION ET AL.&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;No. 444.&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Supreme Court of United States.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;Argued October 13, 1970&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;Decided April 20, 1971&lt;/center&gt;
APPEAL FROM THE UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT FOR THE WESTERN DISTRICT OF NORTH CAROLINA.
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Whiteford S. Blakeney&lt;/i&gt; argued the cause for appellants. With him on the brief was &lt;i&gt;William H. Booe.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;William J. Waggoner&lt;/i&gt; argued the cause for appellees. With him on the brief was &lt;i&gt;Benjamin S. Horack.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Solicitor General Griswold&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Assistant Attorney General Leonard&lt;/i&gt; filed a brief for the United States as &lt;i&gt;amicus curiae.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PER CURIAM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Appellants seek review of the decision of the United States District Court for the Western District of North Carolina declaring a portion of the North Carolina anti-busing statute unconstitutional, and enjoining its enforcement. It is a companion case to No. 498, &lt;i&gt;North Carolina State Board of Education&lt;/i&gt; v. &lt;i&gt;Swann, ante,&lt;/i&gt; p. 43. We postponed decision on the question of jurisdiction, 400 U. S. 803 (1970), and after hearing on the merits we now dismiss the appeal for lack of jurisdiction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the hearing both parties argued to the three-judge court that the anti-busing law was constitutional and urged that the order of the District Court adopting the Finger plan should be set aside. We are thus confronted &lt;span class="star-pagination"&gt;*48&lt;/span&gt; with the anomaly that both litigants desire precisely the same result, namely a holding that the anti-busing statute is constitutional. There is, therefore, no case or controversy within the meaning of Art. III of the Constitution. &lt;i&gt;Muskrat&lt;/i&gt; v. &lt;i&gt;United States,&lt;/i&gt; 219 U. S. 346 (1911). Additionally, since neither party sought an injunction to restrain a state officer from enforcing a state statute alleged to be unconstitutional, 28 U. S. C. ยง 2281, this is not an appeal from "any civil action, suit or proceeding required . . . to be heard . . . by a district court of three judges," 28 U. S. C. ยง 1253, and hence no direct appeal to this Court is available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Dismissed.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</opinion>