<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><opinion id="108816" path="/scotus/ym9/fri-v-sierra-club/" sha1="7bd771495ade8c3f2ee9604b3daf1ece05aabf0e" court="Supreme Court of the United States" time_retrieved="2010-04-28 17:11:43+00:00" date_filed="1973-06-11" precedential_status="Published" local_path="" docket_number="72-804" federal_cite_one="412 U.S. 541" case_name="Fri v. Sierra Club" judges="Per Curiam" nature_of_suit="" source="lawbox merged with resource.org" blocked="False" date_blocked="None" extracted_by_ocr="False" cited_by="315791,1038028,538362,435062,423899,412021,406797,391039,389201,384927,371077,367154,367155,363949,354158,341608,338662,329305,328849,327168,326270,323867,131157">&lt;div&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span class="citation no-link"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;412&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;541&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; (1973)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h1&gt;FRI, ACTING ADMINISTRATOR, ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY&lt;br&gt;
v.&lt;br&gt;
SIERRA CLUB ET AL.&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;No. 72-804.&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Supreme Court of United States.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;Argued April 18, 1973.&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;Decided June 11, 1973.&lt;/center&gt;
CERTIORARI TO THE UNITED STATES COURT OF APPEALS FOR THE DISTRICT OF COLUMBIA CIRCUIT.
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Deputy Solicitor General Wallace&lt;/i&gt; argued the cause for petitioner. With him on the briefs were &lt;i&gt;Solicitor General Griswold, Assistant Attorney General Frizzell, Harriet S. Shapiro, Edmund B. Clark,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Martin Green.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Bruce J. Terris&lt;/i&gt; argued the cause for respondents. With him on the brief were &lt;i&gt;Helen C. Needham, Nathalie Vayssie Black,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;James W. Moorman.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[*]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="star-pagination"&gt;*542&lt;/span&gt; PER CURIAM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The judgment is affirmed by an equally divided Court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MR. JUSTICE POWELL took no part in the decision of this case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;NOTES&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[*]  Briefs of &lt;i&gt;amici curiae&lt;/i&gt; urging reversal were filed by &lt;i&gt;Mark Wilmer, Rex E. Lee, Gary K. Nelson,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General, &lt;i&gt;J. A. Hughes, John Conway, William Duncan, Gordon Pearce, Richard G. Campbell, Lawrence V. Robertson, Jr.,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Donald E. Dickerman,&lt;/i&gt; for the State of Arizona and Ten Named Public Utilities; by &lt;i&gt;Andrew P. Miller,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General, and &lt;i&gt;C. Tabor C. onk,&lt;/i&gt; Assistant Attorney General, for the Commonwealth of Virginia; by &lt;i&gt;Milton A. Smith&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Stanley W. Schroeder&lt;/i&gt; for the Chamber of Commerce of the United States; by &lt;i&gt;Cameron F. MacRae, G. S. Peter Bergen,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Henry V. Nickel&lt;/i&gt; for the Edison Electric Institute; and by &lt;i&gt;Edward A. McCabe, Laurence P. Sherfy,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;David W. Miller&lt;/i&gt; for the American Mining Congress.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Briefs of &lt;i&gt;amici curiae&lt;/i&gt; urging affirmance were filed by &lt;i&gt;Evelle J. Younger,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General, &lt;i&gt;pro se, Robert H. O'Brien,&lt;/i&gt; Assistant Attorney General, and &lt;i&gt;Nicholas C. Yost, Anthony M. Summers,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;C. Foster Knight,&lt;/i&gt; Deputy Attorneys General, for the Attorney General of California; by &lt;i&gt;William J. Scott,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General, &lt;i&gt;Fred F. Herzog,&lt;/i&gt; First Assistant Attorney General, and &lt;i&gt;Harvey M. Sheldon,&lt;/i&gt; Assistant Attorney General, for the State of Illinois; by &lt;i&gt;Frank J. Kelley,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General, &lt;i&gt;Robert A. Derengoski,&lt;/i&gt; Solicitor General, and &lt;i&gt;Jerome Maslowski, Stewart H. Freeman,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Charles S. Alpert,&lt;/i&gt; Assistant Attorney General, for the State of Michigan, joined by &lt;i&gt;Warren Spannaus,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General, and &lt;i&gt;Curtis D. Forslund,&lt;/i&gt; Solicitor General, for the State of Minnesota; by &lt;i&gt;Louis J. Lefkowitz,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General, &lt;i&gt;Samuel A. Hirshowitz,&lt;/i&gt; First Assistant Attorney General, and &lt;i&gt;Philip Weinberg&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;James P. Corcoran,&lt;/i&gt; Assistant Attorneys General, for the State of New York; by &lt;i&gt;John L. Hill,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General, &lt;i&gt;Larry F. York,&lt;/i&gt; First Assistant Attorney General, and &lt;i&gt;Mike Willatt, Phil Maxwell,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Troy C. Webb,&lt;/i&gt; Assistant Attorneys General, for the State of Texas; by &lt;i&gt;David L. Norvell,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General, for the State of New Mexico, joined by the Attorneys General for their respective States as follows: &lt;i&gt;William J. Baxley&lt;/i&gt; of Alabama, &lt;i&gt;Robert Killian&lt;/i&gt; of Connecticut, &lt;i&gt;Robert L. Shevin&lt;/i&gt; of Florida, &lt;i&gt;Vern Miller&lt;/i&gt; of Kansas, &lt;i&gt;William J. Guste, Jr.,&lt;/i&gt; of Louisiana, &lt;i&gt;Jon A. Lund&lt;/i&gt; of Maine, &lt;i&gt;Robert H. Quinn&lt;/i&gt; of Massachusetts, &lt;i&gt;Louis J. Lefkowitz&lt;/i&gt; of New York, &lt;i&gt;Robert Morgan&lt;/i&gt; of North Carolina, &lt;i&gt;William J. Brown&lt;/i&gt; of Ohio, &lt;i&gt;Lee L. Johnson&lt;/i&gt; of Oregon, &lt;i&gt;Israel Packel&lt;/i&gt; of Pennsylvania, &lt;i&gt;Kermit A. Sande&lt;/i&gt; of South Dakota, &lt;i&gt;John L. Hill&lt;/i&gt; of Texas, and &lt;i&gt;Kimberley B. Cheney&lt;/i&gt; of Vermont; by &lt;i&gt;Norman Redlich&lt;/i&gt; for the cities of New York and Boston; by &lt;i&gt;Alfred S. Forsyth&lt;/i&gt; for the Association of the Bar of the city of New York; by &lt;i&gt;David H. Getches&lt;/i&gt; for the Jicarilla Apache Tribe of Indians et al.; and by &lt;i&gt;Neal A. Jackson,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;James F. Bromley&lt;/i&gt; for Natural Resources Defense Council, Inc., et al.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;</opinion>