<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><opinion id="109567" path="/scotus/yz6/cook-v-hudson/" sha1="7fd85d08634e350b410fa2ed0c0a3ca0cf27adcd" court="Supreme Court of the United States" time_retrieved="2010-04-28 17:12:09+00:00" date_filed="1976-12-07" precedential_status="Published" local_path="" docket_number="75-503" federal_cite_one="429 U.S. 165" case_name="Cook v. Hudson" judges="Per Curiam" nature_of_suit="" source="lawbox merged with resource.org" blocked="False" date_blocked="None" extracted_by_ocr="False" cited_by="442183,425951,109652">&lt;div&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span class="citation no-link"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;429&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;165&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; (1976)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h1&gt;COOK ET AL.&lt;br&gt;
v.&lt;br&gt;
HUDSON ET AL.&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;No. 75-503.&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Supreme Court of United States.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;Argued November 1, 1976.&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;Decided December 7, 1976.&lt;/center&gt;
CERTIORARI TO THE UNITED STATES COURT OF APPEALS FOR THE FIFTH CIRCUIT.
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;George Colvin Cochran&lt;/i&gt; argued the cause and filed a brief for petitioners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Will A. Hickman&lt;/i&gt; argued the cause for respondents. With him on the brief was &lt;i&gt;S. T. Rayburn.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[*]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PER CURIAM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certiorari was granted to consider the question presented: whether, consistently with the First and Fourteenth Amendments, a Mississippi public school board may terminate the employment of teachers sending their children not to public schools, but to a private racially segregated school. However, since the grant of certiorari, &lt;i&gt;Runyon&lt;/i&gt; v. &lt;i&gt;McCrary,&lt;/i&gt; 427 U. S. 160 (1976), held that 42 U. S. C. ยง 1981 prohibits private, commercially operated, nonsectarian schools from denying admission to prospective students because they are Negroes. Moreover, a Mississippi statute, Miss. Code Ann. ยง 37-9-59 (Supp. 1976), enacted in 1974 after the school board action here complained of, prohibits school boards "from denying employment or reemployment to any person . . . for the single reason that any eligible child of such person &lt;span class="star-pagination"&gt;*166&lt;/span&gt; does not attend the school system in which such [person] is employed." Though ยง 37-9-59 was cited in the record at the time of granting the writ, examination of the merits on oral argument in light of &lt;i&gt;Runyon&lt;/i&gt; v. &lt;i&gt;McCrary&lt;/i&gt; and ยง 37-9-59 satisfies us that the grant was improvident. Accordingly, the writ of certiorari is dismissed as improvidently granted. Cf. &lt;i&gt;Rice&lt;/i&gt; v. &lt;i&gt;Sioux City Cemetery,&lt;/i&gt; 349 U. S. 70 (1955).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MR. CHIEF JUSTICE BURGER, concurring in the result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I join in the Court's disposition of this case. In doing so, I emphasize that our decision to dismiss the writ of certiorari as improvidently granted intimates no view on the question of when, if ever, public school teachers&#x97;or any comparable public employees&#x97;may be required, as a condition of their employment, to enroll their children in any particular school or refrain from sending them to a school which they, as parents, in their sole discretion, consider desirable. Few familial decisions are as immune from governmental interference as parents' choice of a school for their children, so long as the school chosen otherwise meets the educational standards imposed by the State. See &lt;i&gt;Pierce&lt;/i&gt; v. &lt;i&gt;Society of Sisters,&lt;/i&gt; 268 U. S. 510 (1925); &lt;i&gt;Meyer&lt;/i&gt; v. &lt;i&gt;Nebraska,&lt;/i&gt; 262 U. S. 390 (1923); &lt;i&gt;Wisconsin&lt;/i&gt; v. &lt;i&gt;Yoder,&lt;/i&gt; 406 U. S. 205 (1972).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;NOTES&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[*]  &lt;i&gt;Stephen J. Pollak, John Townsend Rich, Franklin D. Kramer,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;David Rubin&lt;/i&gt; filed a brief for the National Education Assn. as &lt;i&gt;amicus curiae&lt;/i&gt; urging reversal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;</opinion>