<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><opinion id="110672" path="/scotus/yU9/american-medical-assn-v-ftc/" sha1="bdb7b555ca8c8ed8a812fe83d1172a9d2c8173e5" court="Supreme Court of the United States" download_URL="/sata/lawbox/dump/gov.us.courts.united_states_reports/1st/455/American_Medical_Assn._v._FTC,_455_US_676.html" time_retrieved="2010-04-28 17:12:42+00:00" date_filed="1982-03-24" precedential_status="Published" local_path="" docket_number="80-1690" federal_cite_one="455 U.S. 676" case_name="American Medical Assn. v. FTC" judges="Per Curiam" nature_of_suit="" source="lawbox merged with resource.org" blocked="False" date_blocked="None" extracted_by_ocr="False" cited_by="747684,430915,118293">&lt;div&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span class="citation no-link"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;455&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;676&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; (1982)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h1&gt;AMERICAN MEDICAL ASSOCIATION ET AL.&lt;br&gt;
v.&lt;br&gt;
FEDERAL TRADE COMMISSION.&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;No. 80-1690.&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Supreme Court of United States.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;Argued January 11, 1982&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;Decided March 23, 1982&lt;/center&gt;
CERTIORARI TO THE UNITED STATES COURT OF APPEALS FOR THE SECOND CIRCUIT.
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Newton N. Minow&lt;/i&gt; argued the cause for petitioners. With him on the briefs were &lt;i&gt;Jack R. Bierig, David W. Carpenter, William J. Doyle,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Linda L. Randell.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Howard E. Shapiro&lt;/i&gt; argued the cause for respondent. With him on the brief were &lt;i&gt;Solicitor General Lee, Assistant Attorney General Baxter, Deputy Solicitor General Shapiro, Elliott Schulder, March Coleman,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;L. Barry Costilo.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[*]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PER CURIAM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The judgment is affirmed by an equally divided Court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="star-pagination"&gt;*677&lt;/span&gt; JUSTICE BLACKMUN took no part in the consideration or decision of this case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;NOTES&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[*]  &lt;i&gt;Peter M. Sfikas&lt;/i&gt; filed a brief for the American Dental Association as &lt;i&gt;amicus curiae&lt;/i&gt; urging reversal.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A brief for the State of Ohio et al. as &lt;i&gt;amici curiae&lt;/i&gt; urging affirmance was filed by &lt;i&gt;William J. Brown,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Ohio, and &lt;i&gt;Eugene F. McShane, Charles D. Weller,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Clifton E. Johnson,&lt;/i&gt; Assistant Attorneys General; &lt;i&gt;Robert K. Corbin,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Arizona; &lt;i&gt;J. D. MacFarlane,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Colorado, and &lt;i&gt;Thomas P. McMahon,&lt;/i&gt; Assistant Attorney General; &lt;i&gt;Carl R. Ajello,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Connecticut, and &lt;i&gt;Robert M. Langer&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;John R. Lacey,&lt;/i&gt; Assistant Attorneys General; &lt;i&gt;Thomas J. Miller,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Iowa, and &lt;i&gt;John R. Perkins,&lt;/i&gt; Assistant Attorney General; &lt;i&gt;Stephen H. Sachs,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Maryland, and &lt;i&gt;Charles O. Monk II&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Naomi F. Samet,&lt;/i&gt; Assistant Attorneys General; &lt;i&gt;Warren Spannaus,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Minnesota, and &lt;i&gt;Stephen P. Kilgriff,&lt;/i&gt; Special Assistant Attorney General; &lt;i&gt;Paul L. Douglas,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Nebraska, and &lt;i&gt;Dale A. Comer,&lt;/i&gt; Assistant Attorney General; &lt;i&gt;Jeff Bingaman,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of New Mexico, and &lt;i&gt;James J. Wechsler&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Richard H. Levin,&lt;/i&gt; Assistant Attorneys General; &lt;i&gt;Robert Abrams,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of New York, and &lt;i&gt;Lloyd Constantine,&lt;/i&gt; Assistant Attorney General; &lt;i&gt;Rufus L. Edmisten,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of North Carolina, &lt;i&gt;H. A. Cole, Jr.,&lt;/i&gt; Special Deputy Attorney General, and &lt;i&gt;Fred R. Gamin,&lt;/i&gt; Assistant Attorney General; &lt;i&gt;Leroy S. Zimmerman,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Pennsylvania, and &lt;i&gt;Carl S. Hisiro,&lt;/i&gt; Deputy Attorney General; &lt;i&gt;Dennis J. Roberts II,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Rhode Island, and &lt;i&gt;Patrick J. Quinlan,&lt;/i&gt; Special Assistant Attorney General; and &lt;i&gt;Chauncey H. Browning,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of West Virginia, and &lt;i&gt;Charles G. Brown,&lt;/i&gt; Deputy Attorney General.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;</opinion>