<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><opinion id="111079" path="/scotus/z2a/international-brotherhood-of-electrical-workers/" sha1="f44bf6e9bbbf59ab7ed5853401fdf336153125da" court="Supreme Court of the United States" download_URL="http://bulk.resource.org/courts.gov/c/US/464/464.US.950.83-63.html" time_retrieved="2010-04-28 17:12:54+00:00" date_filed="1983-10-31" precedential_status="Published" local_path="" docket_number="83-63" federal_cite_one="464 U.S. 950" lexis_cite="" case_name="International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers, Local Union No. 323, Afl-Cio v. National Labor Relations Board" judges="" nature_of_suit="" source="resource.org" blocked="False" date_blocked="None" extracted_by_ocr="False" cited_by="1147495,1146657,1143867,1107802,588801,530288,475283,467889,463479">&lt;p class="case_cite"&gt;&lt;span class="citation no-link"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;464&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;950&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="case_cite"&gt;104 S.Ct. 366&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="case_cite"&gt;78 L.Ed.2d 326&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="parties"&gt;INTERNATIONAL BROTHERHOOD OF ELECTRICAL WORKERS, LOCAL  UNION NO. 323, AFL-CIO&lt;br&gt;v.&lt;br&gt;NATIONAL LABOR RELATIONS BOARD&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="docket"&gt;No. 83-63&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="court"&gt;Supreme Court of the United States&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="date"&gt;October 31, 1983&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;div class="prelims"&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;On petition for writ of certiorari to the United States Court of Appeals for the Eleventh Circuit.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;The petition for writ of certiorari is denied.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;Justice WHITE, with whom Justice BRENNAN and Justice BLACKMUN join, dissenting from denial of certiorari.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="num" id="p1"&gt;
      &lt;span class="num"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;After determining that one of its members was working in a supervisory capacity for a nonunion employer, Local No. 323 of the International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers (IBEW) charged the employee with violating the IBEW constitution.  That document provides that a member may be penalized for "[w]orking in the interest of any organization or cause which is detrimental to, or opposed to, the IBEW."  The employee was fined and ultimately expelled from the union.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="num" id="p2"&gt;
      &lt;span class="num"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;The National Labor Relations Board charged the Local with an unfair labor practice for violating &amp;#167; 8(b)(1)(B) of the National Labor Relations Act, 29 U.S.C. &amp;#167; 158(b)(1)(B), which provides in pertinent part that "[i]t shall be an unfair labor practice for a labor organization or its agents&amp;#8212;(1) to restrain or coerce . . . (B) an employer in the selection of his representatives for the purposes of collective bargaining or the adjustment of grievances."  After a hearing, the administrative law judge found that the discipline was imposed for "working for a nonunion contractor," which in his view constituted unlawful coercion.  On review, the Board adopted the administrative law judge's findings and conclusions.  It issued a cease-and-desist order and ordered various affirmative relief.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="num" id="p3"&gt;
      &lt;span class="num"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;The Board then successfully petitioned the Court of Appeals for the Eleventh Circuit for enforcement of its order.  The court noted that in &lt;i&gt;NLRB v. International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers, Local 73 (Chewelah Contractor's, Inc.),&lt;/i&gt; &lt;span class="citation"&gt;&lt;a href="/ca9/2Wqg/national-labor-relations-board-v-international-bro/"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;621&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;F.2d&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;1035&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; (1980), the Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit had held that a union does not violate &amp;#167; 8(b)(1)(B) by disciplining a member-supervisor for his employment with a nonunion company if the union neither represents the company's employees nor displays a representational interest in them.  The Eleventh Circuit declined to adopt the Ninth Circuit's interpretation of the statute, stating that it found the &lt;i&gt;Chewelah&lt;/i&gt; limitation inconsistent with the statute's central aim.  It held that regardless of whether the union displays a representational interest in the company's employees, an attempt to force a member-supervisor to cease working for a nonunion company infringes the employer's right to select that person as its representative.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="num" id="p4"&gt;
      &lt;span class="num"&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;The conflict between the Ninth Circuit and the Eleventh Circuit is clear.  Identical action by a union will constitute an unfair labor practice in the Eleventh Circuit but not in the Ninth.  Implementation of the national labor policy is hampered by such conflicting rules.  Accordingly, I would grant the petition to settle the conflict.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    </opinion>