<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><opinion id="111386" path="/scotus/z7s/board-of-ed-of-oklahoma-city-v-national-gay-task-f/" sha1="54289a3e0e391d9532c8a69fd6cfacfa80cdba9e" court="Supreme Court of the United States" download_URL="/sata/lawbox/dump/gov.us.courts.united_states_reports/1st/470/Board_of_Ed._of_Oklahoma_City_v._National_Gay_Task_Force,_470_US_903.html" time_retrieved="2010-04-28 17:13:11+00:00" date_filed="1985-03-26" precedential_status="Published" local_path="" docket_number="83-2030" federal_cite_one="470 U.S. 903" case_name="Board of Ed. of Oklahoma City v. National Gay Task Force" judges="Per Curiam" nature_of_suit="" source="lawbox merged with resource.org" blocked="False" date_blocked="None" extracted_by_ocr="False" cited_by="810546,747620,695545,591476,523620,509653,506634,500686">&lt;div&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span class="citation no-link"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;470&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;903&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; (1985)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h1&gt;BOARD OF EDUCATION OF OKLAHOMA CITY&lt;br&gt;
v.&lt;br&gt;
NATIONAL GAY TASK FORCE&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;No. 83-2030.&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Supreme Court of United States.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;Argued January 14, 1985&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;Decided March 26, 1985&lt;/center&gt;
APPEAL FROM THE UNITED STATES COURT OF APPEALS FOR THE TENTH CIRCUIT
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Dennis W. Arrow&lt;/i&gt; argued the cause for appellant. With him on the briefs were &lt;i&gt;Larry Lewis&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;James B. Croy.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Laurence H. Tribe&lt;/i&gt; argued the cause for appellee. With him on the brief were &lt;i&gt;William B. Rogers&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Leonard Graff.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[*]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PER CURIAM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The judgment is affirmed by an equally divided Court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;JUSTICE POWELL took no part in the decision of this case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;NOTES&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[*]  Briefs of &lt;i&gt;amici curiae&lt;/i&gt; urging reversal were filed for Concerned Women for America Education and Legal Defense Foundation by &lt;i&gt;Jordan W. Lorence;&lt;/i&gt; for the State of Oklahoma by &lt;i&gt;Michael C. Turpen,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General, and &lt;i&gt;David W. Lee,&lt;/i&gt; Assistant Attorney General; for the National School Boards Association by &lt;i&gt;Gwendolyn H. Gregory, August W. Steinhilber,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Thomas A. Shannon;&lt;/i&gt; and for the Washington Legal Foundation by &lt;i&gt;Daniel J. Popeo, Paul D. Kamenar,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;George C. Smith.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Briefs of &lt;i&gt;amici curiae&lt;/i&gt; urging affirmance were filed for the American Association for Personal Privacy et al. by &lt;i&gt;Thomas F. Coleman&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Jay M. Kohorn;&lt;/i&gt; for the American Association of University Professors by &lt;i&gt;Ann H. Franke, Ralph S. Brown,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Matthew Finkin;&lt;/i&gt; for the Center for Constitutional Rights et al. by &lt;i&gt;Anne E. Simon, Sarah Wunsch,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Rhonda Copelon;&lt;/i&gt; for the Lambda Legal Defense and Education Fund, Inc., et al. by &lt;i&gt;Abby R. Rubenfeld&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Rosalyn Richter;&lt;/i&gt; for the National Education Association et al. by &lt;i&gt;Robert Chanin&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Robert M. Weinberg;&lt;/i&gt; and for the State of New York et al. by &lt;i&gt;Robert Abrams,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of New York, &lt;i&gt;Robert Hermann,&lt;/i&gt; Solicitor General, &lt;i&gt;Lawrence S. Kahn,&lt;/i&gt; Assistant Attorney General, and &lt;i&gt;John K. Van de Kamp,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of California.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;</opinion>