<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><opinion id="111401" path="/scotus/z7H/spencer-v-south-carolina-tax-commn/" sha1="3b2ff94021db32df41239916c2a10e39480d2457" court="Supreme Court of the United States" download_URL="/sata/lawbox/dump/gov.us.courts.united_states_reports/1st/471/Spencer_v._South_Carolina_Tax_Comm'n,_471_US_82.html" time_retrieved="2010-04-28 17:13:13+00:00" date_filed="1985-05-13" precedential_status="Published" local_path="" docket_number="84-249" federal_cite_one="471 U.S. 82" case_name="Spencer v. South Carolina Tax Comm'n" judges="Per Curiam" nature_of_suit="" source="lawbox merged with resource.org" blocked="False" date_blocked="None" extracted_by_ocr="False" cited_by="118165,112534">&lt;div&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span class="citation no-link"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;471&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;82&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; (1985)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h1&gt;SPENCER ET UX.&lt;br&gt;
v.&lt;br&gt;
SOUTH CAROLINA TAX COMMISSION ET AL.&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;No. 84-249.&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Supreme Court of United States.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;Argued February 27, 1985&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;Decided March 27, 1985&lt;/center&gt;
CERTIORARI TO THE SUPREME COURT OF SOUTH CAROLINA
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Henry L. Parr, Jr.,&lt;/i&gt; argued the cause for petitioners. With him on the briefs were &lt;i&gt;Eric B. Amstutz&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Frank S. Holleman III.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Ray N. Stevens,&lt;/i&gt; Senior Assistant Attorney General of South Carolina, argued the cause for respondents. With him on the brief were &lt;i&gt;T. Travis Medlock,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General, and &lt;i&gt;Joe L. Allen, Jr.,&lt;/i&gt; Chief Deputy Attorney General.&lt;sup&gt;[*]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PER CURIAM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The judgment is affirmed by an equally divided Court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;JUSTICE POWELL took no part in the decision of this case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;NOTES&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[*]  Briefs of &lt;i&gt;amici curiae&lt;/i&gt; urging affirmance were filed for the State of Alaska et al. by &lt;i&gt;Francis X. Bellotti,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Massachusetts, &lt;i&gt;Thomas R. Kiley,&lt;/i&gt; First Assistant Attorney General, &lt;i&gt;Judith S. Yogman,&lt;/i&gt; Assistant Attorney General, &lt;i&gt;Norman Gorsuch,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Alaska, &lt;i&gt;Steve Clark,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Arkansas, &lt;i&gt;Duane Woodard,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Colorado, &lt;i&gt;Jim Jones,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Idaho, &lt;i&gt;Thomas J. Miller,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Iowa, &lt;i&gt;David L. Armstrong,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Kentucky, &lt;i&gt;Alex W. Rose,&lt;/i&gt; Assistant Attorney General, &lt;i&gt;Stephan H. Sachs,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Maryland, &lt;i&gt;Hubert H. Humphrey III,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Minnesota, &lt;i&gt;Brian McKay,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Nevada, &lt;i&gt;Peter W. Mosseau,&lt;/i&gt; Acting Attorney General of New Hampshire, &lt;i&gt;Robert O. Wefald,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of North Dakota, &lt;i&gt;Anthony J. Celebrezze, Jr.,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Ohio, &lt;i&gt;LeRoy S. Zimmerman,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Pennsylvania, and &lt;i&gt;Mark V. Meierhenry,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of South Dakota; and for the Council of State Governments et al. by &lt;i&gt;Joyce Holmes Benjamin.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;</opinion>