<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><opinion id="111532" path="/scotus/z9Y/commonwealth-of-kentucky-v-state-of-indiana-et-al/" sha1="a2dd50a2518af0c8259c41ba7f61005d9d034a83" court="Supreme Court of the United States" download_URL="http://bulk.resource.org/courts.gov/c/US/474/474.US.1.81.html" time_retrieved="2010-04-28 17:13:17+00:00" date_filed="1985-11-04" precedential_status="Published" local_path="" docket_number="81" federal_cite_one="474 U.S. 1" lexis_cite="" case_name="Commonwealth of Kentucky v. State of Indiana" judges="" nature_of_suit="" source="resource.org" blocked="False" date_blocked="None" extracted_by_ocr="False" cited_by="1080875">&lt;p class="case_cite"&gt;&lt;span class="citation no-link"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;474&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="case_cite"&gt;106 S.Ct. 304&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="case_cite"&gt;88 L.Ed.2d 1&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="parties"&gt;Commonwealth of KENTUCKY&lt;br&gt;v.&lt;br&gt;State of INDIANA et al.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="docket"&gt;No. 81&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="court"&gt;Supreme Court of the United States&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="date"&gt;November 4, 1985&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;div class="num" id="p1"&gt;
      &lt;span class="num"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;On Bill of Complaint.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="num" id="p2"&gt;
      &lt;span class="num"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;The Report of the Special Master is received and ordered filed.  The parties having waived the right to file Exceptions, the Report is adopted.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;DECREE&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="indent"&gt;It is ordered, adjudged, and decreed that:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;div class="num" id="p3"&gt;
      &lt;span class="num"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;1. The boundary line between the State of Indiana and the Commonwealth of Kentucky is fixed as geodetically described in Joint Exhibit 50 to the Special Master's Report filed with this Court on November 4, 1985.  Joint Exhibit 50 is incorporated by reference herein.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="num" id="p4"&gt;
      &lt;span class="num"&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;2. Copies of this Decree and the Special Master's Report (including Joint Exhibits 1-50, inclusive) shall be filed with the Clerk of this Court, the Archives Division of the Indiana Commission on Public Records of Indiana, and the Secretary of State of the Commonwealth of Kentucky.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="num" id="p5"&gt;
      &lt;span class="num"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;3. Copies of this Decree and the Special Master's Report (including Joint Exhibit 50 and paper prints of Joint Exhibits 1-49, inclusive, once they become available) shall be filed with the Office of the County Recorder in each of the following Indiana counties:  the counties of Posey, Vanderburgh, Warrick, Spencer, Perry, Crawford, Harrison, Floyd, Clark, Jefferson, Switzerland, Ohio, and Dearborn;  and with the County Clerk's Office in the Commonwealth of Kentucky in each of the following Kentucky counties:  the counties of Union, Henderson, Daviess, Hancock, Breckinridge, Meade, Hardin, Jefferson, Oldham, Trimble, Carroll, Gallatin, and Boone.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="num" id="p6"&gt;
      &lt;span class="num"&gt;6&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;4. The State of Indiana and the Commonwealth of Kentucky each have concurrent jurisdiction over the Ohio River.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="num" id="p7"&gt;
      &lt;span class="num"&gt;7&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;5. The costs of this proceeding shall be divided between the parties as recommended by the Special Master.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    </opinion>