<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><opinion id="112526" path="/scotus/zs7/ohio-v-huertas/" sha1="6b2e69600affb6e0b63ea9de2d5971de552065ac" court="Supreme Court of the United States" download_URL="/sata/lawbox/dump/gov.us.courts.united_states_reports/1st/498/Ohio_v._Huertas,_498_US_336.html" time_retrieved="2010-04-28 17:13:45+00:00" date_filed="1991-02-19" precedential_status="Published" local_path="" docket_number="89-1944" federal_cite_one="498 U.S. 336" case_name="Ohio v. Huertas" judges="Per Curiam" nature_of_suit="" source="lawbox merged with resource.org" blocked="False" date_blocked="None" extracted_by_ocr="False" cited_by="112643">&lt;div&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span class="citation no-link"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;498&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;336&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; (1991)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h1&gt;OHIO&lt;br&gt;
v.&lt;br&gt;
HUERTAS&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;No. 89-1944.&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Supreme Court of the United States.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;Argued January 16, 1991.&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;Decided January 22, 1991.&lt;/center&gt;
CERTIORARI TO THE SUPREME COURT OF OHIO
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Jonathan E. Rosenbaum&lt;/i&gt; argued the cause and filed a brief for petitioner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Joann Bour-Stokes,&lt;/i&gt; by appointment of the Court, &lt;i&gt;post,&lt;/i&gt; p. 935, argued the cause for respondent. With her on the brief were &lt;i&gt;Randall M. Dana, Davis C. Stebbins,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Richard J. Vickers.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[*]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PER CURIAM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The writ of certiorari is dismissed as improvidently granted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;NOTES&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[*]  Briefs of &lt;i&gt;amici curiae&lt;/i&gt; urging reversal were filed for the United States by &lt;i&gt;Solicitor General Starr, Assistant Attorney General Mueller, Deputy Solicitor General Bryson,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Paul J. Larkin, Jr.;&lt;/i&gt; and for the Washington Legal Foundation et al. by &lt;i&gt;Daniel J. Popeo&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Paul D. Kamenar.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Briefs of &lt;i&gt;amici curiae&lt;/i&gt; urging affirmance were filed for the National Jury Project by &lt;i&gt;Samuel R. Gross;&lt;/i&gt; for the National Legal Aid and Defender Association by &lt;i&gt;Jennifer P. Lyman;&lt;/i&gt; and for Barbara Babcock et al. by &lt;i&gt;Louis D. Bilionis&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Richard A. Rosen.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Briefs of &lt;i&gt;amici curiae&lt;/i&gt; were filed for the State of California by &lt;i&gt;John K. Van de Kamp,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General, &lt;i&gt;Richard B. Iglehart,&lt;/i&gt; Chief Assistant Attorney General, &lt;i&gt;Harley D. Mayfield,&lt;/i&gt; Senior Assistant Attorney General, &lt;i&gt;Frederick R. Millar,&lt;/i&gt; Supervising Deputy Attorney General, and &lt;i&gt;Jay M. Bloom,&lt;/i&gt; Deputy Attorney General; for the Appellate Committee of the California District Attorneys Association by &lt;i&gt;Ira Reiner, Harry B. Sondheim,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Martha E. Bellinger;&lt;/i&gt; for Murder Victims' Families for Reconciliation by &lt;i&gt;Vivian Berger;&lt;/i&gt; and for the National Association of Criminal Defense Lawyers et al. by &lt;i&gt;Margery Malkin Koosed, Harry R. Reinhart,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Dennis Balske.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;</opinion>