<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><opinion id="117951" path="/scotus/B4D/kimberlin-v-quinlan/" sha1="5e595831f9e3058e7e3ebd15ddfc9cfa8b2e55f4" court="Supreme Court of the United States" download_URL="/sata/lawbox/dump/gov.us.courts.united_states_reports/1st/515/Kimberlin_v._Quinlan,_515_US_321.html" time_retrieved="2010-04-28 17:20:19+00:00" date_filed="1995-06-12" precedential_status="Published" local_path="" docket_number="93-2068" federal_cite_one="515 U.S. 321" case_name="Kimberlin v. Quinlan" judges="Per Curiam" nature_of_suit="" source="lawbox merged with resource.org" blocked="False" date_blocked="None" extracted_by_ocr="False" cited_by="792859,778526,187157,184064,759120,185017">&lt;div&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span class="citation no-link"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;515&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;321&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; (1995)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h1&gt;KIMBERLIN&lt;br&gt;
v.&lt;br&gt;
QUINLAN et al.&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;No. 93-2068.&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;United States Supreme Court.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;Argued April 26, 1995.&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;Decided June 12, 1995.&lt;/center&gt;
CERTIORARI TO THE UNITED STATES COURT OF APPEALS FOR THE DISTRICT OF COLUMBIA CIRCUIT
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Howard T. Rosenblatt&lt;/i&gt; argued the cause for petitioner. With him on the briefs were &lt;i&gt;Jerrold J. Ganzfried&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Ellen S. Winter.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Deputy Solicitor General Bender&lt;/i&gt; argued the cause for the United States as &lt;i&gt;amicus curiae&lt;/i&gt; urging reversal. With him on the brief were &lt;i&gt;Solicitor General Days, Assistant Attorney General Hunger,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Cornelia T. L. Pillard.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Michael L. Martinez&lt;/i&gt; argued the cause for respondents. With him on the brief were &lt;i&gt;Steven D. Gordon&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;William J. Dempster.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[*]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="star-pagination"&gt;*322&lt;/span&gt; Per Curiam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The judgment is vacated, and the case is remanded to the United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit for further consideration in light of &lt;i&gt;Johnson&lt;/i&gt; v. &lt;i&gt;Jones, ante,&lt;/i&gt; p. 304.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;NOTES&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[]   Briefs of &lt;i&gt;amici curiae&lt;/i&gt; urging reversal were filed for the State of Maryland et al. by &lt;i&gt;J. Joseph Curran, Jr.,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Maryland, and &lt;i&gt;Andrew H. Baida&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Lawrence P. Fletcher-Hill,&lt;/i&gt; Assistant Attorneys General, &lt;i&gt;Jeff Sessions,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Alabama, &lt;i&gt;Bruce M. Botelho,&lt;/i&gt;  Attorney General of Alaska, &lt;i&gt;Grant Woods,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Arizona, &lt;i&gt;Winston Bryant,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Arkansas, &lt;i&gt;Daniel E. Lungren,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of California, &lt;i&gt;Gale A. Norton,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Colorado, &lt;i&gt;Richard Blumenthal,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Connecticut, &lt;i&gt;M. Jane Brady,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Delaware, &lt;i&gt;Garland Pinkston, Jr.,&lt;/i&gt; Acting Corporation Counsel of the District of Columbia, &lt;i&gt;Michael J. Bowers,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Georgia, &lt;i&gt;Calvin E. Holloway, Sr.,&lt;/i&gt; Acting Attorney General of Guam, &lt;i&gt;Margery S. Bronster,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Hawaii, &lt;i&gt;Alan G. Lance,&lt;/i&gt;  Attorney General of Idaho, &lt;i&gt;James E. Ryan,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Illinois, &lt;i&gt;Pamela Carter,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Indiana, &lt;i&gt;Thomas J. Miller,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Iowa, &lt;i&gt;Carla J. Stovall,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Kansas, &lt;i&gt;Chris Gorman,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Kentucky, &lt;i&gt;Richard P. Ieyoub,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Louisiana, &lt;i&gt;Scott Harshbarger,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Massachusetts, &lt;i&gt;Frank J. Kelley,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Michigan, &lt;i&gt;Hubert H. Humphrey III,&lt;/i&gt;  Attorney General of Minnesota, &lt;i&gt;Mike Moore,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Mississippi, &lt;i&gt;Jeremiah W. (Jay) Nixon,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Missouri, &lt;i&gt;Joseph P. Mazurek,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Montana, &lt;i&gt;Don Stenberg,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Nebraska, &lt;i&gt;Frankie Sue Del Papa,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Nevada, &lt;i&gt;Jeffrey R. Howard,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of New Hampshire, &lt;i&gt;Deborah T. Poritz,&lt;/i&gt;  Attorney General of New Jersey, &lt;i&gt;Tom Udall,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of New Mexico, &lt;i&gt;Michael F. Easley,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of North Carolina, &lt;i&gt;Heidi Heitkamp,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of North Dakota, &lt;i&gt;Betty D. Montgomery,&lt;/i&gt;  Attorney General of Ohio, &lt;i&gt;W. A. Drew Edmondson,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Oklahoma, &lt;i&gt;Theodore R. Kulongoski,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Oregon, &lt;i&gt;Ernest D. Preate, Jr.,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Pennsylvania, &lt;i&gt;Pedro Pierluisi,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Puerto Rico, &lt;i&gt;Jeffrey B. Pine,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Rhode Island, &lt;i&gt;Charles Molony Condon,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of South Carolina, &lt;i&gt;Mark Barnett,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of South Dakota, &lt;i&gt;Dan Morales,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Texas, &lt;i&gt;Jan Graham,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Utah, &lt;i&gt;Jeffrey L. Amestoy,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Vermont, &lt;i&gt;James S. Gilmore III,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Virginia, &lt;i&gt;Christine O. Gregoire,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Washington, &lt;i&gt;James E. Doyle,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Wisconsin, and &lt;i&gt;Joseph B. Meyer,&lt;/i&gt;  Attorney General of Wyoming; and for the International City/County Management Association et al. by &lt;i&gt;Richard Ruda&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Lee Fennell.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[*]   &lt;i&gt;Anthony C. Epstein, Steven R. Shapiro, Arthur B. Spitzer, Leslie A. Brueckner,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Marc D. Stern&lt;/i&gt; filed a brief for the American Civil Liberties Union et al. as &lt;i&gt;amici curiae&lt;/i&gt; urging reversal.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A brief of &lt;i&gt;amici curiae&lt;/i&gt; urging affirmance was filed for the State of Hawaii et al. by &lt;i&gt;Margery S. Bronster,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Hawaii, and &lt;i&gt;Girard D. Lau,&lt;/i&gt; Deputy Attorney General, &lt;i&gt;Winston Bryant,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Arkansas, &lt;i&gt;Daniel E. Lungren,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of California, &lt;i&gt;M. Jane Brady,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Delaware, &lt;i&gt;Alan G. Lance,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Idaho, &lt;i&gt;Pamela Carter,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Indiana, &lt;i&gt;Carla J. Stovall,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Kansas, &lt;i&gt;Chris Gorman,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Kentucky, &lt;i&gt;Hubert H. Humphrey III,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Minnesota, &lt;i&gt;Mike Moore,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Mississippi, &lt;i&gt;Jeremiah W. Nixon,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Missouri, &lt;i&gt;Joseph P. Mazurek,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Montana, &lt;i&gt;Jeffrey R. Howard,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of New Hampshire, &lt;i&gt;Victoria A. Graffeo,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of New York, &lt;i&gt;Betty D. Montgomery,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Ohio, &lt;i&gt;Drew Edmondson,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Oklahoma, &lt;i&gt;Jeffrey B. Pine,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Rhode Island, &lt;i&gt;Mark Barnett,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of South Dakota, &lt;i&gt;Jan Graham,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Utah, &lt;i&gt;Jeffrey L. Amestoy,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Vermont, &lt;i&gt;James S. Gilmore III,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Virginia, &lt;i&gt;James E. Doyle,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Wisconsin, &lt;i&gt;Richard Weil,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands, and &lt;i&gt;Alva A. Swan,&lt;/i&gt; Acting Attorney General of the Virgin Islands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;</opinion>