<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><opinion id="1527677" path="/scotus/8Q8g/kolden-v-selective-serv-local-bd-no-4/" sha1="630e82ed363334fa86d1b009cf83ce4d24acc65e" court="Supreme Court of the United States" time_retrieved="2013-10-30 06:35:22.415098+00:00" date_filed="1970-02-24" precedential_status="Published" local_path="" docket_number="70" federal_cite_one="397 U.S. 47" case_name="Kolden v. Selective Serv. Local Bd. No. 4" judges="Per Curiam" nature_of_suit="" source="lawbox" blocked="False" date_blocked="None" extracted_by_ocr="False">&lt;div&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;b&gt;397 U.S. 47 (1970)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h1&gt;KOLDEN&lt;br&gt;
v.&lt;br&gt;
SELECTIVE SERVICE LOCAL BOARD NO. 4.&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;No. 70.&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Supreme Court of United States.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;Decided February 24, 1970&lt;sup&gt;[*]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
ON PETITION FOR WRIT OF CERTIORARI TO THE UNITED STATES COURT OF APPEALS FOR THE EIGHTH CIRCUIT.
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Melvin L. Wulf, Chester Bruvold,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Lynn Castner&lt;/i&gt; for petitioner in No. 70. &lt;i&gt;John J. Abt&lt;/i&gt; for petitioner in No. 73. &lt;i&gt;Stanley Faulkner&lt;/i&gt; for petitioner in No. 164. &lt;i&gt;Mr. Wulf&lt;/i&gt; for petitioner in No. 183. &lt;i&gt;Robert Eugene Smith&lt;/i&gt; for petitioner in No. 331. &lt;i&gt;Sheldon M. Meizlish&lt;/i&gt; for petitioners in No. 449.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Solicitor General Griswold, Assistant Attorney General Ruckelshaus, Morton Hollander,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Ralph A. Fine&lt;/i&gt; for respondents in Nos. 70, 164, and 183. &lt;i&gt;Solicitor General Griswold, Assistant Attorney General Ruckelshaus,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Mr. Hollander&lt;/i&gt; for respondents in No. 73. &lt;i&gt;Solicitor General Griswold&lt;/i&gt; for respondents in Nos. 331 and 449.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PER CURIAM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The petitions for writs of certiorari are granted, the judgments are vacated and the cases are remanded &lt;span class="star-pagination"&gt;*48&lt;/span&gt; to the respective United States Courts of Appeals for further consideration in light of &lt;i&gt;Breen&lt;/i&gt; v. &lt;i&gt;Selective Service Board,&lt;/i&gt; 396 U. S. 460.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MR. JUSTICE HARLAN would reverse the judgments in these cases and remand them on the basis of his concurring opinion in &lt;i&gt;Breen&lt;/i&gt; v. &lt;i&gt;Selective Service Board,&lt;/i&gt; 396 U. S., at 468, and the Court's opinion in &lt;i&gt;Gutknecht&lt;/i&gt; v. &lt;i&gt;United States,&lt;/i&gt; 396 U. S. 295.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;NOTES&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[*]  Together with No. 73, &lt;i&gt;Chaikin&lt;/i&gt; v. &lt;i&gt;Selective Service Local Board No. 66 et al.;&lt;/i&gt; No. 164, &lt;i&gt;Faulkner&lt;/i&gt; v. &lt;i&gt;Laird, Secretary of Defense, et al.;&lt;/i&gt; No. 183, &lt;i&gt;Osher&lt;/i&gt; v. &lt;i&gt;Selective Service Local Board No. 6 et al.,&lt;/i&gt; on petitions for writs of certiorari to the United States Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit; No. 331, &lt;i&gt;Kraus&lt;/i&gt; v. &lt;i&gt;Selective Service System Local 25 et al.,&lt;/i&gt; on petition for writ of certiorari to the United States Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit; and No. 449, &lt;i&gt;Anderson et al.&lt;/i&gt; v. &lt;i&gt;Hershey, National Director, Selective Service System, et al.,&lt;/i&gt; on petition for writ of certiorari to the United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;</opinion>