<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><opinion id="2522123" path="/scotus/dVJT/marshall-v-hare/" sha1="8aec814d45e85cf152add9726c2c3db7c3969c5d" court="Supreme Court of the United States" time_retrieved="2013-10-30 10:09:48.273139+00:00" date_filed="1964-06-22" precedential_status="Published" local_path="" docket_number="962" federal_cite_one="378 U.S. 561" case_name="Marshall v. Hare" judges="Per Curiam" nature_of_suit="" source="lawbox" blocked="False" date_blocked="None" extracted_by_ocr="False">&lt;div&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;b&gt;378 U.S. 561 (1964)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h1&gt;MARSHALL ET AL.&lt;br&gt;
v.&lt;br&gt;
HARE, SECRETARY OF STATE OF MICHIGAN, ET AL.&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;No. 962.&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Supreme Court of United States.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;Decided June 22, 1964.&lt;/center&gt;
APPEAL FROM THE UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT FOR THE EASTERN DISTRICT OF MICHIGAN.
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Theodore Sachs&lt;/i&gt; for appellants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Robert A. Derengoski,&lt;/i&gt; Solicitor General of Michigan, &lt;i&gt;Stanton S. Faville,&lt;/i&gt; Chief Assistant Attorney General, and &lt;i&gt;James R. Ramsey&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Russell A. Searl,&lt;/i&gt; Assistant Attorneys General, for Hare et al.; and &lt;i&gt;Edmund E. Shepherd&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;R. William Rogers&lt;/i&gt; for Beadle et al., appellees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PER CURIAM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The judgment below is reversed. &lt;i&gt;Reynolds&lt;/i&gt; v. &lt;i&gt;Sims,&lt;/i&gt; 377 U. S. 533; &lt;i&gt;Lucas&lt;/i&gt; v. &lt;i&gt;Forty-Fourth General Assembly of Colorado,&lt;/i&gt; 377 U. S. 713. The case is remanded for further proceedings consistent with the views stated in our opinions in &lt;i&gt;Reynolds&lt;/i&gt; v. &lt;i&gt;Sims&lt;/i&gt; and in the other cases relating to state legislative apportionment decided along with &lt;i&gt;Reynolds.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MR. JUSTICE CLARK and MR. JUSTICE STEWART would affirm the judgment because the Michigan system of legislative apportionment is clearly a rational one and clearly does not frustrate effective majority rule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MR. JUSTICE HARLAN dissents for the reasons stated in his dissenting opinion in &lt;i&gt;Reynolds&lt;/i&gt; v. &lt;i&gt;Sims,&lt;/i&gt; 377 U. S. 533, 589.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</opinion>