<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><opinion id="2621046" path="/scotus/er9s/richmond-school-board-v-board-of-educ/" sha1="007bcffccdfcd368332a36e03fc027f4be3fd4ec" court="Supreme Court of the United States" time_retrieved="2013-11-01 20:30:04.733245+00:00" date_filed="1973-05-21" precedential_status="Published" local_path="" docket_number="72-549" federal_cite_one="412 U.S. 92" case_name="Richmond School Board v. Board of Educ." judges="Per Curiam" nature_of_suit="" source="lawbox" blocked="False" date_blocked="None" extracted_by_ocr="False">&lt;div&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;b&gt;412 U.S. 92 (1973)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h1&gt;SCHOOL BOARD OF CITY OF RICHMOND, VIRGINIA, ET AL.&lt;br&gt;
v.&lt;br&gt;
STATE BOARD OF EDUCATION OF VIRGINIA ET AL.&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;No. 72-549.&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Supreme Court of United States.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;Argued April 23, 1973.&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;Decided May 21, 1973.&lt;sup&gt;[*]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
CERTIORARI TO THE UNITED STATES COURT OF APPEALS FOR THE FOURTH CIRCUIT.
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;George B. Little&lt;/i&gt; argued the cause for petitioners in No. 72-549. With him on the briefs was &lt;i&gt;Conrad B. Mattox, Jr. William T. Coleman, Jr.,&lt;/i&gt; argued the cause for petitioners in No. 72-550. With him on the briefs were &lt;i&gt;Jack Greenberg, James M. Nabrit III, Norman J. Chachkin, Louis R. Louis, William L. Taylor,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Anthony G. Amsterdam.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Philip B. Kurland&lt;/i&gt; argued the cause for respondents in both cases. With him on the brief were &lt;i&gt;Edward I. Rothschild, Andrew P. Miller,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Virginia, &lt;i&gt;William G. Broaddus&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;D. Patrick Lacy, Jr.,&lt;/i&gt; Assistant Attorneys General, &lt;i&gt;Frederick T. Gray, Walter E. Rogers, J. Segar Gravatt, R. D. McIlwaine III, L. Paul Byrne,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;J. Mercer White, Jr.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Solicitor General Griswold&lt;/i&gt; argued the cause for the United States as &lt;i&gt;amicus curiae&lt;/i&gt; urging affirmance in both cases. With him on the brief were &lt;i&gt;Assistant Attorney General Pottinger, A. Raymond Randolph, Jr., Brian K. Landsberg,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;John C. Hoyle.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[&#x86;]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="star-pagination"&gt;*93&lt;/span&gt; PER CURIAM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The judgment is affirmed by an equally divided Court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MR. JUSTICE POWELL took no part in the consideration or decision of these cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;NOTES&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[*]  Together with No. 72-550, &lt;i&gt;Bradley et al.&lt;/i&gt; v. &lt;i&gt;State Board of Education of Virginia et al.,&lt;/i&gt; also on certiorari to the same court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&#x86;]  Briefs of &lt;i&gt;amici curiae&lt;/i&gt; urging reversal in both cases were filed by &lt;i&gt;Stephen J. Pollak, Richard M. Sharp,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;David Rubin&lt;/i&gt; for the National Education Association, and by &lt;i&gt;Melvin L. Wulf, Sanford Jay Rosen,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Philip Hirschkop&lt;/i&gt; for the American Civil Liberties Union et al. &lt;i&gt;Margie Pitts Hames&lt;/i&gt; filed a brief for the Black Parents of Atlanta, Georgia, as &lt;i&gt;amicus curiae&lt;/i&gt; urging reversal in No. 72-550.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Briefs of &lt;i&gt;amici curiae&lt;/i&gt; urging affirmance in both cases were filed by &lt;i&gt;David I. Caplan&lt;/i&gt; for the Jewish Rights Council, and by &lt;i&gt;Harold H. Fuhrman&lt;/i&gt; for the National Suburban League, Ltd. &lt;i&gt;Charles S. Conley&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Floyd B. McKissick&lt;/i&gt; filed a brief for the Congress of Racial Equality as &lt;i&gt;amicus curiae&lt;/i&gt; urging affirmance in No. 72-549.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;</opinion>