<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><opinion id="137724" path="/scotus/GWy/wisconsin-right-to-life-inc-v-federal-election/" sha1="f8062c17fd6edd9062cec01d3f881b3745c041cd" court="Supreme Court of the United States" download_URL="http://bulk.resource.org/courts.gov/c/US/542/542.US.1305.04.194.html" time_retrieved="2010-04-28 17:31:56+00:00" date_filed="2004-09-14" precedential_status="Published" local_path="" docket_number="04A194" federal_cite_one="542 U.S. 1305" lexis_cite="" case_name="Wisconsin Right to Life, Inc. v. Federal Election Commission" judges="" nature_of_suit="" source="resource.org" blocked="False" date_blocked="None" extracted_by_ocr="False" cited_by="2620275,815279,814375">&lt;p class="case_cite"&gt;&lt;span class="citation no-link"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;542&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;1305&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="parties"&gt;WISCONSIN RIGHT TO LIFE, INC.&lt;br&gt;v.&lt;br&gt;FEDERAL ELECTION COMMISSION&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="docket"&gt;No. 04A194.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="court"&gt;Supreme Court of United States.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p class="date"&gt;Decided September 14, 2004.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;div class="prelims"&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;ON APPLICATION FOR INJUNCTION&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;Applicant's request for an injunction pending appeal barring the enforcement of &amp;#167;203 of the Bipartisan Campaign Reform Act of 2002 (BCRA) is denied. Applicant contends that &amp;#167;203&amp;#8212;which bans corporations from using general treasury funds to finance certain electioneering communications&amp;#8212;violates the First Amendment as applied to its political advertisements. An injunction pending appeal would be an extraordinary remedy, particularly when this Court recently held BCRA facially constitutional, &lt;i&gt;McConnell&lt;/i&gt; v. &lt;i&gt;Federal Election Comm'n,&lt;/i&gt; &lt;span class="citation"&gt;&lt;a href="/scotus/EZc/mcconnell-v-federal-election-commn/"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;540&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;93&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, 189-210, and when a three-judge District Court unanimously rejected applicant's request for a preliminary injunction. The All Writs Act, the only source of this Court's authority to issue the instant injunction, is to be used "`sparingly and only in the most critical and exigent circumstances.'" &lt;i&gt;Ohio Citizens for Responsible Energy, Inc.&lt;/i&gt; v. &lt;i&gt;NRC,&lt;/i&gt; 479 U. S. 1312, 1313, (SCALIA, J., in chambers). Applicant has not established that this extraordinary remedy is appropriate here.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;CHIEF JUSTICE REHNQUIST, Circuit Justice.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="num" id="p1"&gt;
      &lt;span class="num"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;Applicant Wisconsin Right to Life, Inc., has requested I grant an injunction pending appeal barring the enforcement of &amp;#167; 203 of the Bipartisan Campaign Reform Act of 2002 (BCRA), 116 Stat. 91, 2 U.S.C. &amp;#167; 441b (2000 ed. and Supp. II), which bars corporations from using general treasury funds to finance electioneering communications as defined in BCRA &amp;#167;201. Applicant contends that &amp;#167;203 violates the First Amendment as applied to its political advertisements. A three-judge District Court, convened pursuant to BCRA &amp;#167;403(a)(1), denied applicant's motion for a preliminary injunction and denied applicant's motion for an injunction pending appeal. I herewith deny the application for an injunction pending appeal.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class="num" id="p2"&gt;
      &lt;span class="num"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;p class="indent"&gt;An injunction pending appeal barring the enforcement of an Act of Congress would be an extraordinary remedy, particularly when this Court recently held BCRA facially constitutional, &lt;i&gt;McConnell&lt;/i&gt; v. &lt;i&gt;Federal Election Comm'n,&lt;/i&gt; &lt;span class="citation"&gt;&lt;a href="/scotus/EZc/mcconnell-v-federal-election-commn/"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;540&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;93&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, 189-210 (2003), and when a unanimous three-judge District Court rejected applicant's request for a preliminary injunction. See &lt;i&gt;Turner Broadcasting System, Inc.&lt;/i&gt; v. &lt;i&gt;FCC,&lt;/i&gt; 507 U. S. 1301, 1302-1303 (1993) (REHNQUIST, C. J., in chambers). The All Writs Act, 28 U. S. C. &amp;#167; 1651(a), is the only source of this Court's authority to issue such an injunction. That authority is to be used "`"sparingly and only in the most critical and exigent circumstances."'" &lt;i&gt;Ohio Citizens for Responsible Energy, Inc.&lt;/i&gt; v. &lt;i&gt;NRC,&lt;/i&gt; &lt;span class="citation"&gt;&lt;a href="/scotus/zeU/ohio-citizens-for-responsible-energy-inc-v/"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;479&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;1312&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;, 1313 (1986) (SCALIA, J., in chambers) (quoting &lt;i&gt;Fishman&lt;/i&gt; v. &lt;i&gt;Schaffer,&lt;/i&gt; 429 U. S. 1325, 1326 (1976) (Marshall, J., in chambers)). It is only appropriately exercised where (1) "necessary or appropriate in aid of [our] jurisdictio[n]," 28 U.S.C. &amp;#167; 1651(a), and (2) the legal rights at issue are "indisputably clear," &lt;i&gt;Brown&lt;/i&gt; v. &lt;i&gt;Gilmore,&lt;/i&gt; 533 U. S. 1301, 1303 (2001) (REHNQUIST, C. J., in chambers). Applicant has failed to establish that this extraordinary remedy is appropriate. Therefore, I decline to issue an injunction pending appeal in this case.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    </opinion>