<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><opinion id="184314" path="/scotus/WMQ/chase-bank-usa-n-a-v-mccoy/" sha1="4c51d98ce2b5856901eac0864bbde3923546a579" court="Supreme Court of the United States" download_URL="http://www.supremecourt.gov/opinions/10pdf/09-329.pdf" time_retrieved="2011-02-05 01:04:07+00:00" date_filed="2011-01-24" precedential_status="Published" local_path="pdf/2011/02/04/Chase_Bank_USA_N._A._v._McCoy.pdf" docket_number="09-329" federal_cite_one="" lexis_cite="" case_name="Chase Bank USA, N. A. v. McCoy" judges="" nature_of_suit="" source="court website" blocked="False" date_blocked="None" extracted_by_ocr="False" cited_by="627148,626300,625518,625437,624985,621369,618071,616803,612649,223628,222564,219253,216626,216281,215155,206614,206190,204779,204689">&lt;pre class="inline"&gt;(Slip Opinion)              OCTOBER TERM, 2010                                       1&#xD;
&#xD;
                                       Syllabus&#xD;
&#xD;
         NOTE: Where it is feasible, a syllabus (headnote) will be released, as is&#xD;
       being done in connection with this case, at the time the opinion is issued.&#xD;
       The syllabus constitutes no part of the opinion of the Court but has been&#xD;
       prepared by the Reporter of Decisions for the convenience of the reader.&#xD;
       See United States v. Detroit Timber &amp; Lumber Co., 200 U. S. 321, 337.&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES&#xD;
&#xD;
                                       Syllabus&#xD;
&#xD;
 CHASE BANK USA, N. A. v. MCCOY, INDIVIDUALLY AND&#xD;
         ON BEHALF OF ALL OTHERS SIMILARLY SITUATED&#xD;
&#xD;
CERTIORARI TO THE UNITED STATES COURT OF APPEALS FOR&#xD;
                  THE NINTH CIRCUIT&#xD;
&#xD;
  No. 09–329.      Argued December 8, 2010—Decided January 24, 2011&#xD;
Regulation Z—promulgated by the Federal Reserve Board (Board) pur&#xD;
  suant to its authority under the Truth in Lending Act—requires&#xD;
  credit card issuers to disclose certain information to cardholders. The&#xD;
  version of the regulation in effect at the time this dispute arose&#xD;
  obliges issuers to provide to cardholders an “[i]nitial disclosure&#xD;
  statement,” 12 CFR §226.6, specifying “each periodic rate that may&#xD;
  be used to compute the finance charge,” §226.6(a)(2). It also imposes&#xD;
  “[s]ubsequent disclosure requirements,” §226.9, including notice to&#xD;
  cardholders “[w]henever any term required to be disclosed under&#xD;
  §226.6 is changed,” §226.9(c)(1). When “a periodic rate or other fi&#xD;
  nance charge is increased because of the consumer’s delinquency or&#xD;
  default,” notice must be given “before the effective date of the&#xD;
  change.” Ibid.&#xD;
     At the time respondent McCoy filed suit, he was the holder of a&#xD;
  credit card issued by petitioner Chase Bank. The cardholder agree&#xD;
  ment provided, in relevant part, that McCoy was eligible for “Pre&#xD;
  ferred rates” as long as he met certain conditions. If any of those&#xD;
  conditions were not met, Chase reserved the right to raise the rate,&#xD;
  up to a pre-set maximum, and to apply the change to both existing&#xD;
  and new balances. McCoy alleges that Chase increased his interest&#xD;
  rate due to his delinquency or default and applied that increase ret&#xD;
  roactively, and that this action violated Regulation Z because Chase&#xD;
  did not notify him of the increase until after it had taken effect. The&#xD;
  District Court dismissed his complaint, holding that because the in&#xD;
  crease did not constitute a “change in terms” under §226.9(c), Chase&#xD;
  was not required to notify him of the increase before implementing it.&#xD;
  The Ninth Circuit reversed in relevant part, holding that Regulation&#xD;
2                  CHASE BANK USA, N. A. v. MCCOY&#xD;
&#xD;
                                  Syllabus&#xD;
&#xD;
    Z requires issuers to provide notice of an interest-rate increase prior&#xD;
    to its effective date.&#xD;
Held: At the time of the transactions at issue, Regulation Z did not re&#xD;
 quire Chase to provide McCoy with a change-in-terms notice before&#xD;
 implementing the agreement term allowing it to raise his interest&#xD;
 rate, up to a pre-set maximum, following delinquency or default.&#xD;
 Pp. 7–19.&#xD;
    (a) This case requires the Court to determine the meaning of a&#xD;
 regulation promulgated by the Board under its statutory authority.&#xD;
 However, Regulation Z’s text is unclear with respect to the crucial in&#xD;
 terpretive question at issue: whether a change to an interest rate,&#xD;
 pursuant to previously-disclosed contractual provision, constitutes a&#xD;
 change to a “term required to be disclosed under §226.6” requiring a&#xD;
 subsequent disclosure under §226.9(c)(1). Because of this ambiguity,&#xD;
 the Court must look to the Board’s own interpretation of the regula&#xD;
 tion for guidance in deciding this case. Pp. 7–12.&#xD;
    (b) The Board has made clear in its amicus brief to this Court that,&#xD;
 in its view, Chase was not required to give McCoy notice of the inter&#xD;
 est rate increase under the applicable version of Regulation Z. This&#xD;
 Court defers to an agency’s interpretation of its own regulation, ad&#xD;
 vanced in a legal brief, unless that interpretation is “plainly errone&#xD;
 ous or inconsistent with the regulation.” Auer v. Robbins, 519 U. S.&#xD;
 452, 461 (internal quotation marks omitted). In Auer, the Court de&#xD;
 ferred to the Secretary of Labor’s interpretation of his own regula&#xD;
 tion, presented in an amicus brief submitted by the agency at the&#xD;
 Court’s invitation. The Court held that the fact that the interpreta&#xD;
 tion came in a legal brief did not, “in the circumstances of th[at] case,&#xD;
 make it unworthy of deference.” Id., at 462. The interpretation was&#xD;
 “in no sense a post hoc rationalization advanced by an agency seeking&#xD;
 to defend past agency action against attack,” ibid. (internal quotation&#xD;
 marks and alteration omitted), and there was “no reason to suspect&#xD;
 that the interpretation [did] not reflect the agency’s fair and consid&#xD;
 ered judgment on the matter in question,” ibid. The brief submitted&#xD;
 by the Board here, at the Court’s invitation, is no different. As in&#xD;
 Auer, there is no reason to believe that the Board’s interpretation is a&#xD;
 “post hoc rationalization” taken as a litigation position, for the Board&#xD;
 is not a party to this case. And its interpretation is neither “plainly&#xD;
 erroneous” nor “inconsistent with” the indeterminate text of Regula&#xD;
 tion Z. Thus, there is no reason to suspect that the Board’s position&#xD;
 in its amicus brief reflects anything other than its fair and considered&#xD;
 judgment as to what the regulation required at the time this dispute&#xD;
 arose. That Congress and the Board may currently hold a different&#xD;
 view does not mean that deference is not warranted to the Board’s&#xD;
 understanding of what the applicable version of Regulation Z re&#xD;
                     Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)                    3&#xD;
&#xD;
                                Syllabus&#xD;
&#xD;
  quired. Under Auer, therefore, it is clear that deference to the inter&#xD;
  pretation in the agency amicus brief is warranted. Pp. 12–16.&#xD;
     (c) McCoy errs in arguing that deference to a legal brief is inappro&#xD;
  priate because the interpretation of Regulation Z in the Official Staff&#xD;
  Commentary commands a different result. While Commentary&#xD;
  promulgated by the Board as an interpretation of Regulation Z may&#xD;
  warrant deference as a general matter, the Commentary explaining&#xD;
  the requirements at issue in this case largely replicates the ambigu&#xD;
  ity present in the regulatory text, and therefore offers no reason to&#xD;
  disregard the interpretation advanced in the Board’s amicus brief.&#xD;
  Pp. 16–19.&#xD;
559 F. 3d 963, reversed and remanded.&#xD;
&#xD;
  SOTOMAYOR, J., delivered the opinion for a unanimous Court.&#xD;
                        Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)                              1&#xD;
&#xD;
                             Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
     NOTICE: This opinion is subject to formal revision before publication in the&#xD;
     preliminary print of the United States Reports. Readers are requested to&#xD;
     notify the Reporter of Decisions, Supreme Court of the United States, Wash­&#xD;
     ington, D. C. 20543, of any typographical or other formal errors, in order&#xD;
     that corrections may be made before the preliminary print goes to press.&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES&#xD;
                                   _________________&#xD;
&#xD;
                                   No. 09–329&#xD;
                                   _________________&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
 CHASE BANK USA, N. A., PETITIONER v. JAMES A. &#xD;
&#xD;
    MCCOY, INDIVIDUALLY AND ON BEHALF OF ALL &#xD;
&#xD;
                    OTHERS SIMILARLY SITUATED&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
 ON WRIT OF CERTIORARI TO THE UNITED STATES COURT OF&#xD;
&#xD;
            APPEALS FOR THE NINTH CIRCUIT&#xD;
&#xD;
                               [January 24, 2011] &#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
   JUSTICE SOTOMAYOR delivered the opinion of the Court.&#xD;
   As applicable to this case, Regulation Z—promulgated&#xD;
by the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System&#xD;
(Board) pursuant to its authority under the Truth in&#xD;
Lending Act (TILA), 82 Stat. 146, 15 U. S. C. §1601 et&#xD;
seq.—requires that issuers of credit cards provide card­&#xD;
holders with an “[i]nitial disclosure statement” specifying,&#xD;
inter alia, “each periodic rate” associated with the account.&#xD;
12 CFR §226.6(a)(2) (2008). The regulation also imposes&#xD;
“[s]ubsequent disclosure requirements,” including notice to&#xD;
cardholders “[w]henever any term required to be disclosed&#xD;
under §226.6 is changed.” §226.9(c)(1). This case presents&#xD;
the question whether Regulation Z requires an issuer to&#xD;
notify a cardholder of an interest-rate increase instituted&#xD;
pursuant to a provision of the cardholder agreement giv­&#xD;
ing the issuer discretion to increase the rate, up to a&#xD;
stated maximum, in the event of the cardholder’s delin­&#xD;
quency or default. We conclude that the version of Reg-&#xD;
ulation Z applicable in this case does not require such&#xD;
notice.&#xD;
2                CHASE BANK USA, N. A. v. MCCOY&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
                               I&#xD;
&#xD;
                               A&#xD;
&#xD;
   Congress passed TILA to promote consumers’ “informed&#xD;
use of credit” by requiring “meaningful disclosure of credit&#xD;
terms,” 15 U. S. C. §1601(a), and granted the Board the&#xD;
authority to issue regulations to achieve TILA’s purposes,&#xD;
§1604(a). Pursuant to this authority, the Board promul­&#xD;
gated Regulation Z, which requires credit card issuers to&#xD;
disclose certain information to consumers.1 Two provi­&#xD;
sions of Regulation Z are at issue in this case. The first,&#xD;
12 CFR §226.6, explains what information credit card&#xD;
issuers are obliged to provide to cardholders in the&#xD;
“[i]nitial disclosure statement,” including “each periodic&#xD;
rate that may be used to compute the finance charge.”&#xD;
§226.6(a)(2). The second, §226.9, imposes upon issuers&#xD;
certain “[s]ubsequent disclosure requirements,” including&#xD;
a requirement to provide notice “[w]henever any term&#xD;
required to be disclosed under §226.6 is changed.”&#xD;
§226.9(c)(1). As a general matter, notice of a change in&#xD;
terms has to be provided 15 days in advance of the effec­&#xD;
tive date of the change. Ibid. When “a periodic rate or&#xD;
other finance charge is increased because of the con­&#xD;
sumer’s delinquency or default,” however, notice only need&#xD;
be given “before the effective date of the change.” Ibid.&#xD;
Regulation Z also explains that no notice is required under&#xD;
§226.9 when the change in terms “results from . . . the&#xD;
consumer’s default or delinquency (other than an increase&#xD;
in the periodic rate or other finance charge).” §226.9(c)(2).&#xD;
   The official interpretation of Regulation Z (Official Staff&#xD;
Commentary or Commentary) promulgated by the Board&#xD;
&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  1 As discussed more fully below, see infra, at 4–5, in 2009 the Board&#xD;
&#xD;
amended Regulation Z, such that the provisions discussed in this&#xD;
opinion are no longer in effect. However, because the pre-2009 provi­&#xD;
sions are the ones applicable to the case before us, we will refer to them&#xD;
in the present tense.&#xD;
                  Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)            3&#xD;
&#xD;
                      Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
explains these requirements further: Section 226.9(c)(1)’s&#xD;
notice-of-change requirement does not apply “if the spe­&#xD;
cific change is set forth initially, such as . . . an increase&#xD;
that occurs when the consumer has been under an agree­&#xD;
ment to maintain a certain balance in a savings account in&#xD;
order to keep a particular rate and the account balance&#xD;
falls below the specified minimum.” 12 CFR pt. 226, Supp.&#xD;
I, Comment 9(c)–1, p. 506 (2008) (hereinafter Comment&#xD;
9(c)–1). On the other hand, the Commentary explains,&#xD;
“notice must be given if the contract allows the creditor to&#xD;
increase the rate at its discretion but does not include&#xD;
specific terms for an increase (for example, when an in­&#xD;
crease may occur under the creditor’s contract reservation&#xD;
right to increase the periodic rate).” Ibid. As to the timing&#xD;
requirements, the Commentary states: “[A] notice of&#xD;
change in terms is required, but it may be mailed or deliv­&#xD;
ered as late as the effective date of the change . . . [i]f&#xD;
there is an increased periodic rate or any other finance&#xD;
charge attributable to the consumer’s delinquency or&#xD;
default.” Id., Comment 9(c)(1)–3, at 507 (hereinafter&#xD;
Comment 9(c)(1)–3).&#xD;
   At least as early as 2004, the Board began considering&#xD;
revisions to Regulation Z. The new regulations the Board&#xD;
eventually issued do not apply to the present case, but the&#xD;
details of their promulgation provide useful background&#xD;
in considering the parties’ arguments with respect to the&#xD;
version of Regulation Z we address here. In 2004 the&#xD;
Board issued an advance notice of proposed rulemaking&#xD;
announcing its intent to consider revisions. 69 Fed. Reg.&#xD;
70925 (2004). In so doing, the Board described how it&#xD;
understood the notice requirements to function at that&#xD;
time:&#xD;
    “[A]dvance notice is not required in all cases. For ex­&#xD;
    ample, if the interest rate or other finance charge in­&#xD;
    creases due to a consumer’s default or delinquency,&#xD;
4             CHASE BANK USA, N. A. v. MCCOY&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
    notice is required, but need not be given in advance.&#xD;
    12 CFR 226.9(c)(1); comment 9(c)(1)–3.         And no&#xD;
    change-in-terms notice is required if the creditor&#xD;
    specifies in advance the circumstances under which&#xD;
    an increase to the finance charge or an annual fee will&#xD;
    occur. Comment 9(c)–1. For example, some credit&#xD;
    card account agreements permit the card issuer to in­&#xD;
    crease the interest rate if the consumer pays late . . . .&#xD;
    Under Regulation Z, because the circumstances are&#xD;
    specified in advance in the account agreement, the&#xD;
    creditor need not provide a change-in-terms notice 15&#xD;
    days in advance of the increase; the new rate will ap­&#xD;
    pear on the periodic statement for the cycle in which&#xD;
    the increase occurs.” Id., at 70931–70932.&#xD;
The Board asked for public comment on whether these&#xD;
“existing disclosure rules” were “adequate to enable con­&#xD;
sumers to make timely decisions about how to manage&#xD;
their accounts.” Id., at 70932.&#xD;
   Subsequently, in 2007, the Board published proposed&#xD;
amendments to Regulation Z and the Commentary. 72&#xD;
Fed. Reg. 32948. One amendment would have required 45&#xD;
days’ advance written notice when “(i) [a] rate is increased&#xD;
due to the consumer’s delinquency or default; or (ii) [a]&#xD;
rate is increased as a penalty for one or more events spec­&#xD;
ified in the account agreement, such as making a late&#xD;
payment or obtaining an extension of credit that exceeds&#xD;
the credit limit.”     Id., at 33058 (proposed 12 CFR&#xD;
§226.9(g)). The Board explained that, under the amend­&#xD;
ments, “creditors would no longer be permitted to provide&#xD;
for the immediate application of penalty pricing upon the&#xD;
occurrence of certain events specified in the contract.” 72&#xD;
Fed. Reg. 33012.&#xD;
   In January 2009, the Board promulgated a final rule&#xD;
implementing many of the proposed changes, scheduled to&#xD;
be effective July 1, 2010. 74 Fed. Reg. 5244. Most sali­&#xD;
                  Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)            5&#xD;
&#xD;
                      Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
ently, the Board included a new provision, §226.9(g),&#xD;
which requires 45 days’ advance notice of increases in&#xD;
rates due to cardholder delinquency or default, or as a&#xD;
penalty, including penalties for “events specified in the&#xD;
account agreement, such as making a late payment . . . .”&#xD;
12 CFR §226.9(g) (2010). In May 2009, Congress en­&#xD;
acted the Credit Card Accountability Responsibility and&#xD;
Disclosure Act (Credit CARD Act or Act), 123 Stat. 1734.&#xD;
The Act amended TILA, in relevant part, to require 45&#xD;
days’ advance notice of most increases in credit card an­&#xD;
nual percentage rates. 15 U. S. C. §1637(i) (2006 ed.,&#xD;
Supp. III). Because the Credit CARD Act’s notice re­&#xD;
quirements with respect to interest-rate increases largely&#xD;
mirror the requirements in the new version of the regu-&#xD;
lation, the Board changed the effective date of those&#xD;
requirements to August 20, 2009, to coincide with the&#xD;
statutory schedule. See 74 Fed. Reg. 36077–36079. The&#xD;
transactions giving rise to the dispute at issue in this case,&#xD;
however, arose prior to enactment of the Act and the&#xD;
promulgation of the new regulatory provisions.&#xD;
                            B&#xD;
  Respondent James A. McCoy brought this action in the&#xD;
Superior Court of Orange County, California on behalf of&#xD;
himself and others similarly situated against petitioner&#xD;
Chase Bank USA, N. A.; Chase removed the action to the&#xD;
United States District Court for the Central District of&#xD;
California under 28 U. S. C. §1441. At the time of the&#xD;
transactions at issue, McCoy was the holder of a credit&#xD;
card issued by Chase. The cardholder agreement between&#xD;
the parties (Agreement) provides, in relevant part, that&#xD;
McCoy is eligible for “Preferred rates,” but that to keep&#xD;
such rates he has to meet certain conditions, including&#xD;
making “at least the required minimum payments when&#xD;
due on [his] Account and on all other loans or accounts&#xD;
with [Chase] and [his] other creditors.” Brief for Respon­&#xD;
6                CHASE BANK USA, N. A. v. MCCOY&#xD;
&#xD;
                         Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
dent 8, n. 2; see also 559 F. 3d 963, 972, n. 1 (CA9 2009)&#xD;
(Cudahy, J., dissenting). If any of the conditions in the&#xD;
Agreement are not met, Chase reserves the right to&#xD;
“change [McCoy’s] interest rate and impose a Non-&#xD;
Preferred rate up to the maximum Non-Preferred rate&#xD;
described in the Pricing Schedule” and to apply any&#xD;
changes “to existing as well as new balances . . . effective&#xD;
with the billing cycle ending on the review date.” Brief for&#xD;
Respondent 8, n. 2.&#xD;
  McCoy’s complaint alleges that Chase increased his&#xD;
interest rate due to his delinquency or default, and applied&#xD;
that increase retroactively. McCoy asserts that the rate&#xD;
increase violates Regulation Z because, pursuant to the&#xD;
Agreement, Chase did not notify him of the increase until&#xD;
after it had taken effect.2 The District Court dismissed&#xD;
McCoy’s complaint, holding that because the increase did&#xD;
not constitute a “change in terms” as contemplated by&#xD;
§226.9(c), Chase was not required to notify him of the&#xD;
increase before implementing it. See App. to Pet. for Cert.&#xD;
37a–47a.&#xD;
  A divided panel of the United States Court of Appeals&#xD;
for the Ninth Circuit reversed in relevant part, holding&#xD;
that Regulation Z requires issuers to provide notice of an&#xD;
interest-rate increase prior to its effective date. See 559&#xD;
F. 3d, at 969. Concluding that the text of Regulation Z is&#xD;
ambiguous and that the agency commentary accompany­&#xD;
ing the 2004 request for comments and the 2007 proposed&#xD;
amendments favors neither party’s interpretation, the&#xD;
court relied primarily on the Official Staff Commentary; in&#xD;
particular, the court noted that Comment 9(c)–1 requires&#xD;
no notice of a change in terms if the “specific change” at&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  2 McCoy also asserted various state-law claims that are not before us.&#xD;
&#xD;
We note that McCoy’s complaint provides little detail regarding the&#xD;
transactions at issue in this case. The parties, however, are in agree­&#xD;
ment as to the essential facts alleged.&#xD;
                    Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)                   7&#xD;
&#xD;
                         Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
issue is set forth in the initial agreement. See id., at 965–&#xD;
967. The court found, however, that because the Agree­&#xD;
ment vests Chase with discretion to impose any Non-&#xD;
Preferred rate it chooses (up to the specified maximum)&#xD;
upon McCoy’s default, the Agreement “provides McCoy&#xD;
with no basis for predicting in advance what retroactive&#xD;
interest rate Chase will choose to charge him if he de­&#xD;
faults.” Id., at 967. Accordingly, the court held that be­&#xD;
cause the Agreement does not alert McCoy to the “specific&#xD;
change” that will occur if he defaults, Chase was obliged to&#xD;
give notice of that change prior to its effective date. Ibid.&#xD;
Relying primarily on the 2004 notice of proposed rulemak­&#xD;
ing and the 2007 proposed amendments, the dissenting&#xD;
judge concluded that Regulation Z does not require notice&#xD;
of an interest-rate increase in the circumstances of this&#xD;
case. See id., at 972–979 (opinion of Cudahy, J.).&#xD;
  After the Ninth Circuit’s ruling, the United States Court&#xD;
of Appeals for the First Circuit decided the same question&#xD;
in Chase’s favor. See Shaner v. Chase Bank USA, N. A.,&#xD;
587 F. 3d 488 (2009). The First Circuit relied in part on&#xD;
an amicus brief submitted by the Board at the court’s&#xD;
request, in which the agency advanced the same interpre­&#xD;
tation of Regulation Z that it now does before this Court.&#xD;
Id., at 493. We granted certiorari to resolve this division&#xD;
in authority.3 561 U. S. ___ (2010).&#xD;
                             II&#xD;
  In order to decide this case, we must determine whether&#xD;
an interest-rate increase constitutes a “change in terms”&#xD;
under Regulation Z, when the change is made pursuant to&#xD;
a provision in the cardholder agreement allowing the&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  3 The United States Court of Appeals for the Seventh Circuit has also&#xD;
&#xD;
rejected the reasoning of the Ninth Circuit, though on a different&#xD;
question than the one presented in this case. See Swanson v. Bank of&#xD;
America, N. A., 559 F. 3d 653, reh’g denied, 563 F. 3d 634 (2009)&#xD;
(disagreeing with the Ninth Circuit’s interpretation of Regulation Z).&#xD;
8             CHASE BANK USA, N. A. v. MCCOY&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
issuer to increase the rate, up to a stated maximum, in the&#xD;
event of the cardholder’s delinquency or default. Accord­&#xD;
ingly, this case calls upon us to determine the meaning of&#xD;
a regulation promulgated by the Board under its statutory&#xD;
authority. The parties dispute the proper interpretation of&#xD;
the regulation itself, as well as whether we should accord&#xD;
deference to the Board’s interpretation of its regulation.&#xD;
As explained below, we conclude that the text of the regu­&#xD;
lation is ambiguous, and that deference is warranted to&#xD;
the interpretation of that text advanced by the Board in&#xD;
its amicus brief.&#xD;
                               A&#xD;
  Our analysis begins with the text of Regulation Z in&#xD;
effect at the time this dispute arose. First, §226.6 requires&#xD;
an “[i]nitial disclosure statement”:&#xD;
      “The creditor shall disclose to the consumer, in ter­&#xD;
    minology consistent with that to be used on the peri­&#xD;
    odic statement, each of the following items, to the&#xD;
    extent applicable:&#xD;
      “(a) Finance charge.       The circumstances under&#xD;
    which a finance charge will be imposed and an expla­&#xD;
    nation of how it will be determined, as follows:&#xD;
        .           .           .          .          .&#xD;
      “(2) A disclosure of each periodic rate that may be&#xD;
    used to compute the finance charge, the range of bal­&#xD;
    ances to which it is applicable, and the corresponding&#xD;
    annual percentage rate. When different periodic rates&#xD;
    apply to different types of transactions, the types of&#xD;
    transactions to which the periodic rates apply shall&#xD;
    also be disclosed.” (Footnotes omitted.)&#xD;
Second, §226.9(c) requires certain “[s]ubsequent disclosure&#xD;
requirements”:&#xD;
     “Change in terms—(1) Written notice required.&#xD;
    Whenever any term required to be disclosed under&#xD;
                 Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)            9&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
    §226.6 is changed or the required minimum periodic&#xD;
    payment is increased, the creditor shall mail or de­&#xD;
    liver written notice of the change to each consumer&#xD;
    who may be affected. The notice shall be mailed or&#xD;
    delivered at least 15 days prior to the effective date of&#xD;
    the change. The 15-day timing requirement does not&#xD;
    apply if the change has been agreed to by the con­&#xD;
    sumer, or if a periodic rate or other finance charge is&#xD;
    increased because of the consumer’s delinquency or&#xD;
    default; the notice shall be given, however, before the&#xD;
    effective date of the change.&#xD;
       “(2) Notice not required. No notice under this sec­&#xD;
    tion is required when the change . . . results from . . .&#xD;
    the consumer’s default or delinquency (other than an&#xD;
    increase in the periodic rate or other finance charge).”&#xD;
   The question is whether the increase in McCoy’s inter­&#xD;
est rate constitutes a change to a “term required to be&#xD;
disclosed under §226.6,” requiring a subsequent disclosure&#xD;
under §226.9(c)(1). One of the initial terms that must be&#xD;
disclosed under §226.6 is “each periodic rate that may be&#xD;
used to compute the finance charge . . . and the corre­&#xD;
sponding annual percentage rate.” §226.6(a)(2). McCoy&#xD;
argues that, because an increase in the interest rate in­&#xD;
creases the “periodic rate” applicable to his account, such&#xD;
an increase constitutes a change in terms within the&#xD;
meaning of §226.9(c)(1). As further support, McCoy points&#xD;
to two provisions in §226.9(c): first, that notice of an in­&#xD;
crease in the interest rate must be provided “before the&#xD;
effective date of the change” when the increase is due to&#xD;
“the consumer’s delinquency or default,” §226.9(c)(1); and&#xD;
second, that no notice is required of a change resulting&#xD;
“from the consumer’s default or delinquency (other than&#xD;
an increase in the periodic rate or other finance charge),”&#xD;
§226.9(c)(2).   Accordingly, because §226.9(c) includes&#xD;
interest-rate increases due to delinquency or default,&#xD;
10               CHASE BANK USA, N. A. v. MCCOY&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
McCoy argues that the plain text of the regulation indi­&#xD;
cates that a change in the periodic rate due to such default&#xD;
is a “change in terms” requiring notice under §226.9(c)(1).&#xD;
   We recognize that McCoy’s argument has some force;&#xD;
read in isolation, the language quoted above certainly&#xD;
suggests that credit card issuers must provide notice of an&#xD;
interest-rate increase imposed pursuant to cardholder&#xD;
delinquency or default. But McCoy’s analysis begs the key&#xD;
question: whether the increase actually changed a “term”&#xD;
of the Agreement that was “required to be disclosed under&#xD;
§226.6.” If not, §226.9(c)’s subsequent notice requirement&#xD;
with respect to a “change in terms” does not apply. Chase&#xD;
argues precisely this: The increase did not change a term&#xD;
in the Agreement, but merely implemented one that had&#xD;
been initially disclosed, as required. This interpretation,&#xD;
though not commanded by the text of the regulation, is&#xD;
reasonable. Section 226.6(a)(2) requires initial disclosure&#xD;
of “each periodic rate that may be used to compute the&#xD;
finance charge.” The Agreement itself discloses both the&#xD;
initial rate (Preferred rate) and the maximum rate to be&#xD;
imposed in the event of default (Non-Preferred rate). See&#xD;
Brief for Respondent 8, n. 2; Brief for Petitioner 13–14.4&#xD;
Accordingly, it is plausible to understand the Agreement&#xD;
to initially disclose “each periodic rate” to be applied to the&#xD;
account, and Chase arguably did not “change” those rates&#xD;
as a result of McCoy’s default. Instead, Chase merely&#xD;
implemented the previously disclosed term specifying the&#xD;
Non-Preferred rate.5&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  4 The Pricing Schedule referred to in the Agreement is not contained&#xD;
in the case record, nor are its contents apparent from the parties’ briefs,&#xD;
but neither side disputes that it specified a maximum Non-Preferred&#xD;
rate applicable to the Agreement.&#xD;
   5 We are not persuaded by McCoy’s argument that, although Chase&#xD;
&#xD;
did not change a “contract term” when it raised his interest rate pursu­&#xD;
ant to the terms of the Agreement, it changed a “credit term,” thereby&#xD;
triggering §226.9(c)’s notice requirement. The relevant text of Regula­&#xD;
                     Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)                   11&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
   This reading still leaves the question why §226.9(c)(1)&#xD;
refers to interest-rate increases resulting from delin­&#xD;
quency or default if such increases do not constitute a&#xD;
“change in terms.” One reasonable explanation Chase&#xD;
offers is that §226.9(c)(1) refers to interest-rate increases&#xD;
that were not specifically outlined in the agreement’s&#xD;
initial terms (unlike those in the present Agreement). For&#xD;
example, credit card agreements routinely include a “res­&#xD;
ervation of rights” provision giving the issuer discretion to&#xD;
change the terms of the contract, often as a means of&#xD;
responding to events that raise doubts about the card­&#xD;
holder’s creditworthiness. An issuer may exercise this&#xD;
general contract-modification authority and raise the&#xD;
interest rate applicable to the account to address any&#xD;
heightened risk. See Brief for Petitioner 6. In such a case,&#xD;
§226.9(c)(1) is best read to require that notice must be&#xD;
given prior to the effective date of the increase, because&#xD;
the unilateral increase instituted by the issuer actually&#xD;
changed a term—the interest rate—in a manner not spe­&#xD;
cifically contemplated by the agreement.6 See Comment&#xD;
9(c)–1 (providing that notice is required if the agreement&#xD;
“does not include specific terms for an increase (for exam­&#xD;
&#xD;
——————&#xD;
tion Z does not refer to, let alone distinguish between, “contract terms”&#xD;
and “credit terms,” and McCoy’s repeated citations to TILA’s broad&#xD;
policy statement do not convince us that such a distinction is war­&#xD;
ranted. See 15 U. S. C. §1601(a) (“It is the purpose of this subchapter&#xD;
to assure a meaningful disclosure of credit terms so that the consumer&#xD;
will be able to compare more readily the various credit terms available&#xD;
to him and avoid the uninformed use of credit”).&#xD;
   6 The Government offers an alternative example. Assume that the&#xD;
&#xD;
agreement is similar to the one at issue here, with a specified maxi­&#xD;
mum level to which the interest rate can be increased if the cardholder&#xD;
defaults. If default occurs but the issuer raises the rate above the&#xD;
contractual maximum, notice must be given prior to the effective date&#xD;
because the issuer actually changed the term of the contract initially&#xD;
specifying the maximum rate possible. See Brief for United States as&#xD;
Amicus Curiae 14–15.&#xD;
12            CHASE BANK USA, N. A. v. MCCOY&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
ple, when an increase may occur under the creditor’s&#xD;
contract reservation right to increase the periodic rate)”).&#xD;
    In short, Regulation Z is unclear with respect to the&#xD;
crucial interpretive question: whether the interest-rate&#xD;
increase at issue in this case constitutes a “change in&#xD;
terms” requiring notice. We need not decide which party’s&#xD;
interpretation is more persuasive, however; both are&#xD;
plausible, and the text alone does not permit a more de­&#xD;
finitive reading. Accordingly, we find Regulation Z to be&#xD;
ambiguous as to the question presented, and must there­&#xD;
fore look to the Board’s own interpretation of the regula­&#xD;
tion for guidance in deciding this case. See Coeur Alaska,&#xD;
Inc. v. Southeast Alaska Conservation Council, 557 U. S.&#xD;
___, ___ (2009) (slip op., at 14) (stating that when an&#xD;
agency’s regulations construing a statute “are ambiguous&#xD;
. . . we next turn to the agencies’ subsequent interpreta­&#xD;
tion of those regulations” for guidance); Ford Motor Credit&#xD;
Co. v. Milhollin, 444 U. S. 555, 560 (1980) (stating that&#xD;
when the question presented “is not governed by clear&#xD;
expression in the . . . regulation . . . it is appropriate to&#xD;
defer to the Federal Reserve Board and staff in determin­&#xD;
ing what resolution of that issue” is appropriate).&#xD;
                             B&#xD;
  The Board has made clear in the amicus brief it has&#xD;
submitted to this Court that, in the Board’s view, Chase&#xD;
was not required to give McCoy notice of the interest rate&#xD;
increase under the version of Regulation Z applicable at&#xD;
the time. Under Auer v. Robbins, 519 U. S. 452 (1997), we&#xD;
defer to an agency’s interpretation of its own regulation,&#xD;
advanced in a legal brief, unless that interpretation is&#xD;
“plainly erroneous or inconsistent with the regulation.”&#xD;
Id., at 461 (internal quotation marks omitted). Because&#xD;
the interpretation the Board presents in its brief is consis­&#xD;
tent with the regulatory text, we need look no further in&#xD;
                     Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)                    13&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
deciding this case.7&#xD;
   In its brief to this Court, the Board explains that the&#xD;
Ninth Circuit “erred in concluding that, at the time of&#xD;
the transactions at issue in this case, Regulation Z required&#xD;
credit card issuers to provide a change-in-terms notice be­&#xD;
fore implementing a contractual default-rate provision.”&#xD;
See Brief for United States as Amicus Curiae 11; see also&#xD;
ibid. (stating that when a term of an agreement author­&#xD;
ized the credit provider “to increase a consumer’s interest&#xD;
rate if the consumer failed to make timely payments . . .&#xD;
any resulting rate increase did not represent a ‘change in&#xD;
terms,’ but rather the implementation of terms already set&#xD;
forth in the initial disclosure statement”); id., at 15–16&#xD;
(stating that “[w]hen a cardholder agreement identifies a&#xD;
contingency that triggers a rate increase, and the maxi­&#xD;
mum possible rate that the issuer may charge if that&#xD;
contingency occurs,” then “no change-in-terms notice is&#xD;
required” under Regulation Z).8 Under the principles set&#xD;
forth in Auer, we give deference to this interpretation.&#xD;
   In Auer we deferred to the Secretary of Labor’s interpre­&#xD;
tation of his own regulation, presented in an amicus brief&#xD;
submitted by the agency at our invitation. 519 U. S., at&#xD;
&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  7 We note that, in reaching its decision, the Ninth Circuit did not&#xD;
&#xD;
have the benefit of briefing from the Board. The Ninth Circuit appar­&#xD;
ently did not solicit the views of the Board in the proceedings below, see&#xD;
Brief for Petitioner 16, and the First Circuit did not solicit the Board’s&#xD;
views in Shaner v. Chase Bank USA, N. A., 587 F. 3d 488 (2009), until&#xD;
after the Ninth Circuit issued its opinion in this case, see Order in No.&#xD;
09–1157 (CA1, Aug. 4, 2009).&#xD;
  8 This is consistent with the view the Board advanced in its amicus&#xD;
&#xD;
brief to the First Circuit, in which the Board noted that it “has in­&#xD;
terpreted the applicable provisions of Regulation Z not to require a&#xD;
pre-effective date change-in-terms notice for an increase in annual per­&#xD;
centage rate when the contingency that will trigger a rate increase and&#xD;
the specific consequences for the consumer’s rate are set forth in the&#xD;
initial card member agreement.” App. to Brief for United States as&#xD;
Amicus Curiae 2a.&#xD;
14            CHASE BANK USA, N. A. v. MCCOY&#xD;
&#xD;
                      Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
461–462. Responding to the petitioners’ objection that the&#xD;
agency’s interpretation came in a legal brief, we held that&#xD;
this fact did not, “in the circumstances of this case, make&#xD;
it unworthy of deference.” Id., at 462. We observed that&#xD;
“[t]he Secretary’s position is in no sense a ‘post hoc ration­&#xD;
alizatio[n]’ advanced by an agency seeking to defend past&#xD;
agency action against attack.” Ibid. (quoting Bowen v.&#xD;
Georgetown Univ. Hospital, 488 U. S. 204, 212 (1988)). We&#xD;
added: “There is simply no reason to suspect that the&#xD;
interpretation does not reflect the agency’s fair and con­&#xD;
sidered judgment on the matter in question.” Auer, 519&#xD;
U. S., at 462.&#xD;
   The brief submitted by the Board in the present case, at&#xD;
our invitation, is no different. As in Auer, there is no&#xD;
reason to believe that the interpretation advanced by the&#xD;
Board is a “post hoc rationalization” taken as a litigation&#xD;
position. The Board is not a party to this case. And as is&#xD;
evident from our discussion of Regulation Z itself, see Part&#xD;
II–A, supra, the Board’s interpretation is neither “plainly&#xD;
erroneous” nor “inconsistent with” the indeterminate text&#xD;
of the regulation. In short, there is no reason to suspect&#xD;
that the position the Board takes in its amicus brief re­&#xD;
flects anything other than the agency’s fair and considered&#xD;
judgment as to what the regulation required at the time&#xD;
this dispute arose.&#xD;
   McCoy may well be correct in asserting that it is better&#xD;
policy to oblige credit-card issuers to give advance notice&#xD;
of a rate increase; after all, both Congress and the Board&#xD;
have recently indicated that such a requirement is war­&#xD;
ranted. See Credit CARD Act, §101(a)(1), 123 Stat. 1735–&#xD;
1736; 12 CFR §226.9(g) (2009). That Congress and the&#xD;
Board may currently hold such views does not mean,&#xD;
however, that deference is not warranted to the Board’s&#xD;
different understanding of what the pre-2009 version of&#xD;
Regulation Z required. To the contrary, the interpretation&#xD;
the Board advances in its amicus brief is entirely consis­&#xD;
                 Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)          15&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
tent with its past views. The 2004 notice of rulemaking&#xD;
and the 2007 proposed amendments to Regulation Z make&#xD;
clear that, prior to 2009, the Board’s fair and considered&#xD;
judgment was that “no change-in-terms notice is required&#xD;
if the creditor specifies in advance the circumstances&#xD;
under which an increase . . . will occur,” 69 Fed. Reg.&#xD;
70931, and “immediate application of penalty pricing upon&#xD;
the occurrence of certain events specified in the contract”&#xD;
was permissible, 72 Fed. Reg. 33012.&#xD;
   Under Auer, therefore, it is clear that deference to the&#xD;
interpretation in the Board’s amicus brief is warranted.&#xD;
The cases McCoy cites in which we declined to apply Auer&#xD;
do not suggest that deference is unwarranted here. In&#xD;
Gonzales v. Oregon, 546 U. S. 243 (2006), we declined to&#xD;
defer because—in sharp contrast to the present case—&#xD;
the regulation in question did “little more than restate the&#xD;
terms of the statute” pursuant to which the regulation was&#xD;
promulgated. Id., at 257. Accordingly, no deference was&#xD;
warranted to an agency interpretation of what were, in&#xD;
fact, Congress’ words. Ibid. In contrast, at the time of the&#xD;
transactions in this case, TILA itself included no require­&#xD;
ments with respect to the disclosure of a change in credit&#xD;
terms. In Christensen v. Harris County, 529 U. S. 576&#xD;
(2000), we declined to apply Auer deference because the&#xD;
regulation in question was unambiguous, and adopting the&#xD;
agency’s contrary interpretation would “permit the agency,&#xD;
under the guise of interpreting a regulation, to create de&#xD;
facto a new regulation.” 529 U. S., at 588. In light of&#xD;
Regulation Z’s ambiguity, there is no such danger here.&#xD;
And our statement in Christensen that “deference is war­&#xD;
ranted only when the language of the regulation is am­&#xD;
biguous,” ibid., is perfectly consonant with Auer itself; if&#xD;
the text of a regulation is unambiguous, a conflicting&#xD;
agency interpretation advanced in an amicus brief will&#xD;
necessarily be “plainly erroneous or inconsistent with the&#xD;
regulation” in question. Auer, 519 U. S., at 461 (internal&#xD;
16               CHASE BANK USA, N. A. v. MCCOY&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
quotation marks omitted). Accordingly, under our prece­&#xD;
dent deference to the Board’s interpretation of its own&#xD;
regulation, as presented in the agency’s amicus brief, is&#xD;
wholly appropriate.&#xD;
                             C&#xD;
  McCoy further argues that deference to a legal brief is&#xD;
inappropriate because the interpretation of Regulation Z&#xD;
in the Official Staff Commentary commands a different&#xD;
result. To be sure, the Official Staff Commentary promul­&#xD;
gated by the Board as an interpretation of Regulation Z&#xD;
may warrant deference as a general matter. See Anderson&#xD;
Bros. Ford v. Valencia, 452 U. S. 205, 219 (1981) (holding&#xD;
that “the Board’s interpretation of its own regulation”&#xD;
should generally “be accepted by the courts”); Milhollin,&#xD;
444 U. S., at 565 (“Unless demonstrably irrational, Fed­&#xD;
eral Reserve Board staff opinions construing [TILA] or&#xD;
Regulation [Z] should be dispositive”). We find, however,&#xD;
that the Commentary at issue here largely replicates the&#xD;
ambiguity present in the regulatory text, and therefore it&#xD;
offers us nothing to which we can defer with respect to the&#xD;
precise interpretive question before us.9 Cf. Smith v. City&#xD;
——————&#xD;
   9 We are not persuaded by McCoy’s argument that the Board’s own&#xD;
&#xD;
regulations make the Official Staff Commentary “the exclusive source of&#xD;
authorized staff opinion.” Brief for Respondent 36 (emphasis added).&#xD;
In the regulations McCoy cites the Board has indicated only that the&#xD;
central purpose of the Commentary is to present agency interpretations&#xD;
that, if relied upon, provide the basis for invoking the good-faith de­&#xD;
fense to liability under TILA. See 15 U. S. C. §1640(f) (precluding&#xD;
liability for “any act done or omitted in good faith in conformity . . .&#xD;
with any interpretation . . . by an official or employee . . . duly author­&#xD;
ized by the Board to issue such interpretations . . . under such proce­&#xD;
dures as the Board may prescribe”); 12 CFR pt. 226, App. C (2008)&#xD;
(“[O]fficial staff interpretations of this regulation . . . provide the&#xD;
protection afforded under [§1640(f)]”); id., Supp. I, Introduction ¶1, p.&#xD;
451 (same); 46 Fed. Reg. 50288 (1981) (same). McCoy cites no authority&#xD;
indicating that, in promulgating the Commentary and establishing&#xD;
certain statutory safe harbors, the Board intended to limit its ability to&#xD;
                     Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)         17&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
of Jackson, 544 U. S. 228, 248 (2005) (O’Connor, J., con­&#xD;
curring in judgment) (noting that deference is not war­&#xD;
ranted when “there is no reasoned agency reading of the&#xD;
text to which we might defer”).&#xD;
   The Ninth Circuit relied primarily on Comment 9(c)(1)–&#xD;
3, which states in relevant part that “a notice of change in&#xD;
terms is required, but it may be mailed or delivered as late&#xD;
as the effective date of the change . . . [i]f there is an&#xD;
increased periodic rate or any other finance charge attri­&#xD;
butable to the consumer’s delinquency or default.” This&#xD;
exposition of the regulation does not add any clarity to the&#xD;
regulatory text, which expresses the same requirement.&#xD;
See §226.9(c)(1) (2008) (“[I]f a periodic rate or other fi­&#xD;
nance charge is increased because of the consumer’s delin­&#xD;
quency or default . . . notice shall be given . . . before the&#xD;
effective date of the change”). And like §226.9(c), Com­&#xD;
ment 9(c) is entitled “Change in terms.” Accordingly,&#xD;
Chase’s plausible interpretation of §226.9(c)(1) is equally&#xD;
applicable to Comment 9(c)(1)–3: On Chase’s view, be­&#xD;
cause the interest-rate increase at issue in this case did&#xD;
not constitute a “change in terms,” the disclosure require­&#xD;
ments in the regulation and Commentary simply do not&#xD;
come into play. See supra, at 10–11.&#xD;
   Comment 9(c)–1 is also ambiguous, though the most&#xD;
plausible reading supports Chase’s position more than it&#xD;
does McCoy’s. The Comment begins: “No notice of a&#xD;
change in terms need be given if the specific change is set&#xD;
forth initially” in the agreement. We do not find that the&#xD;
Comment’s addition of the modifier “specific” to the word&#xD;
“change” enables us to determine, any more than we could&#xD;
in light of the text of the regulation, see supra, at 12,&#xD;
whether the interest-rate increase at issue in this case&#xD;
was a “change in terms” requiring notice. According to&#xD;
Chase, as long as the agreement explains that delinquency&#xD;
—————— &#xD;
&#xD;
issue authoritative interpretations for other purposes. &#xD;
&#xD;
18               CHASE BANK USA, N. A. v. MCCOY&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
or default might trigger an increased interest rate and&#xD;
states the maximum level to which the rate could be in­&#xD;
creased, the “specific change” that ensues upon default has&#xD;
been set forth initially and no additional notice is required&#xD;
before implementation. McCoy argues to the contrary:&#xD;
Under Comment 9(c)–1, any new rate imposed after delin­&#xD;
quency or default must be disclosed prior to the effective&#xD;
date, if the particular rate (rather than the maximum&#xD;
rate) was not specifically mentioned in the agreement. On&#xD;
the whole, then, the Official Staff Commentary’s explana­&#xD;
tion of Regulation Z does not resolve the uncertainty in the&#xD;
regulatory text, and offers us no reason to disregard&#xD;
the interpretation advanced in the Board’s amicus brief.10&#xD;
——————&#xD;
   10 In concluding otherwise, the Ninth Circuit focused on the examples&#xD;
&#xD;
Comment 9(c)–1 provides of changes that, if set forth initially, require&#xD;
no further disclosure when put into effect:&#xD;
“No notice of a change in terms need be given if the specific change is&#xD;
set forth initially, such as: Rate increases under a properly disclosed&#xD;
variable-rate plan, a rate increase that occurs when an employee has&#xD;
been under a preferential rate agreement and terminates employment,&#xD;
or an increase that occurs when the consumer has been under an&#xD;
agreement to maintain a certain balance in a savings account in order&#xD;
to keep a particular rate and the account balance falls below the&#xD;
specified minimum.”&#xD;
   The Ninth Circuit concluded that, in contrast to each of these three&#xD;
examples, “the increase here occurs at Chase’s discretion.” 559 F. 3d&#xD;
963, 966 (2009). That is, once the triggering event—McCoy’s default—&#xD;
occurred, Chase had the latitude to increase the interest rate as it saw&#xD;
fit (up to the limit specified in the Pricing Schedule).&#xD;
   We are not persuaded by the Ninth Circuit’s reasoning. Certainly,&#xD;
under a “variable-rate” plan the interest rate fluctuates according to an&#xD;
external variable easily discernable by the cardholder (like the Federal&#xD;
Prime rate), and the issuer has no discretion. See ibid. But the Com­&#xD;
ment’s second and third examples do not appear to be significantly&#xD;
different from this case: The agreement contains a preset rate, but it&#xD;
also provides that, on the occurrence of a predefined event (terminating&#xD;
employment or a low account balance), the rate will increase.&#xD;
   Moreover, Comment 9(c)–1 further states that notice is needed “if the&#xD;
contract allows the creditor to increase the rate at its discretion but&#xD;
does not include specific terms for an increase”—for example, “when an&#xD;
                     Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)                   19&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
  McCoy further contends that our reliance here on an&#xD;
agency interpretation presented outside the four corners of&#xD;
the Official Staff Commentary will require future liti­&#xD;
gants, as well as the Board, to expend time and resources&#xD;
“to comb through . . . correspondence, publications, and&#xD;
the agency’s website to determine the agency’s position.”&#xD;
Brief for Respondent 37–38. We are not convinced.&#xD;
McCoy may be correct that the Board established the&#xD;
Official Staff Commentary so as to centralize its opinion­&#xD;
making process and avoid “overburdening the industry&#xD;
with excessive detail and multiple research sources.” 46&#xD;
Fed. Reg. 50288. But his suggestion that, if we accord&#xD;
deference to an amicus brief, all other “unofficial” sources&#xD;
will be fair game is of no moment. Today we decide only&#xD;
that the amicus brief submitted by the Board is entitled to&#xD;
deference in light of “the circumstances of this case.”&#xD;
Auer, 519 U. S., at 462.&#xD;
  Accordingly, we conclude that, at the time of the trans­&#xD;
actions at issue in this case, Regulation Z did not require&#xD;
Chase to provide McCoy with a change-in-terms notice&#xD;
before it implemented the Agreement term allowing it to&#xD;
raise his interest rate following delinquency or default.&#xD;
                        *   *    *&#xD;
  For the foregoing reasons, the judgment of the United&#xD;
States Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit is reversed,&#xD;
and the case is remanded for further proceedings consis­&#xD;
tent with this opinion.&#xD;
                                          It is so ordered.&#xD;
——————&#xD;
increase may occur under the creditor’s contract reservation right to&#xD;
increase the periodic rate.” It would seem that the narrower latitude&#xD;
Chase had under the Agreement to set the precise new rate within a&#xD;
specified range after McCoy defaulted is not the kind of “discretion” the&#xD;
last example of Comment 9(c)–1 contemplates. In short, analogizing to&#xD;
the Comment’s examples suggests that Chase’s action in setting a new&#xD;
rate was most likely a “specific change” that the Agreement itself&#xD;
contemplated, and subsequent disclosure was not clearly required.&#xD;
&lt;/pre&gt;</opinion>