<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><opinion id="1992692" path="/scotus/bdmL/maryland-v-blake/" sha1="ffd50f25844f69e60a79f6c53c2adabb98cf0e38" court="Supreme Court of the United States" download_URL="/sata/lawbox/dump/gov.us.courts.united_states_reports/1st/546/Maryland_v._Blake,_546_US_72.html" time_retrieved="2013-10-30 07:59:45.318670+00:00" date_filed="2005-11-14" precedential_status="Published" local_path="" docket_number="04-373" federal_cite_one="546 U.S. 72" case_name="Maryland v. Blake" judges="Per Curiam" nature_of_suit="" source="lawbox" blocked="False" date_blocked="None" extracted_by_ocr="False">&lt;div&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;b&gt;546 U.S. 72 (2005)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h1&gt;MARYLAND&lt;br&gt;
v.&lt;br&gt;
BLAKE.&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;No. 04-373.&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Supreme Court of United States.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;Argued November 1, 2005.&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;Decided November 14, 2005&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Kathryn Grill Graeff,&lt;/i&gt; Assistant Attorney General of Maryland, argued the cause for petitioner. With her on the briefs were &lt;i&gt;J. Joseph Curran, Jr.,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General, and &lt;i&gt;Annabelle L. Lisic&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Diane E. Keller,&lt;/i&gt; Assistant Attorneys General.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;James A. Feldman&lt;/i&gt; argued the cause for the United States as &lt;i&gt;amicus curiae&lt;/i&gt; urging reversal. With him on the brief were &lt;i&gt;Solicitor General Clement, Acting Assistant Attorney General Richter, Deputy Solicitor General Dreeben, John P. Elwood,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Joel M. Gershowitz.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Kenneth W. Ravenell&lt;/i&gt; argued the cause for respondent. With him on the brief were &lt;i&gt;Ivan J. Bates, Matthew A. S. Esworthy,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Jeffrey T. Green.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[*]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="star-pagination"&gt;*73&lt;/span&gt; PER CURIAM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The writ of certiorari is dismissed as improvidently granted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;It is so ordered.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;NOTES&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[*]  Briefs of &lt;i&gt;amici curiae&lt;/i&gt; urging reversal were filed for the State of Texas et al. by &lt;i&gt;Greg Abbott,&lt;/i&gt; Attorney General of Texas, &lt;i&gt;Barry R. McBee,&lt;/i&gt; First Assistant Attorney General, &lt;i&gt;R. Ted Cruz,&lt;/i&gt; Solicitor General, &lt;i&gt;Don Clemmer,&lt;/i&gt; Deputy Attorney General, and &lt;i&gt;Gena Bunn, Edward L. Marshall,&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Fredericka Sargent,&lt;/i&gt; Assistant Attorneys General, and by the Attorneys General for their respective jurisdictions as follows: &lt;i&gt;M. Jane Brady&lt;/i&gt; of Delaware, &lt;i&gt;Robert J. Spagnoletti&lt;/i&gt; of the District of Columbia, &lt;i&gt;Charles J. Crist, Jr.,&lt;/i&gt; of Florida, &lt;i&gt;Mark J. Bennett&lt;/i&gt; of Hawaii, &lt;i&gt;Lawrence G. Wasden&lt;/i&gt; of Idaho, &lt;i&gt;Lisa Madigan&lt;/i&gt; of Illinois, &lt;i&gt;Michael A. Cox&lt;/i&gt; of Michigan, &lt;i&gt;Jim Petro&lt;/i&gt; of Ohio, &lt;i&gt;W. A. Drew Edmondson&lt;/i&gt; of Oklahoma, &lt;i&gt;Hardy Myers&lt;/i&gt; of Oregon, &lt;i&gt;Thomas W. Corbett, Jr.,&lt;/i&gt; of Pennsylvania, &lt;i&gt;Henry D. McMaster&lt;/i&gt; of South Carolina, &lt;i&gt;Lawrence E. Long&lt;/i&gt; of South Dakota, &lt;i&gt;Mark L. Shurtleff&lt;/i&gt; of Utah, and &lt;i&gt;William Sorrell&lt;/i&gt; of Vermont; and for the Criminal Justice Legal Foundation by &lt;i&gt;Kent S. Scheidegger&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Charles L. Hobson.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Briefs of &lt;i&gt;amici curiae&lt;/i&gt; urging affirmance were filed for the National Association of Criminal Defense Lawyers by &lt;i&gt;James J. Tomkovicz&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Joshua L. Dratel;&lt;/i&gt; and for the National Legal Aid and Defender Association by &lt;i&gt;Steven B. Duke.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;</opinion>