<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><opinion id="205606" path="/scotus/247W/michigan-v-bryant/" sha1="068b4dc3f669569d4dd643d4719e77a483a6bc06" court="Supreme Court of the United States" download_URL="http://www.supremecourt.gov/opinions/10pdf/09-150.pdf" time_retrieved="2011-02-28 15:36:05+00:00" date_filed="2012-02-22" precedential_status="Published" local_path="pdf/2011/02/28/Michigan_v._Bryant.pdf" docket_number="09-150" federal_cite_one="" lexis_cite="" case_name="Michigan v. Bryant" judges="" nature_of_suit="" source="court website" blocked="False" date_blocked="None" extracted_by_ocr="False">&lt;pre class="inline"&gt;(Slip Opinion)              OCTOBER TERM, 2010                                       1&#xD;
&#xD;
                                       Syllabus&#xD;
&#xD;
         NOTE: Where it is feasible, a syllabus (headnote) will be released, as is&#xD;
       being done in connection with this case, at the time the opinion is issued.&#xD;
       The syllabus constitutes no part of the opinion of the Court but has been&#xD;
       prepared by the Reporter of Decisions for the convenience of the reader.&#xD;
       See United States v. Detroit Timber &amp; Lumber Co., 200 U. S. 321, 337.&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES&#xD;
&#xD;
                                       Syllabus&#xD;
&#xD;
                         MICHIGAN v. BRYANT&#xD;
&#xD;
       CERTIORARI TO THE SUPREME COURT OF MICHIGAN&#xD;
&#xD;
   No. 09–150.      Argued October 5, 2010—Decided February 28, 2011&#xD;
Michigan police dispatched to a gas station parking lot found Anthony&#xD;
 Covington mortally wounded. Covington told them that he had been&#xD;
 shot by respondent Bryant outside Bryant’s house and had then&#xD;
 driven himself to the lot. At trial, which occurred before Crawford v.&#xD;
 Washington, 541 U. S. 36, and Davis v. Washington, 547 U. S. 813,&#xD;
 were decided, the officers testified about what Covington said. Bry&#xD;
 ant was found guilty of, inter alia, second-degree murder. Ulti&#xD;
 mately, the Michigan Supreme Court reversed his conviction, holding&#xD;
 that the Sixth Amendment’s Confrontation Clause, as explained in&#xD;
 Crawford and Davis, rendered Covington’s statements inadmissible&#xD;
 testimonial hearsay.&#xD;
Held: Covington’s identification and description of the shooter and the&#xD;
 location of the shooting were not testimonial statements because they&#xD;
 had a “primary purpose . . . to enable police assistance to meet an on&#xD;
 going emergency.” Davis, 547 U. S., at 822. Therefore, their admis&#xD;
 sion at Bryant’s trial did not violate the Confrontation Clause. Pp. 5–&#xD;
 32.&#xD;
    (a) In Crawford, this Court held that in order for testimonial evi&#xD;
 dence to be admissible, the Sixth Amendment “demands . . . unavail&#xD;
 ability and a prior opportunity for cross-examination.” 541 U. S., at&#xD;
 68. Crawford did not “spell out a comprehensive definition of ‘testi&#xD;
 monial,’ ” but it noted that testimonial evidence includes, among&#xD;
 other things, “police interrogations.” Ibid. Thus, Sylvia Crawford’s&#xD;
 statements during a station-house interrogation about a stabbing&#xD;
 were testimonial, and their admission when her husband, the ac&#xD;
 cused, had “no opportunity” for cross-examination due to spousal&#xD;
 privilege made out a Sixth Amendment violation. In Davis and&#xD;
 Hammon, both domestic violence cases, the Court explained that&#xD;
 “[s]tatements are nontestimonial when made in the course of police&#xD;
2                         MICHIGAN v. BRYANT&#xD;
&#xD;
                                  Syllabus&#xD;
&#xD;
    interrogation under circumstances objectively indicating that the [in&#xD;
    terrogation’s] primary purpose . . . is to enable police assistance to&#xD;
    meet an ongoing emergency,” but they “are testimonial when the cir&#xD;
    cumstances objectively indicate that there is no such ongoing emer&#xD;
    gency, and that the [interrogation’s] primary purpose is to establish&#xD;
    or prove past events potentially relevant to later criminal prosecu&#xD;
    tion.” 547 U. S., at 822. Thus, a recording of a 911 call describing an&#xD;
    ongoing domestic disturbance was nontestimonial in Davis, where&#xD;
    the victim’s “elicited statements were necessary to be able to resolve&#xD;
    [the ongoing] emergency,” and the statements were not formal. Id.,&#xD;
    at 827. But the statements in Hammon were testimonial, where the&#xD;
    victim was interviewed after the event in a room separate from her&#xD;
    husband and “deliberately recounted, in response to police question&#xD;
    ing” the past events. Id., at 830. Here, the context is a nondomestic&#xD;
    dispute, with the “ongoing emergency” extending beyond an initial&#xD;
    victim to a potential threat to the responding police and the public.&#xD;
    This context requires additional clarification of what Davis meant by&#xD;
    “the primary purpose of the interrogation is to enable police assis&#xD;
    tance to meet an ongoing emergency.” Id., at 822. Pp. 5–12.&#xD;
       (b) To make the “primary purpose” determination, the Court must&#xD;
    objectively evaluate the circumstances in which the encounter be&#xD;
    tween the individual and the police occurs and the parties’ state&#xD;
    ments and actions. Pp. 12–23.&#xD;
         (1) The primary purpose inquiry is objective. The circumstances&#xD;
    in which an encounter occurs—e.g., at or near a crime scene versus at&#xD;
    a police station, during an ongoing emergency or afterwards—are&#xD;
    clearly matters of objective fact. And the relevant inquiry into the&#xD;
    parties’ statements and actions is not the subjective or actual purpose&#xD;
    of the particular parties, but the purpose that reasonable partici&#xD;
    pants would have had, as ascertained from the parties’ statements&#xD;
    and actions and the circumstances in which the encounter occurred.&#xD;
    P. 13.&#xD;
         (2) The existence of an “ongoing emergency” at the time of the&#xD;
    encounter is among the most important circumstances informing the&#xD;
    interrogation’s “primary purpose.” See, e.g., Davis, 547 U. S., at 828–&#xD;
    830. An emergency focuses the participants not on “prov[ing] past&#xD;
    events potentially relevant to later criminal prosecution,” id., at 822,&#xD;
    but on “end[ing] a threatening situation,” id., at 832. The Michigan&#xD;
    Supreme Court failed to appreciate that whether an emergency exists&#xD;
    and is ongoing is a highly context-dependent inquiry. An assessment&#xD;
    of whether an emergency threatening the police and public is ongoing&#xD;
    cannot narrowly focus on whether the threat to the first victim has&#xD;
    been neutralized because the threat to the first responders and public&#xD;
    may continue. The State Supreme Court also did not appreciate that&#xD;
                   Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)                    3&#xD;
&#xD;
                              Syllabus&#xD;
&#xD;
an emergency’s duration and scope may depend in part on the type of&#xD;
weapon involved; the court below relied on Davis and Hammon,&#xD;
where the assailants used their fists, as controlling the scope of an&#xD;
emergency involving a gun. A victim’s medical condition is important&#xD;
to the primary purpose inquiry to the extent that it sheds light on the&#xD;
victim’s ability to have any purpose at all in responding to police&#xD;
questions and on the likelihood that any such purpose would be a tes&#xD;
timonial one. It also provides important context for first responders&#xD;
to judge the existence and magnitude of a continuing threat to the&#xD;
victim, themselves, and the public. This does not mean that an&#xD;
emergency lasts the entire time that a perpetrator is on the loose, but&#xD;
trial courts can determine in the first instance when an interrogation&#xD;
transitions from nontestimonial to testimonial. Finally, whether an&#xD;
ongoing emergency exists is simply one factor informing the ultimate&#xD;
inquiry regarding an interrogation’s “primary purpose.” Another is&#xD;
the encounter’s informality. Formality suggests the absence of an&#xD;
emergency, but informality does not necessarily indicate the presence&#xD;
of an emergency or the lack of testimonial intent. The facts here—&#xD;
the questioning occurred in an exposed, public area, before emer&#xD;
gency medical services arrived, and in a disorganized fashion—&#xD;
distinguish this case from Crawford’s formal station-house interroga&#xD;
tion. Pp. 14–20.&#xD;
      (3) The statements and actions of both the declarant and interro&#xD;
gators also provide objective evidence of the interrogation’s primary&#xD;
purpose. Looking to the contents of both the questions and the an&#xD;
swers ameliorates problems that could arise from looking solely to&#xD;
one participant, since both interrogators and declarants may have&#xD;
mixed motives. Police officers’ dual responsibilities as both first re&#xD;
sponders and criminal investigators may lead them to act with differ&#xD;
ent motives simultaneously or in quick succession. And during an&#xD;
ongoing emergency, victims may want the threat to end, but may not&#xD;
envision prosecution. Alternatively, a severely injured victim may&#xD;
have no purpose at all in answering questions. Taking into account&#xD;
such injuries does not make the inquiry subjective. The inquiry still&#xD;
focuses on the understanding and purpose of a reasonable victim in&#xD;
the actual victim’s circumstances, which prominently include the vic&#xD;
tim’s physical state. Objectively ascertaining the primary purpose of&#xD;
the interrogation by examining the statements and actions of all par&#xD;
ticipants is also consistent with this Court’s prior holdings. E.g.,&#xD;
Davis, 547 U. S., at 822–823, n. 1. Pp. 20–23.&#xD;
   (c) Here, the circumstances of the encounter as well as the state&#xD;
ments and actions of Covington and the police objectively indicate&#xD;
that the interrogation’s “primary purpose” was “to enable police as&#xD;
sistance to meet an ongoing emergency,” 547 U. S., at 822. The cir&#xD;
4                        MICHIGAN v. BRYANT&#xD;
&#xD;
                                 Syllabus&#xD;
&#xD;
    cumstances of the interrogation involved an armed shooter, whose&#xD;
    motive for and location after the shooting were unknown and who&#xD;
    had mortally wounded Covington within a few blocks and a few min&#xD;
    utes of the location where police found Covington. Unlike the emer&#xD;
    gencies in Davis and Hammon, this dispute’s potential scope and&#xD;
    thus the emergency encompassed a potential threat to the police and&#xD;
    the public. And since this case involved a gun, the physical separa&#xD;
    tion that was sufficient to end the emergency in Hammon was not&#xD;
    necessarily sufficient to end the threat here. Informed by the circum&#xD;
    stances of the ongoing emergency, the Court now turns to determin&#xD;
    ing the “primary purpose of the interrogation” as evidenced by the&#xD;
    statements and actions of Covington and the police. The circum&#xD;
    stances of the encounter provide important context for understanding&#xD;
    Covington’s statements to the police. When he responded to their&#xD;
    questions, he was lying in a gas station parking lot bleeding from a&#xD;
    mortal gunshot wound, and his answers were punctuated with ques&#xD;
    tions about when emergency medical services would arrive. Thus,&#xD;
    this Court cannot say that a person in his situation would have had a&#xD;
    “primary purpose” “to establish or prove past events potentially rele&#xD;
    vant to later criminal prosecution.” Ibid. For their part, the police&#xD;
    responded to a call that a man had been shot. They did not know&#xD;
    why, where, or when the shooting had occurred; the shooter’s loca&#xD;
    tion; or anything else about the crime. They asked exactly the type of&#xD;
    questions necessary to enable them “to meet an ongoing emergency.”&#xD;
    Ibid. Nothing in Covington’s responses indicated to the police that&#xD;
    there was no emergency or that the emergency had ended. Finally,&#xD;
    this situation is more similar to the informal, harried 911 call in&#xD;
    Davis than to the structured, station-house interview in Crawford.&#xD;
    The officers all arrived at different times; asked, upon arrival, what&#xD;
    had happened; and generally did not conduct a structured interroga&#xD;
    tion. The informality suggests that their primary purpose was to ad&#xD;
    dress what they considered to be an ongoing emergency, and the cir&#xD;
    cumstances lacked a formality that would have alerted Covington to&#xD;
    or focused him on the possible future prosecutorial use of his state&#xD;
    ments. Pp. 23–32.&#xD;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;span class="citation"&gt;&lt;a href="/mich/5hKN/people-v-bryant/"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;483&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;Mich.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;132&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;pre class="inline"&gt;, 768 N. W. 2d 65, vacated and remanded.&#xD;
&#xD;
   SOTOMAYOR, J., delivered the opinion of the Court, in which ROBERTS,&#xD;
C. J., and KENNEDY, BREYER, and ALITO, JJ., joined. THOMAS, J., filed&#xD;
an opinion concurring in the judgment. SCALIA, J., and GINSBURG, J.,&#xD;
filed dissenting opinions. KAGAN, J., took no part in the consideration&#xD;
or decision of the case.&#xD;
                        Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)                              1&#xD;
&#xD;
                             Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
     NOTICE: This opinion is subject to formal revision before publication in the&#xD;
     preliminary print of the United States Reports. Readers are requested to&#xD;
     notify the Reporter of Decisions, Supreme Court of the United States, Wash&#xD;
     ington, D. C. 20543, of any typographical or other formal errors, in order&#xD;
     that corrections may be made before the preliminary print goes to press.&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES&#xD;
                                   _________________&#xD;
&#xD;
                                   No. 09–150&#xD;
                                   _________________&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
    MICHIGAN, PETITIONER v. RICHARD PERRY &#xD;
&#xD;
                   BRYANT &#xD;
&#xD;
      ON WRIT OF CERTIORARI TO THE SUPREME COURT&#xD;
&#xD;
                      OF MICHIGAN&#xD;
&#xD;
                              [February 28, 2011] &#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
   JUSTICE SOTOMAYOR delivered the opinion of the Court.&#xD;
   At respondent Richard Bryant’s trial, the court admitted&#xD;
statements that the victim, Anthony Covington, made to&#xD;
police officers who discovered him mortally wounded in a&#xD;
gas station parking lot. A jury convicted Bryant of, inter&#xD;
alia, second-degree murder. &lt;/pre&gt;&lt;span class="citation"&gt;&lt;a href="/mich/5hKN/people-v-bryant/"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;483&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;Mich.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;132&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;pre class="inline"&gt;, 137, 768&#xD;
N. W. 2d 65, 67–68 (2009). On appeal, the Supreme Court&#xD;
of Michigan held that the Sixth Amendment’s Confronta&#xD;
tion Clause, as explained in our decisions in Crawford v.&#xD;
Washington, 541 U. S. 36 (2004), and Davis v. Washington,&#xD;
547 U. S. 813 (2006), rendered Covington’s statements&#xD;
inadmissible testimonial hearsay, and the court reversed&#xD;
Bryant’s conviction. 483 Mich., at 157, 768 N. W. 2d, at&#xD;
79. We granted the State’s petition for a writ of certiorari&#xD;
to consider whether the Confrontation Clause barred the&#xD;
admission at trial of Covington’s statements to the police.&#xD;
We hold that the circumstances of the interaction between&#xD;
Covington and the police objectively indicate that the&#xD;
“primary purpose of the interrogation” was “to enable&#xD;
police assistance to meet an ongoing emergency.” Davis,&#xD;
547 U. S., at 822. Therefore, Covington’s identification&#xD;
2                  MICHIGAN v. BRYANT&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
and description of the shooter and the location of the&#xD;
shooting were not testimonial statements, and their ad&#xD;
mission at Bryant’s trial did not violate the Confrontation&#xD;
Clause. We vacate the judgment of the Supreme Court of&#xD;
Michigan and remand.&#xD;
                              I&#xD;
  Around 3:25 a.m. on April 29, 2001, Detroit, Michigan&#xD;
police officers responded to a radio dispatch indicating&#xD;
that a man had been shot. At the scene, they found the&#xD;
victim, Anthony Covington, lying on the ground next to his&#xD;
car in a gas station parking lot. Covington had a gunshot&#xD;
wound to his abdomen, appeared to be in great pain, and&#xD;
spoke with difficulty.&#xD;
  The police asked him “what had happened, who had&#xD;
shot him, and where the shooting had occurred.” 483&#xD;
Mich., at 143, 768 N. W. 2d, at 71. Covington stated that&#xD;
“Rick” shot him at around 3 a.m. Id., at 136, and n. 1, 768&#xD;
N. W. 2d, at 67, and n. 1. He also indicated that he had a&#xD;
conversation with Bryant, whom he recognized based on&#xD;
his voice, through the back door of Bryant’s house. Cov&#xD;
ington explained that when he turned to leave, he was&#xD;
shot through the door and then drove to the gas station,&#xD;
where police found him.&#xD;
  Covington’s conversation with the police ended within 5&#xD;
to 10 minutes when emergency medical services arrived.&#xD;
Covington was transported to a hospital and died within&#xD;
hours. The police left the gas station after speaking with&#xD;
Covington, called for backup, and traveled to Bryant’s&#xD;
house. They did not find Bryant there but did find blood&#xD;
and a bullet on the back porch and an apparent bullet hole&#xD;
in the back door. Police also found Covington’s wallet and&#xD;
identification outside the house.&#xD;
  At trial, which occurred prior to our decisions in Craw&#xD;
ford, 541 U. S. 36, and Davis, 547 U. S. 813, the police&#xD;
officers who spoke with Covington at the gas station testi&#xD;
                 Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)           3&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
fied about what Covington had told them. The jury re&#xD;
turned a guilty verdict on charges of second-degree&#xD;
murder, being a felon in possession of a firearm, and pos&#xD;
session of a firearm during the commission of a felony.&#xD;
   Bryant appealed, and the Michigan Court of Appeals&#xD;
affirmed his conviction. No. 247039, &lt;/pre&gt;&lt;span class="citation no-link"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;2004&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;WL&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;1882661&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;pre class="inline"&gt;&#xD;
(Aug. 24, 2004) (per curiam). Bryant then appealed to the&#xD;
Supreme Court of Michigan, arguing that the trial court&#xD;
erred in admitting Covington’s statements to the police.&#xD;
The Supreme Court of Michigan eventually remanded the&#xD;
case to the Court of Appeals for reconsideration in light of&#xD;
our 2006 decision in Davis. &lt;/pre&gt;&lt;span class="citation no-link"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;477&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;Mich.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;902&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;pre class="inline"&gt;, 722 N. W. 2d&#xD;
797 (2006). On remand, the Court of Appeals again af&#xD;
firmed, holding that Covington’s statements were properly&#xD;
admitted because they were not testimonial. No. 247039,&#xD;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;span class="citation no-link"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;2007&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;WL&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;675471&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;pre class="inline"&gt; (Mar. 6, 2007) (per curiam). Bryant&#xD;
again appealed to the Supreme Court of Michigan, which&#xD;
reversed his conviction. &lt;/pre&gt;&lt;span class="citation"&gt;&lt;a href="/mich/5hKN/people-v-bryant/"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;483&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;Mich.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;132&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;pre class="inline"&gt;, 768 N. W. 2d 65.&#xD;
   Before the Supreme Court of Michigan, Bryant argued&#xD;
that Covington’s statements to the police were testimonial&#xD;
under Crawford and Davis and were therefore inadmissi&#xD;
ble. The State, on the other hand, argued that the state&#xD;
ments were admissible as “excited utterances” under the&#xD;
Michigan Rules of Evidence. 483 Mich., at 142, and n. 6,&#xD;
768 N. W. 2d, at 70, and n. 6. There was no dispute that&#xD;
Covington was unavailable at trial and Bryant had no&#xD;
prior opportunity to cross-examine him. The court there&#xD;
fore assessed whether Covington’s statements to the police&#xD;
identifying and describing the shooter and the time and&#xD;
location of the shooting were testimonial hearsay for&#xD;
purposes of the Confrontation Clause. The court con&#xD;
cluded that the circumstances “clearly indicate that the&#xD;
‘primary purpose’ of the questioning was to establish the&#xD;
facts of an event that had already occurred; the ‘primary&#xD;
purpose’ was not to enable police assistance to meet an&#xD;
ongoing emergency.” Id., at 143, 768 N. W. 2d, at 71. The&#xD;
4                      MICHIGAN v. BRYANT&#xD;
&#xD;
                         Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
court explained that, in its view, Covington was describing&#xD;
past events and as such, his “primary purpose in making&#xD;
these statements to the police . . . was . . . to tell the police&#xD;
who had committed the crime against him, where the&#xD;
crime had been committed, and where the police could find&#xD;
the criminal.” Id., at 144, 768 N. W. 2d, at 71. Noting&#xD;
that the officers’ actions did not suggest that they per&#xD;
ceived an ongoing emergency at the gas station, the court&#xD;
held that there was in fact no ongoing emergency. Id., at&#xD;
145–147, 768 N. W. 2d, at 71–73. The court distinguished&#xD;
the facts of this case from those in Davis, where we held a&#xD;
declarant’s statements in a 911 call to be nontestimonial.&#xD;
It instead analogized this case to Hammon v. Indiana,&#xD;
which we decided jointly with Davis and in which we&#xD;
found testimonial a declarant’s statements to police just&#xD;
after an assault. See 547 U. S., at 829–832. Based on this&#xD;
analysis, the Supreme Court of Michigan held that the&#xD;
admission of Covington’s statements constituted prejudi&#xD;
cial plain error warranting reversal and ordered a new&#xD;
trial. 483 Mich., at 151–153, 768 N. W. 2d, at 75–76. The&#xD;
court did not address whether, absent a Confrontation&#xD;
Clause bar, the statements’ admission would have been&#xD;
otherwise consistent with Michigan’s hearsay rules or due&#xD;
process.1&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  1 The Supreme Court of Michigan held that the question whether the&#xD;
&#xD;
victim’s statements would have been admissible as “dying declarations”&#xD;
was not properly before it because at the preliminary examination, the&#xD;
prosecution, after first invoking both the dying declaration and excited&#xD;
utterance hearsay exceptions, established the factual foundation only&#xD;
for admission of the statements as excited utterances. The trial court&#xD;
ruled that the statements were admissible as excited utterances and&#xD;
did not address their admissibility as dying declarations. 483 Mich., at&#xD;
153–154, 768 N. W. 2d, at 76–77. This occurred prior to our 2004&#xD;
decision in Crawford v. Washington, 541 U. S. 36, where we first&#xD;
suggested that dying declarations, even if testimonial, might be admis&#xD;
sible as a historical exception to the Confrontation Clause. Id., at 56,&#xD;
n. 6; see also Giles v. California, 554 U. S. 353, 358–359 (2008). We&#xD;
                     Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)                   5&#xD;
&#xD;
                         Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
  The majority’s opinion provoked two dissents, both of&#xD;
which would have held Covington’s statements admissible&#xD;
because they were made in circumstances indicating that&#xD;
their “primary purpose” was to assist police in addressing&#xD;
an ongoing emergency. Id., at 157, 768 N. W. 2d, at 79&#xD;
(opinion of Weaver, J.); id., at 157–158, 768 N. W. 2d, at&#xD;
79 (opinion of Corrigan, J.). Justice Corrigan’s dissent&#xD;
explained that the time and space between “the onset of&#xD;
an emergency and statements about that emergency&#xD;
clearly must be considered in context.” Id., at 161, 768&#xD;
N. W. 2d, at 80. Justice Corrigan concluded that the&#xD;
objective circumstances of Covington’s interaction with&#xD;
police rendered this case more similar to the nontestimo&#xD;
nial statements in Davis than to the testimonial state&#xD;
ments in Crawford. 483 Mich., at 164, 768 N. W. 2d,&#xD;
at 82.&#xD;
  We granted certiorari to determine whether the Con&#xD;
frontation Clause barred admission of Covington’s state&#xD;
ments. 559 U. S. ___ (2010).&#xD;
                             II&#xD;
  The Confrontation Clause of the Sixth Amendment&#xD;
states: “In all criminal prosecutions, the accused shall&#xD;
enjoy the right . . . to be confronted with the witnesses&#xD;
against him.” The Fourteenth Amendment renders the&#xD;
Clause binding on the States. Pointer v. Texas, 380 U. S.&#xD;
400, 403 (1965). In Ohio v. Roberts, 448 U. S. 56, 66&#xD;
(1980), we explained that the confrontation right does not&#xD;
bar admission of statements of an unavailable witness if&#xD;
the statements “bea[r] adequate ‘indicia of reliability.’ ”&#xD;
&#xD;
——————&#xD;
noted in Crawford that we “need not decide in this case whether the&#xD;
Sixth Amendment incorporates an exception for testimonial dying&#xD;
declarations.” 541 U. S., at 56, n. 6. Because of the State’s failure to&#xD;
preserve its argument with regard to dying declarations, we similarly&#xD;
need not decide that question here. See also post, p. __ (GINSBURG, J.,&#xD;
dissenting).&#xD;
6                   MICHIGAN v. BRYANT&#xD;
&#xD;
                      Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
We held that reliability can be established if “the evidence&#xD;
falls within a firmly rooted hearsay exception,” or if it does&#xD;
not fall within such an exception, then if it bears “particu&#xD;
larized guarantees of trustworthiness.” Ibid.&#xD;
   Nearly a quarter century later, we decided Crawford v.&#xD;
Washington, 541 U. S. 36. Petitioner Michael Crawford&#xD;
was prosecuted for stabbing a man who had allegedly&#xD;
attempted to rape his wife, Sylvia. Sylvia witnessed the&#xD;
stabbing, and later that night, after she and her husband&#xD;
were both arrested, police interrogated her about the&#xD;
incident. At trial, Sylvia Crawford claimed spousal privi&#xD;
lege and did not testify, but the State introduced a tape&#xD;
recording of Sylvia’s statement to the police in an effort to&#xD;
prove that the stabbing was not in self-defense, as Michael&#xD;
Crawford claimed. The Washington Supreme Court af&#xD;
firmed Crawford’s conviction because it found Sylvia’s&#xD;
statement to be reliable, as required under Ohio v. Rob&#xD;
erts. We reversed, overruling Ohio v. Roberts. 541 U. S.,&#xD;
at 60–68; see also Davis, 547 U. S., at 825, n. 4.&#xD;
   Crawford examined the common-law history of the&#xD;
confrontation right and explained that “the principal evil&#xD;
at which the Confrontation Clause was directed was the&#xD;
civil-law mode of criminal procedure, and particularly its&#xD;
use of ex parte examinations as evidence against the ac&#xD;
cused.” 541 U. S., at 50. We noted that in England, pre&#xD;
trial examinations of suspects and witnesses by govern&#xD;
ment officials “were sometimes read in court in lieu of live&#xD;
testimony.” Id., at 43. In light of this history, we empha&#xD;
sized the word “witnesses” in the Sixth Amendment, defin&#xD;
ing it as “those who ‘bear testimony.’ ” Id., at 51 (quoting&#xD;
2 N. Webster, An American Dictionary of the English&#xD;
Language (1828)). We defined “testimony” as “ ‘ [a] solemn&#xD;
declaration or affirmation made for the purpose of estab&#xD;
lishing or proving some fact.’ ” 541 U. S., at 51 (quoting&#xD;
Webster). We noted that “[a]n accuser who makes a for&#xD;
mal statement to government officers bears testimony in a&#xD;
                 Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)           7&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
sense that a person who makes a casual remark to an&#xD;
acquaintance does not.” Ibid. We therefore limited the&#xD;
Confrontation Clause’s reach to testimonial statements&#xD;
and held that in order for testimonial evidence to be ad&#xD;
missible, the Sixth Amendment “demands what the com&#xD;
mon law required: unavailability and a prior opportunity&#xD;
for cross-examination.” Id., at 68. Although “leav[ing] for&#xD;
another day any effort to spell out a comprehensive defini&#xD;
tion of ‘testimonial,’ ” Crawford noted that “at a minimum”&#xD;
it includes “prior testimony at a preliminary hearing,&#xD;
before a grand jury, or at a former trial; and . . . police&#xD;
interrogations.” Ibid. Under this reasoning, we held that&#xD;
Sylvia Crawford’s statements in the course of police ques&#xD;
tioning were testimonial and that their admission when&#xD;
Michael Crawford “had no opportunity to cross-examine&#xD;
her” due to spousal privilege was “sufficient to make out a&#xD;
violation of the Sixth Amendment.” Ibid.&#xD;
   In 2006, the Court in Davis v. Washington and Hammon&#xD;
v. Indiana, 547 U. S. 813, took a further step to “deter&#xD;
mine more precisely which police interrogations produce&#xD;
testimony” and therefore implicate a Confrontation Clause&#xD;
bar. Id., at 822. We explained that when Crawford said&#xD;
that&#xD;
    “ ‘interrogations by law enforcement officers fall&#xD;
    squarely within [the] class’ of testimonial hearsay, we&#xD;
    had immediately in mind (for that was the case before&#xD;
    us) interrogations solely directed at establishing the&#xD;
    facts of a past crime, in order to identify (or provide&#xD;
    evidence to convict) the perpetrator. The product of&#xD;
    such interrogation, whether reduced to a writing&#xD;
    signed by the declarant or embedded in the memory&#xD;
    (and perhaps notes) of the interrogating officer, is tes&#xD;
    timonial.” Davis, 547 U. S., at 826.&#xD;
We thus made clear in Davis that not all those questioned&#xD;
by the police are witnesses and not all “interrogations by&#xD;
8                       MICHIGAN v. BRYANT&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
law enforcement officers,” Crawford, 541 U. S., at 53, are&#xD;
subject to the Confrontation Clause.2&#xD;
  Davis and Hammon were both domestic violence cases.&#xD;
In Davis, Michelle McCottry made the statements at issue&#xD;
to a 911 operator during a domestic disturbance with&#xD;
Adrian Davis, her former boyfriend. McCottry told the&#xD;
operator, “ ‘He’s here jumpin’ on me again,’ ” and, “ ‘He’s&#xD;
usin’ his fists.’ ” 547 U. S., at 817. The operator then&#xD;
asked McCottry for Davis’ first and last names and middle&#xD;
initial, and at that point in the conversation McCottry&#xD;
reported that Davis had fled in a car. Id., at 818.&#xD;
McCottry did not appear at Davis’ trial, and the State&#xD;
introduced the recording of her conversation with the 911&#xD;
operator. Id., at 819.&#xD;
  In Hammon, decided along with Davis, police responded&#xD;
to a domestic disturbance call at the home of Amy and&#xD;
Hershel Hammon, where they found Amy alone on the&#xD;
front porch. Ibid. She appeared “ ‘somewhat frightened,’ ”&#xD;
but told them “ ‘nothing was the matter.’ ” Ibid. (quoting&#xD;
Hammon v. State, 829 N. E. 2d 444, 446–447 (Ind. 2005)).&#xD;
She gave the police permission to enter the house, where&#xD;
they saw a gas heating unit with the glass front shattered&#xD;
on the floor. One officer remained in the kitchen with&#xD;
Hershel, while another officer talked to Amy in the living&#xD;
room about what had happened. Hershel tried several&#xD;
times to participate in Amy’s conversation with the police&#xD;
and became angry when the police required him to stay&#xD;
separated from Amy. 547 U. S., at 819–820. The police&#xD;
asked Amy to fill out and sign a battery affidavit. She&#xD;
wrote: “ ‘Broke our Furnace &amp; shoved me down on the floor&#xD;
——————&#xD;
   2 We noted in Crawford that “[w]e use the term ‘interrogation’ in its&#xD;
&#xD;
colloquial, rather than any technical legal, sense,” and that “[j]ust as&#xD;
various definitions of ‘testimonial’ exist, one can imagine various&#xD;
definitions of ‘interrogation,’ and we need not select among them in this&#xD;
case.” 541 U. S., at 53, n. 4. Davis did not abandon those qualifica&#xD;
tions; nor do we do so here.&#xD;
                 Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)           9&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
into the broken glass. Hit me in the chest and threw me&#xD;
down. Broke our lamps &amp; phone. Tore up my van where I&#xD;
couldn’t leave the house. Attacked my daughter.’ ” Id., at&#xD;
820. Amy did not appear at Hershel’s trial, so the police&#xD;
officers who spoke with her testified as to her statements&#xD;
and authenticated the affidavit. Ibid. The trial court&#xD;
admitted the affidavit as a present sense impression and&#xD;
admitted the oral statements as excited utterances under&#xD;
state hearsay rules. Ibid. The Indiana Supreme Court&#xD;
affirmed Hammon’s conviction, holding that Amy’s oral&#xD;
statements were not testimonial and that the admission of&#xD;
the affidavit, although erroneous because the affidavit was&#xD;
testimonial, was harmless. Hammon v. State, 829 N. E.&#xD;
2d, at 458–459.&#xD;
  To address the facts of both cases, we expanded upon&#xD;
the meaning of “testimonial” that we first employed in&#xD;
Crawford and discussed the concept of an ongoing emer&#xD;
gency. We explained:&#xD;
    “Statements are nontestimonial when made in the&#xD;
    course of police interrogation under circumstances ob&#xD;
    jectively indicating that the primary purpose of the&#xD;
    interrogation is to enable police assistance to meet an&#xD;
    ongoing emergency. They are testimonial when the&#xD;
    circumstances objectively indicate that there is no&#xD;
    such ongoing emergency, and that the primary pur&#xD;
    pose of the interrogation is to establish or prove past&#xD;
    events potentially relevant to later criminal prosecu&#xD;
    tion.” Davis, 547 U. S., at 822.&#xD;
Examining the Davis and Hammon statements in light of&#xD;
those definitions, we held that the statements at issue&#xD;
in Davis were nontestimonial and the statements in&#xD;
Hammon were testimonial. We distinguished the state&#xD;
ments in Davis from the testimonial statements in Craw&#xD;
ford on several grounds, including that the victim in Davis&#xD;
was “speaking about events as they were actually happen&#xD;
10                       MICHIGAN v. BRYANT&#xD;
&#xD;
                           Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
ing, rather than ‘describ[ing] past events,’ ” that there was&#xD;
an ongoing emergency, that the “elicited statements were&#xD;
necessary to be able to resolve the present emergency,”&#xD;
and that the statements were not formal. 547 U. S., at&#xD;
827. In Hammon, on the other hand, we held that, “[i]t is&#xD;
entirely clear from the circumstances that the interroga&#xD;
tion was part of an investigation into possibly criminal&#xD;
past conduct.” Id., at 829. There was “no emergency in&#xD;
progress.” Ibid. The officer questioning Amy “was not&#xD;
seeking to determine . . . ‘what is happening,’ but rather&#xD;
‘what happened.’ ” Id., at 830. It was “formal enough”&#xD;
that the police interrogated Amy in a room separate from&#xD;
her husband where, “some time after the events described&#xD;
were over,” she “deliberately recounted, in response to&#xD;
police questioning, how potentially criminal past events&#xD;
began and progressed.” Ibid. Because her statements&#xD;
“were neither a cry for help nor the provision of informa&#xD;
tion enabling officers immediately to end a threatening&#xD;
situation,” id., at 832, we held that they were testimonial.&#xD;
   Davis did not “attemp[t] to produce an exhaustive classi&#xD;
fication of all conceivable statements—or even all conceiv&#xD;
able statements in response to police interrogation—as&#xD;
either testimonial or nontestimonial.” Id., at 822.3 The&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  3 Davis  explained that 911 operators “may at least be agents of&#xD;
law enforcement when they conduct interrogations of 911 callers,” and&#xD;
therefore “consider[ed] their acts to be acts of the police” for purposes of&#xD;
the opinion. 547 U. S., at 823, n. 2. Davis explicitly reserved the&#xD;
question of “whether and when statements made to someone other than&#xD;
law enforcement personnel are ‘testimonial.’ ” Ibid. We have no need to&#xD;
decide that question in this case either because Covington’s statements&#xD;
were made to police officers. The dissent also claims to reserve this&#xD;
question, see post, at 3, n. 1 (opinion of SCALIA, J.), but supports one of&#xD;
its arguments by relying on King v. Brasier, 1 Leach 199, 200, 168 Eng.&#xD;
Rep. 202, 202–203 (K. B. 1779), which involved statements made by a&#xD;
child to her mother—a private citizen—just after the child had been&#xD;
sexually assaulted. See also Crawford v. Washington, 541 U. S. 36, 69–&#xD;
70 (2004) (Rehnquist, C. J., concurring in judgment) (citing King v.&#xD;
                      Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)                     11&#xD;
&#xD;
                           Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
basic purpose of the Confrontation Clause was to “targe[t]”&#xD;
the sort of “abuses” exemplified at the notorious treason&#xD;
trial of Sir Walter Raleigh. Crawford, 541 U. S., at 51.&#xD;
Thus, the most important instances in which the Clause&#xD;
restricts the introduction of out-of-court statements are&#xD;
those in which state actors are involved in a formal, out-of&#xD;
court interrogation of a witness to obtain evidence for&#xD;
trial.4 See id., at 43–44. Even where such an interroga&#xD;
tion is conducted with all good faith, introduction of the&#xD;
resulting statements at trial can be unfair to the accused&#xD;
if they are untested by cross-examination. Whether for&#xD;
mal or informal, out-of-court statements can evade the&#xD;
basic objective of the Confrontation Clause, which is to&#xD;
prevent the accused from being deprived of the opportu&#xD;
nity to cross-examine the declarant about statements&#xD;
taken for use at trial. When, as in Davis, the primary&#xD;
purpose of an interrogation is to respond to an “ongoing&#xD;
emergency,” its purpose is not to create a record for trial&#xD;
and thus is not within the scope of the Clause. But there&#xD;
may be other circumstances, aside from ongoing emergen&#xD;
cies, when a statement is not procured with a primary&#xD;
purpose of creating an out-of-court substitute for trial&#xD;
testimony. In making the primary purpose determination,&#xD;
standard rules of hearsay, designed to identify some state&#xD;
——————&#xD;
Brasier for the different proposition that “out-of-court statements made&#xD;
by someone other than the accused and not taken under oath, unlike ex&#xD;
parte depositions or affidavits, were generally not considered substan&#xD;
tive evidence upon which a conviction could be based”).&#xD;
   4 Contrary to the dissent’s excited suggestion, nothing in this opinion&#xD;
&#xD;
casts “favorable light,” post, at 11 (opinion of SCALIA, J.), on the conduct&#xD;
of Sir Walter Raleigh’s trial or other 16th- and 17th-century English&#xD;
treason trials. The dissent is correct that such trials are “unquestiona&#xD;
bly infamous,” ibid., and our decision here confirms, rather than un&#xD;
dermines, that assessment. See also n. 17, infra. For all of the&#xD;
reasons discussed in JUSTICE THOMAS’ opinion concurring in the judg&#xD;
ment, the situation presented in this case is nothing like the circum&#xD;
stances presented by Sir Walter Raleigh’s trial. See post, p. __.&#xD;
12                      MICHIGAN v. BRYANT&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
ments as reliable, will be relevant. Where no such pri&#xD;
mary purpose exists, the admissibility of a statement is&#xD;
the concern of state and federal rules of evidence, not the&#xD;
Confrontation Clause.5&#xD;
  Deciding this case also requires further explanation of&#xD;
the “ongoing emergency” circumstance addressed in Davis.&#xD;
Because Davis and Hammon arose in the domestic vio&#xD;
lence context, that was the situation “we had immediately&#xD;
in mind (for that was the case before us).” 547 U. S., at&#xD;
826. We now face a new context: a nondomestic dispute,&#xD;
involving a victim found in a public location, suffering&#xD;
from a fatal gunshot wound, and a perpetrator whose&#xD;
location was unknown at the time the police located the&#xD;
victim. Thus, we confront for the first time circumstances&#xD;
in which the “ongoing emergency” discussed in Davis&#xD;
extends beyond an initial victim to a potential threat to&#xD;
the responding police and the public at large. This new&#xD;
context requires us to provide additional clarification with&#xD;
regard to what Davis meant by “the primary purpose of&#xD;
the interrogation is to enable police assistance to meet an&#xD;
ongoing emergency.” Id., at 822.&#xD;
                           III&#xD;
   To determine whether the “primary purpose” of an&#xD;
interrogation is “to enable police assistance to meet an&#xD;
ongoing emergency,” Davis, 547 U. S., at 822, which would&#xD;
render the resulting statements nontestimonial, we objec&#xD;
tively evaluate the circumstances in which the encounter&#xD;
occurs and the statements and actions of the parties.&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
——————&#xD;
   5 See Davis v. Washington, 547 U. S. 813, 823–824 (2006) (explaining&#xD;
&#xD;
the question before the Court as “whether the Confrontation Clause&#xD;
applies only to testimonial hearsay” and answering in the affirmative&#xD;
because “[a] limitation so clearly reflected in the text of the constitu&#xD;
tional provision must fairly be said to mark out not merely its ‘core,’ but&#xD;
its perimeter”). See also post, at 2 (SCALIA, J., dissenting).&#xD;
                     Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011) &#xD;
                  13&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court &#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
                              A&#xD;
&#xD;
   The Michigan Supreme Court correctly understood that&#xD;
this inquiry is objective.6 483 Mich., at 142, 768 N. W. 2d,&#xD;
at 70. Davis uses the word “objective” or “objectively” no&#xD;
fewer than eight times in describing the relevant inquiry.&#xD;
See 547 U. S., at 822, 826–828, 830–831, and n. 5; see, e.g.,&#xD;
id., at 826 (“The question before us in Davis, then, is&#xD;
whether, objectively considered, the interrogation that&#xD;
took place in the course of the 911 call produced testimo&#xD;
nial statements”). “Objectively” also appears in the defini&#xD;
tions of both testimonial and nontestimonial statements&#xD;
that Davis established. Id., at 822.&#xD;
   An objective analysis of the circumstances of an encoun&#xD;
ter and the statements and actions of the parties to it&#xD;
provides the most accurate assessment of the “primary&#xD;
purpose of the interrogation.” The circumstances in which&#xD;
an encounter occurs—e.g., at or near the scene of the crime&#xD;
versus at a police station, during an ongoing emergency&#xD;
or afterwards—are clearly matters of objective fact. The&#xD;
statements and actions of the parties must also be objec&#xD;
tively evaluated. That is, the relevant inquiry is not the&#xD;
subjective or actual purpose of the individuals involved in&#xD;
a particular encounter, but rather the purpose that rea&#xD;
sonable participants would have had, as ascertained from&#xD;
the individuals’ statements and actions and the circum&#xD;
stances in which the encounter occurred.7&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  6 Bryant suggests that Michigan is arguing for “a subjective analysis&#xD;
of the intent of the interrogator’s questioning.” Brief for Respondent&#xD;
12. We do not read Michigan’s brief to be arguing for a subjective&#xD;
inquiry, and any such argument would be in error. We do not under&#xD;
stand the dissent to disagree that the inquiry is objective.&#xD;
  7 This approach is consistent with our rejection of subjective inquiries&#xD;
&#xD;
in other areas of criminal law. See, e.g., Whren v. United States, 517&#xD;
U. S. 806, 813 (1996) (refusing to evaluate Fourth Amendment reason&#xD;
ableness subjectively in light of the officers’ actual motivations); New&#xD;
York v. Quarles, 467 U. S. 649, 655–656, and n. 6 (1984) (holding that&#xD;
an officer’s subjective motivation is irrelevant to determining the&#xD;
14                      MICHIGAN v. BRYANT&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
                              B&#xD;
   As our recent Confrontation Clause cases have ex&#xD;
plained, the existence of an “ongoing emergency” at the&#xD;
time of an encounter between an individual and the police&#xD;
is among the most important circumstances informing the&#xD;
“primary purpose” of an interrogation. See Davis, 547&#xD;
U. S., at 828–830; Crawford, 541 U. S., at 65. The exis&#xD;
tence of an ongoing emergency is relevant to determining&#xD;
the primary purpose of the interrogation because an&#xD;
emergency focuses the participants on something other&#xD;
than “prov[ing] past events potentially relevant to later&#xD;
criminal prosecution.”8 Davis, 547 U. S., at 822. Rather,&#xD;
it focuses them on “end[ing] a threatening situation.” Id.,&#xD;
at 832. Implicit in Davis is the idea that because the&#xD;
prospect of fabrication in statements given for the primary&#xD;
purpose of resolving that emergency is presumably signifi&#xD;
cantly diminished, the Confrontation Clause does not&#xD;
require such statements to be subject to the crucible of&#xD;
cross-examination.&#xD;
   This logic is not unlike that justifying the excited utter&#xD;
ance exception in hearsay law. Statements “relating to a&#xD;
startling event or condition made while the declarant was&#xD;
under the stress of excitement caused by the event or&#xD;
—————— &#xD;
&#xD;
applicability of the public safety exception to Miranda v. Arizona, 384&#xD;
&#xD;
U. S. 436 (1966)); Rhode Island v. Innis, 446 U. S. 291, 301–302 (1980)&#xD;
(holding that a police officer’s subjective intent to obtain incriminatory&#xD;
statements is not relevant to determining whether an interrogation has&#xD;
occurred).&#xD;
  8 The existence of an ongoing emergency must be objectively assessed&#xD;
&#xD;
from the perspective of the parties to the interrogation at the time, not&#xD;
with the benefit of hindsight. If the information the parties knew at&#xD;
the time of the encounter would lead a reasonable person to believe&#xD;
that there was an emergency, even if that belief was later proved&#xD;
incorrect, that is sufficient for purposes of the Confrontation Clause.&#xD;
The emergency is relevant to the “primary purpose of the interrogation”&#xD;
because of the effect it has on the parties’ purpose, not because of its&#xD;
actual existence.&#xD;
                     Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)                   15&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
condition,” Fed. Rule Evid. 803(2); see also Mich. Rule&#xD;
Evid. 803(2) (2010), are considered reliable because the&#xD;
declarant, in the excitement, presumably cannot form a&#xD;
falsehood. See Idaho v. Wright, 497 U. S. 805, 820 (1990)&#xD;
(“The basis for the ‘excited utterance’ exception . . . is that&#xD;
such statements are given under circumstances that&#xD;
eliminate the possibility of fabrication, coaching, or con&#xD;
fabulation . . . ”); 5 J. Weinstein &amp; M. Berger, Weinstein’s&#xD;
Federal Evidence §803.04[1] (J. McLaughlin ed., 2d ed.&#xD;
2010) (same); Advisory Committee’s Notes on Fed. Rule&#xD;
Evid. 803(2), 28 U. S. C. App., p. 371 (same). An ongoing&#xD;
emergency has a similar effect of focusing an individual’s&#xD;
attention on responding to the emergency.9&#xD;
   Following our precedents, the court below correctly&#xD;
began its analysis with the circumstances in which Cov&#xD;
ington interacted with the police. 483 Mich., at 143, 768&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  9 Many other exceptions to the hearsay rules similarly rest on the&#xD;
&#xD;
belief that certain statements are, by their nature, made for a purpose&#xD;
other than use in a prosecution and therefore should not be barred by&#xD;
hearsay prohibitions. See, e.g., Fed. Rule Evid. 801(d)(2)(E) (statement&#xD;
by a co-conspirator during and in furtherance of the conspiracy); 803(4)&#xD;
(Statements for Purposes of Medical Diagnosis or Treatment); 803(6)&#xD;
(Records of Regularly Conducted Activity); 803(8) (Public Records and&#xD;
Reports); 803(9) (Records of Vital Statistics); 803(11) (Records of Reli&#xD;
gious Organizations); 803(12) (Marriage, Baptismal, and Similar&#xD;
Certificates); 803(13) (Family Records); 804(b)(3) (Statement Against&#xD;
Interest); see also Melendez-Diaz v. Massachusetts, 557 U. S. __, __&#xD;
(2009) (slip op., at 18) (“Business and public records are generally&#xD;
admissible absent confrontation not because they qualify under an&#xD;
exception to the hearsay rules, but because—having been created for&#xD;
the administration of an entity’s affairs and not for the purpose of&#xD;
establishing or proving some fact at trial—they are not testimonial”);&#xD;
Giles v. California, 554 U. S., at 376 (noting in the context of domestic&#xD;
violence that “[s]tatements to friends and neighbors about abuse and&#xD;
intimidation and statements to physicians in the course of receiving&#xD;
treatment would be excluded, if at all, only by hearsay rules”); Craw&#xD;
ford, 541 U. S., at 56 (“Most of the hearsay exceptions covered state&#xD;
ments that by their nature were not testimonial—for example, business&#xD;
records or statements in furtherance of a conspiracy”).&#xD;
16                 MICHIGAN v. BRYANT&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
N. W. 2d, at 71. But in doing so, the court construed Davis&#xD;
to have decided more than it did and thus employed an&#xD;
unduly narrow understanding of “ongoing emergency” that&#xD;
Davis does not require.&#xD;
  First, the Michigan Supreme Court repeatedly and&#xD;
incorrectly asserted that Davis “defined” “ ‘ongoing emer&#xD;
gency.’ ” 483 Mich., at 147, 768 N. W. 2d, at 73; see also&#xD;
id., at 144, 768 N. W. 2d, at 71–72. In fact, Davis did not&#xD;
even define the extent of the emergency in that case. The&#xD;
Michigan Supreme Court erroneously read Davis as decid&#xD;
ing that “the statements made after the defendant stopped&#xD;
assaulting the victim and left the premises did not occur&#xD;
during an ‘ongoing emergency.’ ” 483 Mich., at 150, n. 15,&#xD;
768 N. W. 2d, at 75, n. 15. We explicitly explained in&#xD;
Davis, however, that we were asked to review only the&#xD;
testimonial nature of Michelle McCottry’s initial state&#xD;
ments during the 911 call; we therefore merely assumed&#xD;
the correctness of the Washington Supreme Court’s hold&#xD;
ing that admission of her other statements was harmless,&#xD;
without deciding whether those subsequent statements&#xD;
were also made for the primary purpose of resolving an&#xD;
ongoing emergency. 547 U. S., at 829.&#xD;
  Second, by assuming that Davis defined the outer&#xD;
bounds of “ongoing emergency,” the Michigan Supreme&#xD;
Court failed to appreciate that whether an emergency&#xD;
exists and is ongoing is a highly context-dependent in&#xD;
quiry. See Brief for United States as Amicus Curiae 20.&#xD;
Davis and Hammon involved domestic violence, a known&#xD;
and identified perpetrator, and, in Hammon, a neutralized&#xD;
threat. Because Davis and Hammon were domestic vio&#xD;
lence cases, we focused only on the threat to the victims&#xD;
and assessed the ongoing emergency from the perspective&#xD;
of whether there was a continuing threat to them. 547&#xD;
U. S., at 827, 829–830.&#xD;
  Domestic violence cases like Davis and Hammon often&#xD;
have a narrower zone of potential victims than cases&#xD;
                 Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)          17&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
involving threats to public safety. An assessment of&#xD;
whether an emergency that threatens the police and pub&#xD;
lic is ongoing cannot narrowly focus on whether the threat&#xD;
solely to the first victim has been neutralized because the&#xD;
threat to the first responders and public may continue.&#xD;
See 483 Mich., at 164, 768 N. W. 2d, at 82 (Corrigan, J.,&#xD;
dissenting) (examining the threat to the victim, police, and&#xD;
the public); Brief for United States as Amicus Curiae 19–&#xD;
20 (“An emergency posed by an unknown shooter who&#xD;
remains at large does not automatically abate just because&#xD;
the police can provide security to his first victim”).&#xD;
   The Michigan Supreme Court also did not appreciate&#xD;
that the duration and scope of an emergency may depend&#xD;
in part on the type of weapon employed. The court relied&#xD;
on Davis and Hammon, in which the assailants used their&#xD;
fists, as controlling the scope of the emergency here, which&#xD;
involved the use of a gun. The problem with that reason&#xD;
ing is clear when considered in light of the assault on Amy&#xD;
Hammon. Hershel Hammon was armed only with his fists&#xD;
when he attacked his wife, so removing Amy to a separate&#xD;
room was sufficient to end the emergency. 547 U. S., at&#xD;
830–832. If Hershel had been reported to be armed with a&#xD;
gun, however, separation by a single household wall might&#xD;
not have been sufficient to end the emergency. Id., at 819.&#xD;
   The Michigan Supreme Court’s failure to focus on the&#xD;
context-dependent nature of our Davis decision also led it&#xD;
to conclude that the medical condition of a declarant is&#xD;
irrelevant. 483 Mich., at 149, 768 N. W. 2d, at 74 (“The&#xD;
Court said nothing at all that would remotely suggest that&#xD;
whether the victim was in need of medical attention was&#xD;
in any way relevant to whether there was an ‘ongoing&#xD;
emergency’ ”). But Davis and Hammon did not present&#xD;
medical emergencies, despite some injuries to the victims.&#xD;
547 U. S., at 818, 820. Thus, we have not previously&#xD;
considered, much less ruled out, the relevance of a victim’s&#xD;
severe injuries to the primary purpose inquiry.&#xD;
18                     MICHIGAN v. BRYANT&#xD;
&#xD;
                        Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
   Taking into account the victim’s medical state does not,&#xD;
as the Michigan Supreme Court below thought, “rende[r]&#xD;
non-testimonial” “all statements made while the police are&#xD;
questioning a seriously injured complainant.” 483 Mich.,&#xD;
at 149, 768 N. W. 2d, at 74. The medical condition of the&#xD;
victim is important to the primary purpose inquiry to the&#xD;
extent that it sheds light on the ability of the victim to&#xD;
have any purpose at all in responding to police questions&#xD;
and on the likelihood that any purpose formed would&#xD;
necessarily be a testimonial one. The victim’s medical&#xD;
state also provides important context for first responders&#xD;
to judge the existence and magnitude of a continuing&#xD;
threat to the victim, themselves, and the public.&#xD;
   As the Solicitor General’s brief observes, Brief for&#xD;
United States as Amicus Curiae 20, and contrary to the&#xD;
Michigan Supreme Court’s claims, 483 Mich., at 147, 768&#xD;
N. W. 2d, at 73, none of this suggests that an emergency is&#xD;
ongoing in every place or even just surrounding the victim&#xD;
for the entire time that the perpetrator of a violent crime&#xD;
is on the loose. As we recognized in Davis, “a conversation&#xD;
which begins as an interrogation to determine the need for&#xD;
emergency assistance” can “evolve into testimonial state&#xD;
ments.” 547 U. S., at 828 (internal quotation marks omit&#xD;
ted). This evolution may occur if, for example, a declarant&#xD;
provides police with information that makes clear that&#xD;
what appeared to be an emergency is not or is no longer an&#xD;
emergency or that what appeared to be a public threat is&#xD;
actually a private dispute. It could also occur if a perpe&#xD;
trator is disarmed, surrenders, is apprehended, or, as in&#xD;
Davis, flees with little prospect of posing a threat to the&#xD;
public. Trial courts can determine in the first instance&#xD;
when any transition from nontestimonial to testimonial&#xD;
occurs,10 and exclude “the portions of any statement that&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  10 Recognizing the evolutionary potential of a situation in criminal&#xD;
&#xD;
law is not unique to the Confrontation Clause context. We noted in&#xD;
                     Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)                    19&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
have become testimonial, as they do, for example, with&#xD;
unduly prejudicial portions of otherwise admissible evi&#xD;
dence.” Id., at 829.&#xD;
   Finally, our discussion of the Michigan Supreme Court’s&#xD;
misunderstanding of what Davis meant by “ongoing emer&#xD;
gency” should not be taken to imply that the existence vel&#xD;
non of an ongoing emergency is dispositive of the testimo&#xD;
nial inquiry. As Davis made clear, whether an ongoing&#xD;
emergency exists is simply one factor—albeit an important&#xD;
factor—that informs the ultimate inquiry regarding the&#xD;
“primary purpose” of an interrogation. Another factor the&#xD;
Michigan Supreme Court did not sufficiently account for is&#xD;
the importance of informality in an encounter between a&#xD;
victim and police. Formality is not the sole touchstone of&#xD;
our primary purpose inquiry because, although formality&#xD;
suggests the absence of an emergency and therefore an&#xD;
increased likelihood that the purpose of the interrogation&#xD;
is to “establish or prove past events potentially relevant to&#xD;
later criminal prosecution,” id., at 822, informality does&#xD;
not necessarily indicate the presence of an emergency or&#xD;
the lack of testimonial intent. Cf. id., at 826 (explaining&#xD;
that Confrontation Clause requirements cannot “readily&#xD;
be evaded” by the parties deliberately keeping the written&#xD;
product of an interrogation informal “instead of having the&#xD;
declarant sign a deposition”). The court below, however,&#xD;
too readily dismissed the informality of the circumstances&#xD;
in this case in a single brief footnote and in fact seems to&#xD;
have suggested that the encounter in this case was formal.&#xD;
483 Mich., at 150, n. 16, 768 N. W. 2d, at 75, n. 16. As we&#xD;
——————&#xD;
Davis that “[j]ust as, for Fifth Amendment purposes, ‘police officers can&#xD;
and will distinguish almost instinctively between questions necessary&#xD;
to secure their own safety or the safety of the public and questions&#xD;
designed solely to elicit testimonial evidence from a suspect, . . . trial&#xD;
courts will recognize the point at which, for Sixth Amendment pur&#xD;
poses, statements in response to interrogations become testimonial.”&#xD;
547 U. S., at 829 (quoting New York v. Quarles, 467 U. S., at 658–659).&#xD;
20                      MICHIGAN v. BRYANT&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
explain further below, the questioning in this case oc&#xD;
curred in an exposed, public area, prior to the arrival of&#xD;
emergency medical services, and in a disorganized fashion.&#xD;
All of those facts make this case distinguishable from&#xD;
the formal station-house interrogation in Crawford. See&#xD;
Davis, 547 U. S., at 827.&#xD;
                              C&#xD;
  In addition to the circumstances in which an encounter&#xD;
occurs, the statements and actions of both the declarant&#xD;
and interrogators provide objective evidence of the pri&#xD;
mary purpose of the interrogation. See, e.g., Davis, 547&#xD;
U. S., at 827 (“[T]he nature of what was asked and an&#xD;
swered in Davis, again viewed objectively, was such that&#xD;
the elicited statements were necessary to be able to resolve&#xD;
the present emergency, rather than simply to learn (as in&#xD;
Crawford) what had happened in the past” (first emphasis&#xD;
added)). The Michigan Supreme Court did, at least&#xD;
briefly, conduct this inquiry. 483 Mich., at 144–147, 768&#xD;
N. W. 2d, at 71–73.&#xD;
  As the Michigan Supreme Court correctly recognized,&#xD;
id., at 140, n. 5, 768 N. W. 2d, at 69, n. 5, Davis requires a&#xD;
combined inquiry that accounts for both the declarant and&#xD;
the interrogator.11 In many instances, the primary pur&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  11 Some  portions of Davis, however, have caused confusion about&#xD;
whether the inquiry prescribes examination of one participant to the&#xD;
exclusion of the other. Davis’ language indicating that a statement’s&#xD;
testimonial or nontestimonial nature derives from “the primary pur&#xD;
pose of the interrogation,” 547 U. S., at 822 (emphasis added), could be&#xD;
read to suggest that the relevant purpose is that of the interrogator. In&#xD;
contrast, footnote 1 in Davis explains, “it is in the final analysis the&#xD;
declarant’s statements, not the interrogator’s questions, that the&#xD;
Confrontation Clause requires us to evaluate.” Id., at 822–823, n. 1.&#xD;
Bryant draws on the footnote to argue that the primary purpose inquiry&#xD;
must be conducted solely from the perspective of the declarant, and&#xD;
argues against adoption of a purpose-of-the-interrogator perspective.&#xD;
Brief for Respondent 10–13; see also Brief for Richard D. Friedman as&#xD;
Amicus Curiae 5–15. But this statement in footnote 1 of Davis merely&#xD;
                     Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)                   21&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
pose of the interrogation will be most accurately ascer&#xD;
tained by looking to the contents of both the questions and&#xD;
the answers. To give an extreme example, if the police say&#xD;
to a victim, “Tell us who did this to you so that we can&#xD;
arrest and prosecute them,” the victim’s response that&#xD;
“Rick did it,” appears purely accusatory because by virtue&#xD;
of the phrasing of the question, the victim necessarily has&#xD;
prosecution in mind when she answers.&#xD;
  The combined approach also ameliorates problems that&#xD;
could arise from looking solely to one participant. Pre&#xD;
dominant among these is the problem of mixed motives&#xD;
on the part of both interrogators and declarants. Police&#xD;
officers in our society function as both first responders and&#xD;
criminal investigators. Their dual responsibilities may&#xD;
mean that they act with different motives simultaneously&#xD;
or in quick succession. See New York v. Quarles, 467 U. S.&#xD;
649, 656 (1984) (“Undoubtedly most police officers [decid&#xD;
ing whether to give Miranda warnings in a possible emer&#xD;
gency situation] would act out of a host of different, in&#xD;
stinctive, and largely unverifiable motives—their own&#xD;
safety, the safety of others, and perhaps as well the desire&#xD;
to obtain incriminating evidence from the suspect”); see&#xD;
also Davis, 547 U. S., at 839 (THOMAS, J., concurring in&#xD;
judgment in part and dissenting in part) (“In many, if not&#xD;
most, cases where police respond to a report of a crime,&#xD;
whether pursuant to a 911 call from the victim or other&#xD;
wise, the purposes of an interrogation, viewed from the&#xD;
perspective of the police, are both to respond to the emer&#xD;
——————&#xD;
acknowledges that the Confrontation Clause is not implicated when&#xD;
statements are offered “for purposes other than establishing the truth&#xD;
of the matter asserted.” Crawford, 541 U. S., at 60, n. 9. An interroga&#xD;
tor’s questions, unlike a declarant’s answers, do not assert the truth of&#xD;
any matter. The language in the footnote was not meant to determine&#xD;
how the courts are to assess the nature of the declarant’s purpose, but&#xD;
merely to remind readers that it is the statements, and not the ques&#xD;
tions, that must be evaluated under the Sixth Amendment.&#xD;
22                      MICHIGAN v. BRYANT&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
gency situation and to gather evidence”).&#xD;
   Victims are also likely to have mixed motives when they&#xD;
make statements to the police. During an ongoing emer&#xD;
gency, a victim is most likely to want the threat to her and&#xD;
to other potential victims to end, but that does not neces&#xD;
sarily mean that the victim wants or envisions prosecution&#xD;
of the assailant. A victim may want the attacker to be&#xD;
incapacitated temporarily or rehabilitated. Alternatively,&#xD;
a severely injured victim may have no purpose at all in&#xD;
answering questions posed; the answers may be simply&#xD;
reflexive. The victim’s injuries could be so debilitating&#xD;
as to prevent her from thinking sufficiently clearly to un&#xD;
derstand whether her statements are for the purpose of&#xD;
addressing an ongoing emergency or for the purpose of fu&#xD;
ture prosecution.12 Taking into account a victim’s injuries&#xD;
does not transform this objective inquiry into a subjective&#xD;
one. The inquiry is still objective because it focuses on the&#xD;
understanding and purpose of a reasonable victim in the&#xD;
circumstances of the actual victim—circumstances that&#xD;
prominently include the victim’s physical state.&#xD;
   The dissent suggests, post, at 3–4 (opinion of SCALIA, J.),&#xD;
that we intend to give controlling weight to the “intentions&#xD;
of the police,” post, at 4. That is a misreading of our opin&#xD;
ion. At trial, the declarant’s statements, not the interro&#xD;
gator’s questions, will be introduced to “establis[h] the&#xD;
truth of the matter asserted,” Crawford, 541 U. S., at 60,&#xD;
n. 9, and must therefore pass the Sixth Amendment test.&#xD;
&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  12 In such a situation, the severe injuries of the victim would un&#xD;
&#xD;
doubtedly also weigh on the credibility and reliability that the trier of&#xD;
fact would afford to the statements. Cf. Advisory Committee’s Notes on&#xD;
Fed. Rule Evid. 803(2), 28 U. S. C. App., p. 371 (noting that although&#xD;
the “theory” of the excited utterance exception “has been criticized on&#xD;
the ground that excitement impairs [the] accuracy of observation as&#xD;
well as eliminating conscious fabrication,” it “finds support in cases&#xD;
without number” (citing 6 J. Wigmore, Evidence §1750 (J. Chadbourn&#xD;
rev. 1976))).&#xD;
                 Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)           23&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
See n. 11, supra. In determining whether a declarant’s&#xD;
statements are testimonial, courts should look to all of the&#xD;
relevant circumstances. Even JUSTICE SCALIA concedes&#xD;
that the interrogator is relevant to this evaluation, post,&#xD;
at 3, and we agree that “[t]he identity of an interrogator,&#xD;
and the content and tenor of his questions,” ibid., can illu&#xD;
minate the “primary purpose of the interrogation.” The&#xD;
dissent, see post, at 3–5 (opinion of SCALIA, J.), criticizes&#xD;
the complexity of our approach, but we, at least, are un&#xD;
willing to sacrifice accuracy for simplicity. Simpler is not&#xD;
always better, and courts making a “primary purpose”&#xD;
assessment should not be unjustifiably restrained from&#xD;
consulting all relevant information, including the state&#xD;
ments and actions of interrogators.&#xD;
  Objectively ascertaining the primary purpose of the&#xD;
interrogation by examining the statements and actions of&#xD;
all participants is also the approach most consistent with&#xD;
our past holdings. E.g., Davis, 547 U. S., at 822–823, n. 1&#xD;
(noting that “volunteered testimony” is still testimony and&#xD;
remains subject to the requirements of the Confrontation&#xD;
Clause).&#xD;
                             IV&#xD;
   As we suggested in Davis, when a court must determine&#xD;
whether the Confrontation Clause bars the admission of a&#xD;
statement at trial, it should determine the “primary pur&#xD;
pose of the interrogation” by objectively evaluating the&#xD;
statements and actions of the parties to the encounter, in&#xD;
light of the circumstances in which the interrogation&#xD;
occurs. The existence of an emergency or the parties’&#xD;
perception that an emergency is ongoing is among the&#xD;
most important circumstances that courts must take into&#xD;
account in determining whether an interrogation is tes&#xD;
timonial because statements made to assist police in&#xD;
addressing an ongoing emergency presumably lack the&#xD;
testimonial purpose that would subject them to the&#xD;
24                      MICHIGAN v. BRYANT&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
requirement of confrontation.13 As the context of this case&#xD;
brings into sharp relief, the existence and duration of an&#xD;
emergency depend on the type and scope of danger posed&#xD;
to the victim, the police, and the public.&#xD;
  Applying this analysis to the facts of this case is more&#xD;
difficult than in Davis because we do not have the luxury&#xD;
of reviewing a transcript of the conversation between the&#xD;
victim and the police officers. Further complicating our&#xD;
task is the fact that the trial in this case occurred before&#xD;
our decisions in Crawford and Davis. We therefore review&#xD;
a record that was not developed to ascertain the “primary&#xD;
purpose of the interrogation.”&#xD;
  We first examine the circumstances in which the inter&#xD;
rogation occurred. The parties disagree over whether&#xD;
there was an emergency when the police arrived at the gas&#xD;
station. Bryant argues, and the Michigan Supreme Court&#xD;
accepted, 483 Mich., at 147, 768 N. W. 2d, at 73, that there&#xD;
was no ongoing emergency because “there . . . was no&#xD;
criminal conduct occurring. No shots were being fired, no&#xD;
one was seen in possession of a firearm, nor were any&#xD;
witnesses seen cowering in fear or running from the&#xD;
scene.” Brief for Respondent 27. Bryant, while conceding&#xD;
that “a serious or life-threatening injury creates a medical&#xD;
emergency for a victim,” id., at 30, further argues that a&#xD;
declarant’s medical emergency is not relevant to the ongo&#xD;
——————&#xD;
   13 Of course the Confrontation Clause is not the only bar to admissi&#xD;
&#xD;
bility of hearsay statements at trial. State and federal rules of evidence&#xD;
prohibit the introduction of hearsay, subject to exceptions. Consistent&#xD;
with those rules, the Due Process Clauses of the Fifth and Fourteenth&#xD;
Amendments may constitute a further bar to admission of, for example,&#xD;
unreliable evidence. See Montana v. Egelhoff, 518 U. S. 37, 53 (1996)&#xD;
(plurality opinion) (“[E]rroneous evidentiary rulings can, in combina&#xD;
tion, rise to the level of a due process violation”); Dutton v. Evans, 400&#xD;
U. S. 74, 96–97 (1970) (Harlan, J., concurring in result) (“[T]he Fifth&#xD;
and Fourteenth Amendments’ commands that federal and state trials,&#xD;
respectively, must be conducted in accordance with due process of law”&#xD;
is the “standard” by which to “test federal and state rules of evidence”).&#xD;
                     Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)                    25&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
ing emergency determination.&#xD;
   In contrast, Michigan and the Solicitor General explain&#xD;
that when the police responded to the call that a man had&#xD;
been shot and found Covington bleeding on the gas station&#xD;
parking lot, “they did not know who Covington was,&#xD;
whether the shooting had occurred at the gas station or at&#xD;
a different location, who the assailant was, or whether the&#xD;
assailant posed a continuing threat to Covington or oth&#xD;
ers.” Brief for United States as Amicus Curiae 15; Brief&#xD;
for Petitioner 16; see also id., at 15 (“[W]hen an officer&#xD;
arrives on the scene and does not know where the perpe&#xD;
trator is, whether he is armed, whether he might have&#xD;
other targets, and whether the violence might continue&#xD;
at the scene or elsewhere, interrogation that has the pri&#xD;
mary purpose of establishing those facts to assess the situ&#xD;
ation is designed to meet the ongoing emergency and is&#xD;
nontestimonial”).&#xD;
   The Michigan Supreme Court stated that the police&#xD;
asked Covington, “what had happened, who had shot him,&#xD;
and where the shooting had occurred.” 483 Mich., at 143,&#xD;
768 N. W. 2d, at 71. The joint appendix contains the&#xD;
transcripts of the preliminary examination, suppression&#xD;
hearing, and trial testimony of five officers who responded&#xD;
to the scene and found Covington. The officers’ testimony&#xD;
is essentially consistent but, at the same time, not specific.&#xD;
The officers basically agree on what information they&#xD;
learned from Covington, but not on the order in which&#xD;
they learned it or on whether Covington’s statements were&#xD;
in response to general or detailed questions. They all&#xD;
agree that the first question was “what happened?” The&#xD;
answer was either “I was shot” or “Rick shot me.”14&#xD;
——————&#xD;
   14 See App. 76 (testimony of Officer McCallister); id., at 101, 113–114&#xD;
&#xD;
(testimony of Sgt. Wenturine); id., at 127, 131–133 (testimony of Officer&#xD;
Stuglin). Covington told them that Rick had shot him through the back&#xD;
door of Rick’s house, id., at 127–128 (testimony of Officer Stuglin),&#xD;
located at the corner of Pennsylvania and Laura, id., at 102 (testimony&#xD;
26                       MICHIGAN v. BRYANT&#xD;
&#xD;
                           Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
   As explained above, the scope of an emergency in terms&#xD;
of its threat to individuals other than the initial assailant&#xD;
and victim will often depend on the type of dispute in&#xD;
volved. Nothing Covington said to the police indicated&#xD;
that the cause of the shooting was a purely private dispute&#xD;
or that the threat from the shooter had ended. The record&#xD;
reveals little about the motive for the shooting. The police&#xD;
officers who spoke with Covington at the gas station testi&#xD;
fied that Covington did not tell them what words Coving&#xD;
ton and Rick had exchanged prior to the shooting.15 What&#xD;
Covington did tell the officers was that he fled Bryant’s&#xD;
back porch, indicating that he perceived an ongoing&#xD;
threat.16 The police did not know, and Covington did not&#xD;
tell them, whether the threat was limited to him. The&#xD;
——————&#xD;
of Sgt. Wenturine), and that Covington recognized Rick by his voice, id.,&#xD;
at 128 (testimony of Officer Stuglin). Covington also gave them a&#xD;
physical description of Rick. Id., at 84–85, 93–94 (testimony of Officer&#xD;
McAllister); id., at 103, 115 (testimony of Sgt. Wenturine); id., at 134&#xD;
(testimony of Officer Stuglin).&#xD;
   15 See id., at 114 (“Q Did he tell you what Rick said? A He said they&#xD;
&#xD;
were having a conversation. Q Did he tell you what Rick said? A He&#xD;
did not” (testimony of Sgt. Wenturine) (paragraph breaks omitted)); see&#xD;
also id., at 79 (testimony of Officer McAllister); id., at 128 (testimony of&#xD;
Officer Stuglin).&#xD;
   16 See id., at 127–128 (“A He said he’d went up, he went up to the&#xD;
&#xD;
back door of a house; that a person he said he knew, and he was knock&#xD;
ing and he was knocking on the door he said he’d talked to somebody&#xD;
through the door. He said he recognized the voice. Q Did he say who it&#xD;
was that he recognized the voice of? A That’s when he told me it was,&#xD;
he said it was Rick a/k/a Buster. Q And did he say what the conversa&#xD;
tion was about at the door? A I don’t, I don’t believe so. Q All right.&#xD;
And did he say what happened there, whether or not they had a con&#xD;
versation or not, did he say what ended up happening? A He said what&#xD;
happened was that he heard a shot and then he started to turn to get&#xD;
off the porch and then another one and then that’s when he was hit by&#xD;
a gunshot” (testimony of Officer Stuglin) (paragraph breaks omitted)).&#xD;
Unlike the dissent’s apparent ability to read Covington’s mind, post, at&#xD;
6 (opinion of SCALIA, J.), we rely on the available evidence, which&#xD;
suggests that Covington perceived an ongoing threat.&#xD;
                     Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)                   27&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
potential scope of the dispute and therefore the emergency&#xD;
in this case thus stretches more broadly than those at&#xD;
issue in Davis and Hammon and encompasses a threat&#xD;
potentially to the police and the public.&#xD;
  This is also the first of our post-Crawford Confrontation&#xD;
Clause cases to involve a gun. The physical separation&#xD;
that was sufficient to end the emergency in Hammon was&#xD;
not necessarily sufficient to end the threat in this case;&#xD;
Covington was shot through the back door of Bryant’s&#xD;
house. Bryant’s argument that there was no ongoing&#xD;
emergency because “[n]o shots were being fired,” Brief for&#xD;
Respondent 27, surely construes ongoing emergency too&#xD;
narrowly. An emergency does not last only for the time&#xD;
between when the assailant pulls the trigger and the&#xD;
bullet hits the victim. If an out-of-sight sniper pauses&#xD;
between shots, no one would say that the emergency&#xD;
ceases during the pause. That is an extreme example and&#xD;
not the situation here, but it serves to highlight the im&#xD;
plausibility, at least as to certain weapons, of construing&#xD;
the emergency to last only precisely as long as the violent&#xD;
act itself, as some have construed our opinion in Davis.&#xD;
See Brief for Respondent 23–25.&#xD;
  At no point during the questioning did either Covington&#xD;
or the police know the location of the shooter. In fact,&#xD;
Bryant was not at home by the time the police searched&#xD;
his house at approximately 5:30 a.m. 483 Mich., at 136,&#xD;
768 N. W. 2d, at 67. At some point between 3 a.m. and&#xD;
5:30 a.m., Bryant left his house. At bottom, there was an&#xD;
ongoing emergency here where an armed shooter, whose&#xD;
motive for and location after the shooting were unknown,&#xD;
had mortally wounded Covington within a few blocks&#xD;
and a few minutes of the location where the police found&#xD;
Covington.17&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  17 It hardly bears mention that the emergency situation in this case is&#xD;
&#xD;
readily distinguishable from the “treasonous conspiracies of unknown&#xD;
28                       MICHIGAN v. BRYANT&#xD;
&#xD;
                           Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
  This is not to suggest that the emergency continued&#xD;
until Bryant was arrested in California a year after the&#xD;
shooting. Id., at 137, 768 N. W. 2d, at 67. We need not&#xD;
decide precisely when the emergency ended because Cov&#xD;
ington’s encounter with the police and all of the state&#xD;
ments he made during that interaction occurred within&#xD;
the first few minutes of the police officers’ arrival and&#xD;
well before they secured the scene of the shooting—the&#xD;
shooter’s last known location.&#xD;
  We reiterate, moreover, that the existence vel non of an&#xD;
ongoing emergency is not the touchstone of the testimonial&#xD;
inquiry; rather, the ultimate inquiry is whether the “pri&#xD;
mary purpose of the interrogation [was] to enable police&#xD;
assistance to meet [the] ongoing emergency.” Davis, 547&#xD;
U. S., at 822. We turn now to that inquiry, as informed by&#xD;
the circumstances of the ongoing emergency just de&#xD;
scribed. The circumstances of the encounter provide im&#xD;
portant context for understanding Covington’s statements&#xD;
to the police. When the police arrived at Covington’s side,&#xD;
their first question to him was “What happened?”18 Cov&#xD;
ington’s response was either “Rick shot me” or “I was&#xD;
shot,” followed very quickly by an identification of “Rick”&#xD;
——————&#xD;
scope, aimed at killing or overthrowing the king,” post, at 11, about&#xD;
which JUSTICE SCALIA’s dissent is quite concerned.&#xD;
   18 Although the dissent claims otherwise, post, at 7 (opinion of&#xD;
&#xD;
SCALIA, J.), at least one officer asked Covington something akin to “how&#xD;
was he doing.” App. 131 (testimony of Officer Stuglin) (“A I approached&#xD;
the subject, the victim, Mr. Covington, on the ground and had asked&#xD;
something like what happened or are you okay, something to that&#xD;
line. . . . Q So you asked this man how are you, how are you doing? A&#xD;
Well, basically it’s, you know, what’s wrong, you know” (paragraph&#xD;
breaks omitted)). The officers also testified about their assessment of&#xD;
Covington’s wounds. See id., at 35 (suppression hearing testimony of&#xD;
Officer Brown) (“[H]e had blood . . . on the front of his body”); id., at 75&#xD;
(testimony of Officer McCallister) (“It appeared he had a stomach&#xD;
wound of a gunshot”); id., at 132 (testimony of Officer Stuglin) (“Q Did&#xD;
you see the wound? A Yes, I did. Q You had to move some clothing to&#xD;
do that? A Yes” (paragraph breaks omitted)).&#xD;
                     Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)                    29&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
as the shooter. App. 76. In response to further questions,&#xD;
Covington explained that the shooting occurred through&#xD;
the back door of Bryant’s house and provided a physical&#xD;
description of the shooter. When he made the statements,&#xD;
Covington was lying in a gas station parking lot bleeding&#xD;
from a mortal gunshot wound to his abdomen. His an&#xD;
swers to the police officers’ questions were punctuated&#xD;
with questions about when emergency medical services&#xD;
would arrive. Id., at 56–57 (suppression hearing testi&#xD;
mony of Officer Brown). He was obviously in considerable&#xD;
pain and had difficulty breathing and talking. Id., at 75,&#xD;
83–84 (testimony of Officer McCallister); id., at 101, 110–&#xD;
111 (testimony of Sgt. Wenturine); id., at 126, 137 (testi&#xD;
mony of Officer Stuglin). From this description of his&#xD;
condition and report of his statements, we cannot say that&#xD;
a person in Covington’s situation would have had a “pri&#xD;
mary purpose” “to establish or prove past events poten&#xD;
tially relevant to later criminal prosecution.” Davis, 547&#xD;
U. S., at 822.&#xD;
   For their part, the police responded to a call that a man&#xD;
had been shot. As discussed above, they did not know&#xD;
why, where, or when the shooting had occurred. Nor did&#xD;
they know the location of the shooter or anything else&#xD;
about the circumstances in which the crime occurred.19&#xD;
——————&#xD;
   19 Contrary to the dissent’s suggestion, post, at 8 (opinion of SCALIA,&#xD;
&#xD;
J.), and despite the fact that the record was developed prior to Davis’&#xD;
focus on the existence of an “ongoing emergency,” the record contains&#xD;
some testimony to support the idea that the police officers were con&#xD;
cerned about the location of the shooter when they arrived on the scene&#xD;
and thus to suggest that the purpose of the questioning of Covington&#xD;
was to determine the shooter’s location. See App. 136 (testimony of&#xD;
Officer Stuglin) (stating that upon arrival officers questioned the gas&#xD;
station clerk about whether the shooting occurred in the gas station&#xD;
parking lot and about concern for safety); see also ibid. (testimony of&#xD;
Officer Stuglin) (“Q . . . So you have some concern, there may be a&#xD;
person with a gun or somebody, a shooter right there in the immediate&#xD;
area? A Sure, yes. Q And you want to see that that area gets secured?&#xD;
30                      MICHIGAN v. BRYANT&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
The questions they asked—“what had happened, who had&#xD;
shot him, and where the shooting occurred,” 483 Mich., at&#xD;
143, 768 N. W. 2d, at 71—were the exact type of questions&#xD;
necessary to allow the police to “ ‘assess the situation, the&#xD;
threat to their own safety, and possible danger to the&#xD;
potential victim’ ” and to the public, Davis, 547 U. S., at&#xD;
832 (quoting Hiibel v. Sixth Judicial Dist. Court of Nev.,&#xD;
Humboldt Cty., 542 U. S. 177, 186 (2004)), including to&#xD;
allow them to ascertain “whether they would be encoun&#xD;
tering a violent felon,”20 Davis, 547 U. S., at 827. In other&#xD;
words, they solicited the information necessary to enable&#xD;
them “to meet an ongoing emergency.” Id., at 822.&#xD;
  Nothing in Covington’s responses indicated to the police&#xD;
that, contrary to their expectation upon responding to a&#xD;
call reporting a shooting, there was no emergency or that&#xD;
a prior emergency had ended. Covington did indicate that&#xD;
he had been shot at another location about 25 minutes&#xD;
earlier, but he did not know the location of the shooter at&#xD;
the time the police arrived and, as far as we can tell from&#xD;
the record, he gave no indication that the shooter, having&#xD;
shot at him twice, would be satisfied that Covington was&#xD;
only wounded. In fact, Covington did not indicate any&#xD;
possible motive for the shooting, and thereby gave no&#xD;
reason to think that the shooter would not shoot again if&#xD;
he arrived on the scene. As we noted in Davis, “initial&#xD;
inquiries” may “often . . . produce nontestimonial state&#xD;
——————&#xD;
A Correct. Q For your safety as well as everyone else? A Correct”&#xD;
(paragraph breaks omitted)); id., at 82 (testimony of Officer McCallis&#xD;
ter). But see id., at 83 (cross-examination of Officer McAllister) (“Q You&#xD;
didn’t, you didn’t look around and say, gee, there might be a shooter&#xD;
around here, I better keep an eye open? A I did not, no. That could&#xD;
have been my partner I don’t know” (paragraph breaks omitted)).&#xD;
  20 Hiibel, like our post-Crawford Confrontation Clause cases, involved&#xD;
&#xD;
domestic violence, which explains the Court’s focus on the security of&#xD;
the victim and the police: they were the only parties potentially threat&#xD;
ened by the assailant. 542 U. S., at 186 (noting that the case involved a&#xD;
“domestic assault”).&#xD;
                  Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)           31&#xD;
&#xD;
                      Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
ments.” Id., at 832. The initial inquiries in this case&#xD;
resulted in the type of nontestimonial statements we&#xD;
contemplated in Davis.&#xD;
   Finally, we consider the informality of the situation and&#xD;
the interrogation. This situation is more similar, though&#xD;
not identical, to the informal, harried 911 call in Davis&#xD;
than to the structured, station-house interview in Craw&#xD;
ford. As the officers’ trial testimony reflects, the situation&#xD;
was fluid and somewhat confused: the officers arrived at&#xD;
different times; apparently each, upon arrival, asked&#xD;
Covington “what happened?”; and, contrary to the dis&#xD;
sent’s portrayal, post, at 7–9 (opinion of SCALIA, J.), they&#xD;
did not conduct a structured interrogation. App. 84 (tes&#xD;
timony of Officer McCallister) (explaining duplicate ques&#xD;
tioning, especially as to “what happened?”); id., at 101–102&#xD;
(testimony of Sgt. Wenturine) (same); id., at 126–127&#xD;
(testimony of Officer Stuglin) (same). The informality&#xD;
suggests that the interrogators’ primary purpose was&#xD;
simply to address what they perceived to be an ongoing&#xD;
emergency, and the circumstances lacked any formality&#xD;
that would have alerted Covington to or focused him on&#xD;
the possible future prosecutorial use of his statements.&#xD;
   Because the circumstances of the encounter as well as&#xD;
the statements and actions of Covington and the police&#xD;
objectively indicate that the “primary purpose of the inter&#xD;
rogation” was “to enable police assistance to meet an&#xD;
ongoing emergency,” Davis, 547 U. S., at 822, Covington’s&#xD;
identification and description of the shooter and the lo&#xD;
cation of the shooting were not testimonial hearsay.&#xD;
The Confrontation Clause did not bar their admission at&#xD;
Bryant’s trial.&#xD;
&#xD;
                         *      *     *&#xD;
&#xD;
  For the foregoing reasons, we hold that Covington’s&#xD;
statements were not testimonial and that their admission&#xD;
32                 MICHIGAN v. BRYANT&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
at Bryant’s trial did not violate the Confrontation Clause.&#xD;
We leave for the Michigan courts to decide on remand&#xD;
whether the statements’ admission was otherwise permit&#xD;
ted by state hearsay rules. The judgment of the Supreme&#xD;
Court of Michigan is vacated, and the case is remanded for&#xD;
further proceedings not inconsistent with this opinion.&#xD;
&#xD;
                                            It is so ordered.&#xD;
&#xD;
  JUSTICE KAGAN took no part in the consideration or&#xD;
decision of this case.&#xD;
                 Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)           1&#xD;
&#xD;
               THOMAS, J., concurring in judgment&#xD;
&#xD;
SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES&#xD;
                          _________________&#xD;
&#xD;
                          No. 09–150&#xD;
                          _________________&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
    MICHIGAN, PETITIONER v. RICHARD PERRY &#xD;
&#xD;
                   BRYANT &#xD;
&#xD;
     ON WRIT OF CERTIORARI TO THE SUPREME COURT&#xD;
&#xD;
                     OF MICHIGAN&#xD;
&#xD;
                      [February 28, 2011] &#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
  JUSTICE THOMAS, concurring in the judgment.&#xD;
  I agree with the Court that the admission of Covington’s&#xD;
out-of-court statements did not violate the Confrontation&#xD;
Clause, but I reach this conclusion because Covington’s&#xD;
questioning by police lacked sufficient formality and so&#xD;
lemnity for his statements to be considered “testimonial.”&#xD;
See Crawford v. Washington, 541 U. S. 36, 68 (2004).&#xD;
  In determining whether Covington’s statements to&#xD;
police implicate the Confrontation Clause, the Court&#xD;
evaluates the “ ‘primary purpose’ ” of the interrogation.&#xD;
Ante, at 12. The majority’s analysis⎯which relies on,&#xD;
inter alia, what the police knew when they arrived at the&#xD;
scene, the specific questions they asked, the particular&#xD;
information Covington conveyed, the weapon involved,&#xD;
and Covington’s medical condition⎯illustrates the uncer&#xD;
tainty that this test creates for law enforcement and the&#xD;
lower courts. Ante, at 25–31. I have criticized the&#xD;
primary-purpose test as “an exercise in fiction” that is&#xD;
“disconnected from history” and “yields no predictable&#xD;
results.” Davis v. Washington, 547 U. S. 813, 839, 838&#xD;
(2006) (opinion concurring in judgment in part and dis&#xD;
senting in part).&#xD;
  Rather than attempting to reconstruct the “primary&#xD;
purpose” of the participants, I would consider the extent to&#xD;
which the interrogation resembles those historical prac&#xD;
2                   MICHIGAN v. BRYANT&#xD;
&#xD;
               THOMAS, J., concurring in judgment&#xD;
&#xD;
tices that the Confrontation Clause addressed. See, e.g.,&#xD;
id., at 835–836 (describing “practices that occurred under&#xD;
the English bail and committal statutes passed during the&#xD;
reign of Queen Mary”). As the majority notes, Covington&#xD;
interacted with the police under highly informal circum&#xD;
stances, while he bled from a fatal gunshot wound. Ante,&#xD;
at 19–20, 31. The police questioning was not “a formalized&#xD;
dialogue,” did not result in “formalized testimonial ma&#xD;
terials” such as a deposition or affidavit, and bore no “in-&#xD;
dicia of solemnity.” Davis, supra, at 840, 837 (opinion of&#xD;
THOMAS, J.); see also Giles v. California, 554 U. S. 353,&#xD;
377–378 (2008) (THOMAS, J., concurring). Nor is there any&#xD;
indication that the statements were offered at trial “in&#xD;
order to evade confrontation.” Davis, supra, at 840. This&#xD;
interrogation bears little if any resemblance to the histori&#xD;
cal practices that the Confrontation Clause aimed to elimi&#xD;
nate. Covington thus did not “bea[r] testimony” against&#xD;
Bryant, Crawford, supra, at 51, and the introduction of his&#xD;
statements at trial did not implicate the Confrontation&#xD;
Clause. I concur in the judgment.&#xD;
                  Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)            1&#xD;
&#xD;
                      SCALIA, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES&#xD;
                          _________________&#xD;
&#xD;
                           No. 09–150&#xD;
                          _________________&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
     MICHIGAN, PETITIONER v. RICHARD PERRY &#xD;
&#xD;
                    BRYANT &#xD;
&#xD;
     ON WRIT OF CERTIORARI TO THE SUPREME COURT&#xD;
&#xD;
                     OF MICHIGAN&#xD;
&#xD;
                      [February 28, 2011] &#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
   JUSTICE SCALIA, dissenting.&#xD;
   Today’s tale—a story of five officers conducting suc&#xD;
cessive examinations of a dying man with the primary&#xD;
purpose, not of obtaining and preserving his testimony&#xD;
regarding his killer, but of protecting him, them, and&#xD;
others from a murderer somewhere on the loose—is so&#xD;
transparently false that professing to believe it demeans&#xD;
this institution. But reaching a patently incorrect conclu&#xD;
sion on the facts is a relatively benign judicial mischief; it&#xD;
affects, after all, only the case at hand. In its vain attempt&#xD;
to make the incredible plausible, however—or perhaps as&#xD;
an intended second goal—today’s opinion distorts our&#xD;
Confrontation Clause jurisprudence and leaves it in a&#xD;
shambles. Instead of clarifying the law, the Court makes&#xD;
itself the obfuscator of last resort. Because I continue to&#xD;
adhere to the Confrontation Clause that the People&#xD;
adopted, as described in Crawford v. Washington, 541&#xD;
U. S. 36 (2004), I dissent.&#xD;
                              I&#xD;
&#xD;
                              A&#xD;
&#xD;
  The Confrontation Clause of the Sixth Amendment,&#xD;
made binding on the States by the Fourteenth Amend&#xD;
ment, Pointer v. Texas, 380 U. S. 400, 403 (1965), provides&#xD;
that “[i]n all criminal prosecutions, the accused shall enjoy&#xD;
2                   MICHIGAN v. BRYANT&#xD;
&#xD;
                     SCALIA, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
the right . . . to be confronted with the witnesses against&#xD;
him.” In Crawford, we held that this provision guarantees&#xD;
a defendant his common-law right to confront those “who&#xD;
‘bear testimony’ ” against him. 541 U. S., at 51. A witness&#xD;
must deliver his testimony against the defendant in per&#xD;
son, or the prosecution must prove that the witness is&#xD;
unavailable to appear at trial and that the defendant&#xD;
has had a prior opportunity for cross-examination. Id., at&#xD;
53–54.&#xD;
    Not all hearsay falls within the Confrontation Clause’s&#xD;
grasp. At trial a witness “bears testimony” by providing&#xD;
“ ‘[a] solemn declaration or affirmation . . . for the purpose&#xD;
of establishing or proving some fact.’ ” Id., at 51 (quoting 2&#xD;
N. Webster, An American Dictionary of the English Lan&#xD;
guage (1828)). The Confrontation Clause protects defen&#xD;
dants only from hearsay statements that do the same.&#xD;
Davis v. Washington, 547 U. S. 813, 823–824 (2006). In&#xD;
Davis, we explained how to identify testimonial hearsay&#xD;
prompted by police questioning in the field. A statement&#xD;
is testimonial “when the circumstances objectively indi&#xD;
cate . . . that the primary purpose of the interrogation is to&#xD;
establish or prove past events potentially relevant to later&#xD;
criminal prosecution.” Id., at 822. When, however, the&#xD;
circumstances objectively indicate that the declarant’s&#xD;
statements were “a cry for help [o]r the provision of infor&#xD;
mation enabling officers immediately to end a threatening&#xD;
situation,” id., at 832, they bear little resemblance to in&#xD;
court testimony. “No ‘witness’ goes into court to proclaim&#xD;
an emergency and seek help.” Id., at 828.&#xD;
    Crawford and Davis did not address whose perspective&#xD;
matters—the declarant’s, the interrogator’s, or both—&#xD;
when assessing “the primary purpose of [an] interroga&#xD;
tion.” In those cases the statements were testimonial from&#xD;
any perspective. I think the same is true here, but be&#xD;
cause the Court picks a perspective so will I: The decla&#xD;
rant’s intent is what counts. In-court testimony is more&#xD;
                   Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)                 3&#xD;
&#xD;
                       SCALIA, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
than a narrative of past events; it is a solemn declaration&#xD;
made in the course of a criminal trial. For an out-of-court&#xD;
statement to qualify as testimonial, the declarant must&#xD;
intend the statement to be a solemn declaration rather&#xD;
than an unconsidered or offhand remark; and he must&#xD;
make the statement with the understanding that it may&#xD;
be used to invoke the coercive machinery of the State&#xD;
against the accused.1 See Friedman, Grappling with the&#xD;
Meaning of “Testimonial,” 71 Brooklyn L. Rev. 241, 259&#xD;
(2005). That is what distinguishes a narrative told to a&#xD;
friend over dinner from a statement to the police. See&#xD;
Crawford, supra, at 51. The hidden purpose of an interro&#xD;
gator cannot substitute for the declarant’s intentional&#xD;
solemnity or his understanding of how his words may be&#xD;
used.&#xD;
   A declarant-focused inquiry is also the only inquiry that&#xD;
would work in every fact pattern implicating the Confron&#xD;
tation Clause. The Clause applies to volunteered testi&#xD;
mony as well as statements solicited through police inter&#xD;
rogation. See Davis, supra, at 822–823, n. 1. An inquiry&#xD;
into an officer’s purposes would make no sense when a&#xD;
declarant blurts out “Rick shot me” as soon as the officer&#xD;
arrives on the scene. I see no reason to adopt a different&#xD;
test—one that accounts for an officer’s intent—when the&#xD;
officer asks “what happened” before the declarant makes&#xD;
his accusation. (This does not mean the interrogator is&#xD;
irrelevant. The identity of an interrogator, and the con&#xD;
tent and tenor of his questions, can bear upon whether a&#xD;
declarant intends to make a solemn statement, and envi&#xD;
sions its use at a criminal trial. But none of this means&#xD;
that the interrogator’s purpose matters.)&#xD;
   In an unsuccessful attempt to make its finding of emer&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  1 I remain agnostic about whether and when statements to nonstate&#xD;
&#xD;
actors are testimonial. See Davis v. Washington, 547 U. S. 813, 823,&#xD;
n. 2 (2006).&#xD;
4                  MICHIGAN v. BRYANT&#xD;
&#xD;
                     SCALIA, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
gency plausible, the Court instead adopts a test that looks&#xD;
to the purposes of both the police and the declarant. It&#xD;
claims that this is demanded by necessity, fretting that a&#xD;
domestic-violence victim may want her abuser briefly&#xD;
arrested—presumably to teach him a lesson—but not&#xD;
desire prosecution. See ante, at 22. I do not need to probe&#xD;
the purposes of the police to solve that problem. Even if a&#xD;
victim speaks to the police “to establish or prove past&#xD;
events” solely for the purpose of getting her abuser ar&#xD;
rested, she surely knows her account is “potentially rel&#xD;
evant to later criminal prosecution” should one ensue.&#xD;
Davis, supra, at 822.&#xD;
   The Court also wrings its hands over the possibility that&#xD;
“a severely injured victim” may lack the capacity to form a&#xD;
purpose, and instead answer questions “reflexive[ly].”&#xD;
Ante, at 22. How to assess whether a declarant with&#xD;
diminished capacity bore testimony is a difficult question,&#xD;
and one I do not need to answer today. But the Court’s&#xD;
proposed answer—to substitute the intentions of the police&#xD;
for the missing intentions of the declarant—cannot be the&#xD;
correct one. When the declarant has diminished capacity,&#xD;
focusing on the interrogators make less sense, not more.&#xD;
The inquiry under Crawford turns in part on the actions&#xD;
and statements of a declarant’s audience only because&#xD;
they shape the declarant’s perception of why his audience&#xD;
is listening and therefore influence his purpose in making&#xD;
the declaration. See 541 U. S., at 51. But a person who&#xD;
cannot perceive his own purposes certainly cannot per&#xD;
ceive why a listener might be interested in what he has to&#xD;
say. As far as I can tell, the Court’s substituted-intent&#xD;
theory “has nothing to be said for it except that it can&#xD;
sometimes make our job easier,” Jerman v. Carlisle,&#xD;
McNellie, Rini, Kramer &amp; Ulrich, L. P. A., 559 U. S. ___,&#xD;
___ (2010) (SCALIA, J., concurring in part and concurring&#xD;
in judgment) (slip op., at 2).&#xD;
   The Court claims one affirmative virtue for its focus on&#xD;
                 Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)            5&#xD;
&#xD;
                     SCALIA, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
the purposes of both the declarant and the police: It “ame&#xD;
liorates problems that . . . arise” when declarants have&#xD;
“mixed motives.” Ante, at 21. I am at a loss to know how.&#xD;
Sorting out the primary purpose of a declarant with mixed&#xD;
motives is sometimes difficult. But adding in the mixed&#xD;
motives of the police only compounds the problem. Now&#xD;
courts will have to sort through two sets of mixed motives&#xD;
to determine the primary purpose of an interrogation.&#xD;
And the Court’s solution creates a mixed-motive problem&#xD;
where (under the proper theory) it does not exist—viz.,&#xD;
where the police and the declarant each have one motive,&#xD;
but those motives conflict. The Court does not provide an&#xD;
answer to this glaringly obvious problem, probably be&#xD;
cause it does not have one.&#xD;
   The only virtue of the Court’s approach (if it can be&#xD;
misnamned a virtue) is that it leaves judges free to reach&#xD;
the “fairest” result under the totality of the circumstances.&#xD;
If the dastardly police trick a declarant into giving an&#xD;
incriminating statement against a sympathetic defendant,&#xD;
a court can focus on the police’s intent and declare the&#xD;
statement testimonial. If the defendant “deserves” to go to&#xD;
jail, then a court can focus on whatever perspective is&#xD;
necessary to declare damning hearsay nontestimonial.&#xD;
And when all else fails, a court can mix-and-match per&#xD;
spectives to reach its desired outcome. Unfortunately,&#xD;
under this malleable approach “the guarantee of confron&#xD;
tation is no guarantee at all.” Giles v. California, 554&#xD;
U. S. 353, 375 (2008) (plurality).&#xD;
                             B&#xD;
  Looking to the declarant’s purpose (as we should), this is&#xD;
an absurdly easy case. Roughly 25 minutes after Anthony&#xD;
Covington had been shot, Detroit police responded to a 911&#xD;
call reporting that a gunshot victim had appeared at a&#xD;
neighborhood gas station. They quickly arrived at the&#xD;
scene, and in less than 10 minutes five different Detroit&#xD;
6                   MICHIGAN v. BRYANT&#xD;
&#xD;
                     SCALIA, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
police officers questioned Covington about the shooting.&#xD;
Each asked him a similar battery of questions: “what&#xD;
happened” and when, App. 39, 126, “who shot” the victim,”&#xD;
id., at 22, and “where” did the shooting take place, id., at&#xD;
132. See also id., at 113. After Covington would answer,&#xD;
they would ask follow-up questions, such as “how tall is”&#xD;
the shooter, id., at 134, “[h]ow much does he weigh,” ibid.&#xD;
what is the exact address or physical description of the&#xD;
house where the shooting took place, and what chain&#xD;
of events led to the shooting. The battery relented when&#xD;
the paramedics arrived and began tending to Covington’s&#xD;
wounds.&#xD;
   From Covington’s perspective, his statements had little&#xD;
value except to ensure the arrest and eventual prosecution&#xD;
of Richard Bryant. He knew the “threatening situation,”&#xD;
Davis, 547 U. S., at 832, had ended six blocks away and 25&#xD;
minutes earlier when he fled from Bryant’s back porch.&#xD;
See &lt;/pre&gt;&lt;span class="citation"&gt;&lt;a href="/mich/5hKN/people-v-bryant/"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;483&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;Mich.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;132&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;pre class="inline"&gt;, 135–136, 768 N.W. 2d 65, 67 (2009);&#xD;
App. 105. Bryant had not confronted him face-to-face&#xD;
before he was mortally wounded, instead shooting him&#xD;
through a door. See 483 Mich., at 136–137, 768 N.W. 2d,&#xD;
at 67. Even if Bryant had pursued him (unlikely), and&#xD;
after seeing that Covington had ended up at the gas sta&#xD;
tion was unable to confront him there before the police&#xD;
arrived (doubly unlikely), it was entirely beyond imagina&#xD;
tion that Bryant would again open fire while Covington&#xD;
was surrounded by five armed police officers. And Coving&#xD;
ton knew the shooting was the work of a drug dealer, not a&#xD;
spree killer who might randomly threaten others. Id., at&#xD;
135, 137, 768 N.W. 2d, at 67.&#xD;
   Covington’s knowledge that he had nothing to fear&#xD;
differs significantly from Michelle McCottry’s state of&#xD;
mind during her “frantic” statements to a 911 operator at&#xD;
issue in Davis, 547 U. S., at 827. Her “call was plainly a&#xD;
call for help against a bona fide physical threat” describing&#xD;
“events as they were actually happening.” Ibid. She did&#xD;
                      Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)                     7&#xD;
&#xD;
                          SCALIA, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
not have the luxuries of police protection and of time and&#xD;
space separating her from immediate danger that Coving&#xD;
ton enjoyed when he made his statements. See id., at 831.&#xD;
   Covington’s pressing medical needs do not suggest that&#xD;
he was responding to an emergency, but to the contrary&#xD;
reinforce the testimonial character of his statements. He&#xD;
understood the police were focused on investigating a past&#xD;
crime, not his medical needs. None of the officers asked&#xD;
Covington how he was doing, attempted more than super&#xD;
ficially to assess the severity of his wounds, or attempted&#xD;
to administer first aid.2 They instead primarily asked&#xD;
questions with little, if any, relevance to Covington’s dire&#xD;
situation. Police, paramedics, and doctors do not need to&#xD;
know the address where a shooting took place, the name of&#xD;
the shooter, or the shooter’s height and weight to provide&#xD;
proper medical care. Underscoring that Covington under&#xD;
stood the officers’ investigative role, he interrupted their&#xD;
interrogation to ask “when is EMS coming?” App. 57.&#xD;
When, in other words, would the focus shift to his medical&#xD;
needs rather than Bryant’s crime?&#xD;
   Neither Covington’s statements nor the colloquy be&#xD;
tween him and the officers would have been out of place at&#xD;
a trial; it would have been a routine direct examination.&#xD;
See Davis, 547 U. S., at 830. Like a witness, Covington&#xD;
recounted in detail how a past criminal event began and&#xD;
progressed, and like a prosecutor, the police elicited that&#xD;
account through structured questioning. Preventing the&#xD;
&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  2 Officer Stuglin’s testimony does not undermine my assessment of&#xD;
&#xD;
the officers’ behavior, although the Court suggests otherwise. See ante,&#xD;
at 28, n. 18. Officer Stuglin first testified that he “asked something like&#xD;
what happened or are you okay, something to that line.” App., 131.&#xD;
When pressed on whether he asked “how are you doing?,” he responded,&#xD;
“Well, basically . . . what’s wrong.” Ibid. Other officers were not so&#xD;
equivocal: They admitted they had no need to “ask him how he was&#xD;
doing. . . . It was very obvious how he was doing.” Id., at 110; see also&#xD;
id., at 19.&#xD;
8                       MICHIGAN v. BRYANT&#xD;
&#xD;
                          SCALIA, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
admission of “weaker substitute[s] for live testimony at&#xD;
trial” such as this, id., at 828 (internal quotation marks&#xD;
omitted), is precisely what motivated the Framers to adopt&#xD;
the Confrontation Clause and what motivated our deci&#xD;
sions in Crawford and in Hammon v. Indiana, decided&#xD;
with Davis. Ex parte examinations raise the same consti&#xD;
tutional concerns whether they take place in a gas-station&#xD;
parking lot or in a police interrogation room.&#xD;
                               C&#xD;
  Worse still for the repute of today’s opinion, this is an&#xD;
absurdly easy case even if one (erroneously) takes the&#xD;
interrogating officers’ purpose into account. The five&#xD;
officers interrogated Covington primarily to investigate&#xD;
past criminal events. None—absolutely none—of their&#xD;
actions indicated that they perceived an imminent threat.&#xD;
They did not draw their weapons, and indeed did not&#xD;
immediately search the gas station for potential shooters.3&#xD;
To the contrary, all five testified that they questioned&#xD;
Covington before conducting any investigation at the scene.&#xD;
Would this have made any sense if they feared the pres&#xD;
ence of a shooter? Most tellingly, none of the officers&#xD;
started his interrogation by asking what would have been&#xD;
the obvious first question if any hint of such a fear existed:&#xD;
Where is the shooter?&#xD;
  But do not rely solely on my word about the officers’&#xD;
primary purpose. Listen to Sergeant Wenturine, who&#xD;
candidly admitted that he interrogated Covington because&#xD;
he “ha[d] a man here that [he] believe[d] [was] dying [so&#xD;
——————&#xD;
    3 The&#xD;
        Court cites Officer Stuglin’s testimony that “I think [Brown and&#xD;
Pellerito] did a little bit of both” joining the interrogation and helping&#xD;
to secure the scene. Id., at 135–136. But the point is not whether they&#xD;
did both; it is whether they moved to secure the area first. No officer’s&#xD;
testimony suggests this. Pellerito testified that he, Stuglin, and Brown&#xD;
arrived at the scene at roughly the same time and all three immedi&#xD;
ately went to Covington. See id., at 17–18. The testimony of Brown&#xD;
and McCallister corroborate that account. See id., at 34–36, 79–82.&#xD;
                 Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)            9&#xD;
&#xD;
                     SCALIA, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
he was] gonna find out who did this, period.” App. 112. In&#xD;
short, he needed to interrogate Covington to solve a crime.&#xD;
Wenturine never mentioned an interest in ending an&#xD;
ongoing emergency.&#xD;
  At the very least, the officers’ intentions turned investi&#xD;
gative during their 10-minute encounter with Covington,&#xD;
and the conversation “evolve[d] into testimonial state&#xD;
ments.” Davis, 547 U. S., at 828 (internal quotation&#xD;
marks omitted). The fifth officer to arrive at the scene did&#xD;
not need to run straight to Covington and ask a battery of&#xD;
questions “to determine the need for emergency assis&#xD;
tance,” Ibid. He could have asked his fellow officers, who&#xD;
presumably had a better sense of that than Covington—&#xD;
and a better sense of what he could do to assist. No, the&#xD;
value of asking the same battery of questions a fifth time&#xD;
was to ensure that Covington told a consistent story and&#xD;
to see if any new details helpful to the investigation and&#xD;
eventual prosecution would emerge. Having the testimony&#xD;
of five officers to recount Covington’s consistent story&#xD;
undoubtedly helped obtain Bryant’s conviction. (Which&#xD;
came, I may note, after the first jury could not reach a&#xD;
verdict. See 483 Mich., at 137, 768 N.W. 2d, at 67.)&#xD;
                            D&#xD;
   A final word about the Court’s active imagination. The&#xD;
Court invents a world where an ongoing emergency exists&#xD;
whenever “an armed shooter, whose motive for and lo&#xD;
cation after the shooting [are] unknown, . . . mortally&#xD;
wound[s]” one individual “within a few blocks and [25]&#xD;
minutes of the location where the police” ultimately find&#xD;
that victim. Ante, at 27. Breathlessly, it worries that a&#xD;
shooter could leave the scene armed and ready to pull the&#xD;
trigger again. See ante, at 17–18, 27, 30. Nothing sug&#xD;
gests the five officers in this case shared the Court’s&#xD;
10                     MICHIGAN v. BRYANT&#xD;
&#xD;
                         SCALIA, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
dystopian4 view of Detroit, where drug dealers hunt their&#xD;
shooting victim down and fire into a crowd of police offi&#xD;
cers to finish him off, see ante, at 30, or where spree kill&#xD;
ers shoot through a door and then roam the streets leaving&#xD;
a trail of bodies behind. Because almost 90 percent of&#xD;
murders involve a single victim,5 it is much more likely—&#xD;
indeed, I think it certain—that the officers viewed their&#xD;
encounter with Covington for what it was: an investi&#xD;
gation into a past crime with no ongoing or immediate&#xD;
consequences.&#xD;
   The Court’s distorted view creates an expansive excep&#xD;
tion to the Confrontation Clause for violent crimes. Be&#xD;
cause Bryant posed a continuing threat to public safety in&#xD;
the Court’s imagination, the emergency persisted for&#xD;
confrontation purposes at least until the police learned his&#xD;
“motive for and location after the shooting.” Ante, at 27.&#xD;
It may have persisted in this case until the police “secured&#xD;
the scene of the shooting” two-and-a-half hours later.&#xD;
Ante, at 28. (The relevance of securing the scene is un&#xD;
clear so long as the killer is still at large—especially if, as&#xD;
the Court speculates, he may be a spree-killer.) This is a&#xD;
dangerous definition of emergency. Many individuals who&#xD;
testify against a defendant at trial first offer their ac&#xD;
counts to police in the hours after a violent act. If the&#xD;
police can plausibly claim that a “potential threat to . . .&#xD;
the public” persisted through those first few hours, ante,&#xD;
at 12 (and if the claim is plausible here it is always plau&#xD;
&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  4 The opposite of utopian. The word was coined by John Stuart Mill&#xD;
&#xD;
as a caustic description of British policy. See 190 Hansard’s Parlia&#xD;
mentary Debates, Third Series 1517 (3d Ser. 1868); 5 Oxford English&#xD;
Dictionary 13 (2d ed. 1989).&#xD;
  5 See Federal Bureau of Investigation, Crime in the United States,&#xD;
&#xD;
2009: Expanded Homicide Data Table 4, Murder by Victim/Offender&#xD;
Situations, 2009 (Sept. 2010), online at http://www2.fbi.gov/ucr/&#xD;
cius2009/offenses/expanded_information/data/shrtable_04.html (as visited&#xD;
Feb. 25, 2011, and available in Clerk of Court’s case file).&#xD;
                 Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)          11&#xD;
&#xD;
                     SCALIA, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
sible) a defendant will have no constitutionally protected&#xD;
right to exclude the uncross-examined testimony of such&#xD;
witnesses. His conviction could rest (as perhaps it did&#xD;
here) solely on the officers’ recollection at trial of the&#xD;
witnesses’ accusations.&#xD;
   The Framers could not have envisioned such a hollow&#xD;
constitutional guarantee. No framing-era confrontation&#xD;
case that I know of, neither here nor in England, took such&#xD;
an enfeebled view of the right to confrontation. For exam&#xD;
ple, King v. Brasier, 1 Leach 199, 200, 168 Eng. Rep. 202,&#xD;
202–203 (K. B. 1779), held inadmissible a mother’s ac&#xD;
count of her young daughter’s statements “immediately on&#xD;
her coming home” after being sexually assaulted. The&#xD;
daughter needed to testify herself. But today’s majority&#xD;
presumably would hold the daughter’s account to her&#xD;
mother a nontestimonial statement made during an ongo&#xD;
ing emergency. She could not have known whether her&#xD;
attacker might reappear to attack again or attempt to&#xD;
silence the lone witness against him. Her mother likely&#xD;
listened to the account to assess the threat to her own&#xD;
safety and to decide whether the rapist posed a threat&#xD;
to the community that required the immediate interven&#xD;
tion of the local authorities. Cf. ante, at 29–30. Utter&#xD;
nonsense.&#xD;
   The 16th- and 17th-century English treason trials that&#xD;
helped inspire the Confrontation Clause show that today’s&#xD;
decision is a mistake. The Court’s expansive definition of&#xD;
an “ongoing emergency” and its willingness to consider the&#xD;
perspective of the interrogator and the declarant cast a&#xD;
more favorable light on those trials than history or our&#xD;
past decisions suggest they deserve. Royal officials con&#xD;
ducted many of the ex parte examinations introduced&#xD;
against Sir Walter Raleigh and Sir John Fenwick while&#xD;
investigating alleged treasonous conspiracies of unknown&#xD;
scope, aimed at killing or overthrowing the King. See&#xD;
Brief for National Association of Criminal Defense Law&#xD;
12                 MICHIGAN v. BRYANT&#xD;
&#xD;
                     SCALIA, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
yers as Amicus Curiae 21–22, and n. 11. Social stability in&#xD;
16th- and 17th-century England depended mainly on the&#xD;
continuity of the ruling monarch, cf. 1 J. Stephen, A His&#xD;
tory of the Criminal Law of England 354 (1883), so such a&#xD;
conspiracy posed the most pressing emergency imaginable.&#xD;
Presumably, the royal officials investigating it would have&#xD;
understood the gravity of the situation and would have&#xD;
focused their interrogations primarily on ending the&#xD;
threat, not on generating testimony for trial. I therefore&#xD;
doubt that under the Court’s test English officials acted&#xD;
improperly by denying Raleigh and Fenwick the opportu&#xD;
nity to confront their accusers “face to face,” id., at 326.&#xD;
  Under my approach, in contrast, those English trials&#xD;
remain unquestionably infamous. Lord Cobham did not&#xD;
speak with royal officials to end an ongoing emergency.&#xD;
He was a traitor! He spoke, as Raleigh correctly observed,&#xD;
to establish Raleigh’s guilt and to save his own life. See 1&#xD;
D. Jardine, Criminal Trials 435 (1832). Cobham’s state&#xD;
ments, when assessed from his perspective, had only a&#xD;
testimonial purpose. The same is true of Covington’s&#xD;
statements here.&#xD;
                             II &#xD;
&#xD;
                             A&#xD;
&#xD;
  But today’s decision is not only a gross distortion of the&#xD;
facts. It is a gross distortion of the law—a revisionist&#xD;
narrative in which reliability continues to guide our Con&#xD;
frontation Clause jurisprudence, at least where emergen&#xD;
cies and faux emergencies are concerned.&#xD;
  According to today’s opinion, the Davis inquiry into&#xD;
whether a declarant spoke to end an ongoing emergency or&#xD;
rather to “prove past events potentially relevant to later&#xD;
criminal prosecution,” 547 U. S., at 822, is not aimed at&#xD;
answering whether the declarant acted as a witness.&#xD;
Instead, the Davis inquiry probes the reliability of a decla&#xD;
rant’s statements, “[i]mplicit[ly]” importing the excited&#xD;
                 Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)           13&#xD;
&#xD;
                     SCALIA, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
utterances hearsay exception into the Constitution. Ante,&#xD;
at 14–15. A statement during an ongoing emergency is&#xD;
sufficiently reliable, the Court says, “because the prospect&#xD;
of fabrication . . . is presumably significantly diminished,”&#xD;
so it “does not [need] to be subject to the crucible of cross&#xD;
examination.” Id., at 14.&#xD;
   Compare that with the holding of Crawford: “Where&#xD;
testimonial statements are at issue, the only indicium of&#xD;
reliability sufficient to satisfy constitutional demands is&#xD;
the one the Constitution actually prescribes: confronta&#xD;
tion.” 541 U. S., at 68–69. Today’s opinion adopts, for&#xD;
emergencies and faux emergencies at least, the discredited&#xD;
logic of White v. Illinois, 502 U. S. 346, 355–356, and n. 8&#xD;
(1992), and Idaho v. Wright, 497 U. S. 805, 819–820&#xD;
(1990). White is, of course, the decision that both Craw&#xD;
ford and Davis found most incompatible with the text and&#xD;
history of the Confrontation Clause. See Davis, supra, at&#xD;
825; Crawford, supra, at 58, n. 8. (This is not to say that&#xD;
that “reliability” logic can actually justify today’s result:&#xD;
Twenty-five minutes is plenty of time for a shooting victim&#xD;
to reflect and fabricate a false story.)&#xD;
   The Court announces that in future cases it will look to&#xD;
“standard rules of hearsay, designed to identify some&#xD;
statements as reliable,” when deciding whether a state&#xD;
ment is testimonial. Ante, at 11–12. Ohio v. Roberts, 448&#xD;
U. S. 56 (1980) said something remarkably similar: An&#xD;
out-of-court statement is admissible if it “falls within a&#xD;
firmly rooted hearsay exception” or otherwise “bears ade&#xD;
quate ‘indicia of reliability.’ ” Id., at 66. We tried that&#xD;
approach to the Confrontation Clause for nearly 25 years&#xD;
before Crawford rejected it as an unworkable standard&#xD;
unmoored from the text and the historical roots of the&#xD;
Confrontation Clause. See 541 U. S., at 54, 60, 63–65, 67–&#xD;
68. The arguments in Raleigh’s infamous 17th-century&#xD;
treason trial contained full debate about the reliability of&#xD;
Lord Cobham’s ex parte accusations, see Raleigh’s Case,&#xD;
14                  MICHIGAN v. BRYANT&#xD;
&#xD;
                     SCALIA, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
2 How. St. Tr. 1, 14, 17, 19–20, 22–23, 29 (1603); that&#xD;
case remains the canonical example of a Confrontation&#xD;
Clause violation, not because Raleigh should have won the&#xD;
debate but because he should have been allowed&#xD;
cross-examination.&#xD;
   The Court attempts to fit its resurrected interest in&#xD;
reliability into the Crawford framework, but the result is&#xD;
incoherent. Reliability, the Court tells us, is a good indi&#xD;
cator of whether “a statement is . . . an out-of-court substi&#xD;
tute for trial testimony.” Ante, at 11. That is patently&#xD;
false. Reliability tells us nothing about whether a state&#xD;
ment is testimonial. Testimonial and nontestimonial&#xD;
statements alike come in varying degrees of reliability.&#xD;
An eyewitness’s statements to the police after a fender&#xD;
bender, for example, are both reliable and testimonial.&#xD;
Statements to the police from one driver attempting to&#xD;
blame the other would be similarly testimonial but rarely&#xD;
reliable.&#xD;
   The Court suggests otherwise because it “misunder&#xD;
stands the relationship” between qualification for one of&#xD;
the standard hearsay exceptions and exemption from the&#xD;
confrontation requirement. Melendez-Diaz v. Massachu&#xD;
setts, 557 U. S. ___, ___ (2009) (slip op., at 18). That rela&#xD;
tionship is not a causal one. Hearsay law exempts busi&#xD;
ness records, for example, because businesses have a&#xD;
financial incentive to keep reliable records. See Fed. Rule&#xD;
Evid. 803(6). The Sixth Amendment also generally admits&#xD;
business records into evidence, but not because the records&#xD;
are reliable or because hearsay law says so. It admits&#xD;
them “because—having been created for the administra&#xD;
tion of an entity’s affairs and not for the purpose of estab&#xD;
lishing or proving some fact at trial—they are not” weaker&#xD;
substitutes for live testimony. Melendez-Diaz, 557 U. S.,&#xD;
at ___ (slip op., at 18). Moreover, the scope of the exemp&#xD;
tion from confrontation and that of the hearsay exceptions&#xD;
also are not always coextensive. The reliability logic of the&#xD;
                 Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)          15&#xD;
&#xD;
                     SCALIA, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
business-record exception would extend to records main&#xD;
tained by neutral parties providing litigation-support&#xD;
services, such as evidence testing. The Confrontation&#xD;
Clause is not so forgiving. Business records prepared&#xD;
specifically for use at a criminal trial are testimonial and&#xD;
require confrontation. See ibid.&#xD;
  Is it possible that the Court does not recognize the&#xD;
contradiction between its focus on reliable statements and&#xD;
Crawford’s focus on testimonial ones? Does it not realize&#xD;
that the two cannot coexist? Or does it intend, by follow&#xD;
ing today’s illogical roadmap, to resurrect Roberts by a&#xD;
thousand unprincipled distinctions without ever explicitly&#xD;
overruling Crawford? After all, honestly overruling Craw&#xD;
ford would destroy the illusion of judicial minimalism and&#xD;
restraint. And it would force the Court to explain how&#xD;
the Justices’ preference comports with the meaning of the&#xD;
Confrontation Clause that the People adopted—or to&#xD;
confess that only the Justices’ preference really matters.&#xD;
                              B&#xD;
  The Court recedes from Crawford in a second significant&#xD;
way. It requires judges to conduct “open-ended balancing&#xD;
tests” and “amorphous, if not entirely subjective,” inquir&#xD;
ies into the totality of the circumstances bearing upon&#xD;
reliability. 541 U. S., at 63, 68. Where the prosecution&#xD;
cries “emergency,” the admissibility of a statement now&#xD;
turns on “a highly context-dependent inquiry,” ante, at 16,&#xD;
into the type of weapon the defendant wielded, see ante, at&#xD;
17; the type of crime the defendant committed, see ante, at&#xD;
12, 16–17; the medical condition of the declarant, see ante,&#xD;
at 17–18; if the declarant is injured, whether paramedics&#xD;
have arrived on the scene, see ante, at 20; whether the&#xD;
encounter takes place in an “exposed public area,” ibid.;&#xD;
whether the encounter appears disorganized, see ibid.;&#xD;
whether the declarant is capable of forming a purpose, see&#xD;
ante, at 22; whether the police have secured the scene of&#xD;
16                 MICHIGAN v. BRYANT&#xD;
&#xD;
                     SCALIA, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
the crime, see ante, at 28; the formality of the statement,&#xD;
see ante, at 19; and finally, whether the statement strikes&#xD;
us as reliable, see ante, at 11–12, 14–15. This is no better&#xD;
than the nine-factor balancing test we rejected in Craw&#xD;
ford, 541 U. S., at 63. I do not look forward to resolving&#xD;
conflicts in the future over whether knives and poison are&#xD;
more like guns or fists for Confrontation Clause purposes,&#xD;
or whether rape and armed robbery are more like murder&#xD;
or domestic violence.&#xD;
   It can be said, of course, that under Crawford analysis&#xD;
of whether a statement is testimonial requires considera&#xD;
tion of all the circumstances, and so is also something of a&#xD;
multifactor balancing test. But the “reliability” test does&#xD;
not replace that analysis; it supplements it. As I under&#xD;
stand the Court’s opinion, even when it is determined that&#xD;
no emergency exists (or perhaps before that determination&#xD;
is made) the statement would be found admissible as far&#xD;
as the Confrontation Clause is concerned if it is not&#xD;
testimonial.&#xD;
   In any case, we did not disavow multifactor balancing&#xD;
for reliability in Crawford out of a preference for rules&#xD;
over standards. We did so because it “d[id] violence to” the&#xD;
Framers’ design. Id., at 68. It was judges’ open-ended&#xD;
determination of what was reliable that violated the trial&#xD;
rights of Englishmen in the political trials of the 16th and&#xD;
17th centuries. See, e.g., Throckmorton’s Case, 1 How. St.&#xD;
Tr. 869, 875–876 (1554); Raleigh’s Case, 2 How. St. Tr., at&#xD;
15–16, 24. The Framers placed the Confrontation Clause&#xD;
in the Bill of Rights to ensure that those abuses (and the&#xD;
abuses by the Admiralty courts in colonial America) would&#xD;
not be repeated in this country. Not even the least dan&#xD;
gerous branch can be trusted to assess the reliability of&#xD;
uncross-examined testimony in politically charged trials or&#xD;
trials implicating threats to national security. See Craw&#xD;
ford, supra, at 67–68; cf. Hamdi v. Rumsfeld, 542 U. S.&#xD;
507, 576–578 (2004) (SCALIA, J., dissenting).&#xD;
                 Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)           17&#xD;
&#xD;
                     SCALIA, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
                          *    *     *&#xD;
   Judicial decisions, like the Constitution itself, are noth&#xD;
ing more than “parchment barriers,” 5 Writings of James&#xD;
Madison 269, 272 (G. Hunt ed. 1901). Both depend on a&#xD;
judicial culture that understands its constitutionally&#xD;
assigned role, has the courage to persist in that role when&#xD;
it means announcing unpopular decisions, and has the&#xD;
modesty to persist when it produces results that go&#xD;
against the judges’ policy preferences. Today’s opinion&#xD;
falls far short of living up to that obligation—short on the&#xD;
facts, and short on the law.&#xD;
   For all I know, Bryant has received his just deserts. But&#xD;
he surely has not received them pursuant to the proce&#xD;
dures that our Constitution requires. And what has been&#xD;
taken away from him has been taken away from us all.&#xD;
                 Cite as: 562 U. S. ____ (2011)            1&#xD;
&#xD;
                    GINSBURG, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES&#xD;
                         _________________&#xD;
&#xD;
                          No. 09–150&#xD;
                         _________________&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
    MICHIGAN, PETITIONER v. RICHARD PERRY &#xD;
&#xD;
                   BRYANT &#xD;
&#xD;
     ON WRIT OF CERTIORARI TO THE SUPREME COURT&#xD;
&#xD;
                     OF MICHIGAN&#xD;
&#xD;
                      [February 28, 2011] &#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
   JUSTICE GINSBURG, dissenting.&#xD;
   I agree with JUSTICE SCALIA that Covington’s state&#xD;
ments were testimonial and that “[t]he declarant’s intent&#xD;
is what counts.” Ante, at 2 (dissenting opinion). Even if&#xD;
the interrogators’ intent were what counts, I further&#xD;
agree, Covington’s statements would still be testimonial.&#xD;
Ante, at 8. It is most likely that “the officers viewed their&#xD;
encounter with Covington [as] an investigation into a past&#xD;
crime with no ongoing or immediate consequences.” Ante,&#xD;
at 10. Today’s decision, JUSTICE SCALIA rightly notes,&#xD;
“creates an expansive exception to the Confrontation&#xD;
Clause for violent crimes.” Ibid. In so doing, the decision&#xD;
confounds our recent Confrontation Clause jurisprudence,&#xD;
ante, at 12, which made it plain that “[r]eliability tells us&#xD;
nothing about whether a statement is testimonial,” ante,&#xD;
at 14 (emphasis deleted).&#xD;
   I would add, however, this observation. In Crawford v.&#xD;
Washington, 541 U. S. 36, 56, n. 6 (2004), this Court noted&#xD;
that, in the law we inherited from England, there was a&#xD;
well-established exception to the confrontation require&#xD;
ment: The cloak protecting the accused against admission&#xD;
of out-of-court testimonial statements was removed for&#xD;
dying declarations. This historic exception, we recalled in&#xD;
Giles v. California, 554 U. S. 353, 358 (2008); see id., at&#xD;
361–362, 368, applied to statements made by a person&#xD;
2                  MICHIGAN v. BRYANT&#xD;
&#xD;
                   GINSBURG, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
about to die and aware that death was imminent. Were&#xD;
the issue properly tendered here, I would take up the&#xD;
question whether the exception for dying declarations&#xD;
survives our recent Confrontation Clause decisions. The&#xD;
Michigan Supreme Court, however, held, as a matter of&#xD;
state law, that the prosecutor had abandoned the issue.&#xD;
See &lt;/pre&gt;&lt;span class="citation"&gt;&lt;a href="/mich/5hKN/people-v-bryant/"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;483&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;Mich.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;132&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;pre class="inline"&gt;, 156–157, 768 N. W. 2d 65, 78 (2009).&#xD;
The matter, therefore, is not one the Court can address in&#xD;
this case.&#xD;
&lt;/pre&gt;</opinion>