<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><opinion id="621044" path="/scotus/4bBE/golan-v-holder/" sha1="44b9028bf4afd8452a04f8249e09d35815e9819a" court="Supreme Court of the United States" download_URL="http://www.supremecourt.gov/opinions/11pdf/10-545.pdf" time_retrieved="2012-01-18 15:37:05+00:00" date_filed="2012-01-18" precedential_status="Published" local_path="pdf/2012/01/18/Golan_v._Holder.pdf" docket_number="10-545" federal_cite_one="" lexis_cite="" case_name="Golan v. Holder" judges="" nature_of_suit="" source="court website" blocked="False" date_blocked="None" extracted_by_ocr="False">&lt;pre class="inline"&gt;(Slip Opinion)              OCTOBER TERM, 2011                                       1&#xD;
&#xD;
                                       Syllabus&#xD;
&#xD;
         NOTE: Where it is feasible, a syllabus (headnote) will be released, as is&#xD;
       being done in connection with this case, at the time the opinion is issued.&#xD;
       The syllabus constitutes no part of the opinion of the Court but has been&#xD;
       prepared by the Reporter of Decisions for the convenience of the reader.&#xD;
       See United States v. Detroit Timber &amp; Lumber Co., 200 U. S. 321, 337.&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES&#xD;
&#xD;
                                       Syllabus&#xD;
&#xD;
    GOLAN ET AL. v. HOLDER, ATTORNEY GENERAL, &#xD;
&#xD;
                        ET AL. &#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
CERTIORARI TO THE UNITED STATES COURT OF APPEALS FOR&#xD;
                 THE TENTH CIRCUIT&#xD;
&#xD;
    No. 10–545.     Argued October 5, 2011—Decided January 18, 2012&#xD;
The Berne Convention for the Protection of Literary and Artistic Works&#xD;
  (Berne), which took effect in 1886, is the principal accord governing&#xD;
  international copyright relations. Berne’s 164 member states agree&#xD;
  to provide a minimum level of copyright protection and to treat au-&#xD;
  thors from other member countries as well as they treat their own.&#xD;
  Of central importance in this case, Article 18 of Berne requires coun-&#xD;
  tries to protect the works of other member states unless the works’&#xD;
  copyright term has expired in either the country where protection is&#xD;
  claimed or the country of origin. A different system of transnational&#xD;
  copyright protection long prevailed in this country. Throughout most&#xD;
  of the 20th century, the only foreign authors eligible for Copyright&#xD;
  Act protection were those whose countries granted reciprocal rights&#xD;
  to American authors and whose works were printed in the United&#xD;
  States. Despite Article 18, when the United States joined Berne in&#xD;
  1989, it did not protect any foreign works lodged in the U. S. public&#xD;
  domain, many of them works never protected here. In 1994, howev-&#xD;
  er, the Agreement on Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property&#xD;
  Rights mandated implementation of Berne’s first 21 articles, on pain&#xD;
  of enforcement by the World Trade Organization.&#xD;
     In response, Congress applied the term of protection available to&#xD;
  U. S. works to preexisting works from Berne member countries. Sec-&#xD;
  tion 514 of the Uruguay Round Agreements Act (URAA) grants copy-&#xD;
  right protection to works protected in their country of origin, but&#xD;
  lacking protection in the United States for any of three reasons: The&#xD;
  United States did not protect works from the country of origin at the&#xD;
  time of publication; the United States did not protect sound record-&#xD;
  ings fixed before 1972; or the author had not complied with certain&#xD;
2                          GOLAN v. HOLDER&#xD;
&#xD;
                                 Syllabus&#xD;
&#xD;
    U. S. statutory formalities. Works encompassed by §514 are granted&#xD;
    the protection they would have enjoyed had the United States main-&#xD;
    tained copyright relations with the author’s country or removed for-&#xD;
    malities incompatible with Berne. As a consequence of the barriers&#xD;
    to U. S. copyright protection prior to §514’s enactment, foreign works&#xD;
    “restored” to protection by the measure had entered the public do-&#xD;
    main in this country. To cushion the impact of their placement in&#xD;
    protected status, §514 provides ameliorating accommodations for&#xD;
    parties who had exploited affected works before the URAA was&#xD;
    enacted.&#xD;
      Petitioners are orchestra conductors, musicians, publishers, and&#xD;
    others who formerly enjoyed free access to works §514 removed from&#xD;
    the public domain. They maintain that Congress, in passing §514,&#xD;
    exceeded its authority under the Copyright Clause and transgressed&#xD;
    First Amendment limitations. The District Court granted the Attor-&#xD;
    ney General’s motion for summary judgment. Affirming in part, the&#xD;
    Tenth Circuit agreed that Congress had not offended the Copyright&#xD;
    Clause, but concluded that §514 required further First Amendment&#xD;
    inspection in light of Eldred v. Ashcroft, 537 U. S. 186. On remand,&#xD;
    the District Court granted summary judgment to petitioners on the&#xD;
    First Amendment claim, holding that §514’s constriction of the public&#xD;
    domain was not justified by any of the asserted federal interests. The&#xD;
    Tenth Circuit reversed, ruling that §514 was narrowly tailored to fit&#xD;
    the important government aim of protecting U. S. copyright holders’&#xD;
    interests abroad.&#xD;
Held:&#xD;
    1. Section 514 does not exceed Congress’ authority under the Copy-&#xD;
 right Clause. Pp. 13–23.&#xD;
       (a) The text of the Copyright Clause does not exclude application&#xD;
 of copyright protection to works in the public domain. Eldred is&#xD;
 largely dispositive of petitioners’ claim that the Clause’s confinement&#xD;
 of a copyright’s lifespan to a “limited Tim[e]” prevents the removal of&#xD;
 works from the public domain. In Eldred, the Court upheld the Cop-&#xD;
 yright Term Extension Act (CTEA), which extended, by 20 years, the&#xD;
 terms of existing copyrights. The text of the Copyright Clause, the&#xD;
 Court observed, contains no “command that a time prescription, once&#xD;
 set, becomes forever ‘fixed’ or ‘inalterable,’ ” and the Court declined to&#xD;
 infer any such command. 537 U. S., at 199. The construction peti-&#xD;
 tioners tender here is similarly infirm. The terms afforded works re-&#xD;
 stored by §514 are no less “limited” than those the CTEA lengthened.&#xD;
 Nor had the “limited Tim[e]” already passed for the works at issue&#xD;
 here—many of them works formerly denied any U. S. copyright pro-&#xD;
 tection—for a period of exclusivity must begin before it may end. Pe-&#xD;
 titioners also urge that the Government’s position would allow Con-&#xD;
                   Cite as: 565 U. S. ____ (2012)                      3&#xD;
&#xD;
                              Syllabus&#xD;
&#xD;
gress to legislate perpetual copyright terms by instituting successive&#xD;
“limited” terms as prior terms expire. But as in Eldred, such hypo-&#xD;
thetical misbehavior is far afield from this case. In aligning the&#xD;
United States with other nations bound by Berne, Congress can hard-&#xD;
ly be charged with a design to move stealthily toward a perpetual&#xD;
copyright regime. Pp. 13–15.&#xD;
   (b) Historical practice corroborates the Court’s reading of the Copy-&#xD;
right Clause to permit the protection of previously unprotected&#xD;
works. In the Copyright Act of 1790, the First Congress protected&#xD;
works that had been freely reproducible under State copyright laws.&#xD;
Subsequent actions confirm that Congress has not understood the&#xD;
Copyright Clause to preclude protection for existing works. Several&#xD;
private bills restored the copyrights and patents of works and inven-&#xD;
tions previously in the public domain. Congress has also passed gen-&#xD;
erally applicable legislation granting copyrights and patents to works&#xD;
and inventions that had lost protection. Pp. 15–19.&#xD;
   (c) Petitioners also argue that §514 fails to “promote the Progress of&#xD;
Science” as contemplated by the initial words of the Copyright&#xD;
Clause. Specifically, they claim that because §514 affects only works&#xD;
already created, it cannot meet the Clause’s objective. The creation&#xD;
of new works, however, is not the sole way Congress may promote&#xD;
“Science,” i.e., knowledge and learning. In Eldred, this Court rejected&#xD;
a nearly identical argument, concluding that the Clause does not de-&#xD;
mand that each copyright provision, examined discretely, operate to&#xD;
induce new works. Rather the Clause “empowers Congress to deter-&#xD;
mine the intellectual property regimes that, overall, in that body’s&#xD;
judgment, will serve the ends of the Clause.” 537 U. S., at 222.&#xD;
Nothing in the text or history of the Copyright Clause, moreover, con-&#xD;
fines the “Progress of Science” exclusively to “incentives for creation.”&#xD;
Historical evidence, congressional practice, and this Court’s deci-&#xD;
sions, in fact, suggest that inducing the dissemination of existing&#xD;
works is an appropriate means to promote science. Pp. 20–22.&#xD;
   (d) Considered against this backdrop, §514 falls comfortably within&#xD;
Congress’ Copyright Clause authority. Congress had reason to be-&#xD;
lieve that a well-functioning international copyright system would&#xD;
encourage the dissemination of existing and future works. And tes-&#xD;
timony informed Congress that full compliance with Berne would ex-&#xD;
pand the foreign markets available to U. S. authors and invigorate&#xD;
protection against piracy of U. S. works abroad, thus benefitting cop-&#xD;
yright-intensive industries stateside and inducing greater investment&#xD;
in the creative process. This Court has no warrant to reject Congress’&#xD;
rational judgment that exemplary adherence to Berne would serve&#xD;
the objectives of the Copyright Clause. Pp. 22–23.&#xD;
   2. The First Amendment does not inhibit the restoration author-&#xD;
4                           GOLAN v. HOLDER&#xD;
&#xD;
                                  Syllabus&#xD;
&#xD;
    ized by §514. Pp. 23–32.&#xD;
         (a) The pathmarking Eldred decision is again instructive. There,&#xD;
    the Court held that the CTEA’s enlargement of a copyright’s duration&#xD;
    did not offend the First Amendment’s freedom of expression guaran-&#xD;
    tee. Recognizing that some restriction on expression is the inherent&#xD;
    and intended effect of every grant of copyright, the Court observed&#xD;
    that the Framers regarded copyright protection not simply as a limit&#xD;
    on the manner in which expressive works may be used, but also as an&#xD;
    “engine of free expression.” 537 U. S., at 219. The “traditional con-&#xD;
    tours” of copyright protection, i.e., the “idea/expression dichotomy”&#xD;
    and the “fair use” defense, moreover, serve as “built-in First Amend-&#xD;
    ment accommodations.” Ibid. Given the speech-protective purposes&#xD;
    and safeguards embraced by copyright law, there was no call for the&#xD;
    heightened review sought in Eldred. The Court reaches the same&#xD;
    conclusion here. Section 514 leaves undisturbed the idea/expression&#xD;
    distinction and the fair use defense. Moreover, Congress adopted&#xD;
    measures to ease the transition from a national scheme to an inter-&#xD;
    national copyright regime. Pp. 23–26.&#xD;
         (b) Petitioners claim that First Amendment interests of a higher&#xD;
    order are at stake because they—unlike their Eldred counterparts—&#xD;
    enjoyed “vested rights” in works that had already entered the public&#xD;
    domain. Their contentions depend on an argument already consid-&#xD;
    ered and rejected, namely, that the Constitution renders the public&#xD;
    domain largely untouchable by Congress. Nothing in the historical&#xD;
    record, subsequent congressional practice, or this Court’s jurispru-&#xD;
    dence warrants exceptional First Amendment solicitude for copy-&#xD;
    righted works that were once in the public domain. Congress has&#xD;
    several times adjusted copyright law to protect new categories of&#xD;
    works as well as works previously in the public domain. Section 514,&#xD;
    moreover, does not impose a blanket prohibition on public access.&#xD;
    The question is whether would-be users of certain foreign works must&#xD;
    pay for their desired use of the author’s expression, or else limit their&#xD;
    exploitation to “fair use” of those works. By fully implementing&#xD;
    Berne, Congress ensured that these works, like domestic and most&#xD;
    other foreign works, would be governed by the same legal regime.&#xD;
    Section 514 simply placed foreign works in the position they would&#xD;
    have occupied if the current copyright regime had been in effect when&#xD;
    those works were created and first published. Pp. 26–30.&#xD;
609 F. 3d 1076, affirmed.&#xD;
&#xD;
  GINSBURG, J., delivered the opinion of the Court, in which ROBERTS,&#xD;
C. J., and SCALIA, KENNEDY, THOMAS, and SOTOMAYOR, JJ., joined.&#xD;
BREYER, J., filed a dissenting opinion, in which ALITO, J., joined. KA-&#xD;
GAN, J., took no part in the consideration or decision of the case.&#xD;
                        Cite as: 565 U. S. ____ (2012)                              1&#xD;
&#xD;
                             Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
     NOTICE: This opinion is subject to formal revision before publication in the&#xD;
     preliminary print of the United States Reports. Readers are requested to&#xD;
     notify the Reporter of Decisions, Supreme Court of the United States, Wash-&#xD;
     ington, D. C. 20543, of any typographical or other formal errors, in order&#xD;
     that corrections may be made before the preliminary print goes to press.&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES&#xD;
                                   _________________&#xD;
&#xD;
                                   No. 10–545&#xD;
                                   _________________&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
LAWRENCE GOLAN, ET AL., PETITIONERS v. ERIC H.&#xD;
   HOLDER, JR., ATTORNEY GENERAL, ET AL.&#xD;
 ON WRIT OF CERTIORARI TO THE UNITED STATES COURT OF&#xD;
            APPEALS FOR THE TENTH CIRCUIT&#xD;
                               [January 18, 2012]&#xD;
&#xD;
   JUSTICE GINSBURG delivered the opinion of the Court.&#xD;
   The Berne Convention for the Protection of Literary and&#xD;
Artistic Works (Berne Convention or Berne), which took&#xD;
effect in 1886, is the principal accord governing interna-&#xD;
tional copyright relations. Latecomer to the international&#xD;
copyright regime launched by Berne, the United States&#xD;
joined the Convention in 1989. To perfect U. S. implemen-&#xD;
tation of Berne, and as part of our response to the Uru-&#xD;
guay Round of multilateral trade negotiations, Congress,&#xD;
in 1994, gave works enjoying copyright protection abroad&#xD;
the same full term of protection available to U. S. works.&#xD;
Congress did so in §514 of the Uruguay Round Agree-&#xD;
ments Act (URAA), which grants copyright protection to&#xD;
preexisting works of Berne member countries, protected in&#xD;
their country of origin, but lacking protection in the United&#xD;
States for any of three reasons: The United States did&#xD;
not protect works from the country of origin at the time of&#xD;
publication; the United States did not protect sound record-&#xD;
ings fixed before 1972; or the author had failed to comply&#xD;
with U. S. statutory formalities (formalities Congress no&#xD;
longer requires as prerequisites to copyright protection).&#xD;
   The URAA accords no protection to a foreign work after&#xD;
2                    GOLAN v. HOLDER&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
its full copyright term has expired, causing it to fall into&#xD;
the public domain, whether under the laws of the country&#xD;
of origin or of this country. Works encompassed by §514&#xD;
are granted the protection they would have enjoyed had&#xD;
the United States maintained copyright relations with the&#xD;
author’s country or removed formalities incompatible with&#xD;
Berne. Foreign authors, however, gain no credit for the&#xD;
protection they lacked in years prior to §514’s enactment.&#xD;
They therefore enjoy fewer total years of exclusivity than&#xD;
do their U. S. counterparts. As a consequence of the barri-&#xD;
ers to U. S. copyright protection prior to the enactment of&#xD;
§514, foreign works “restored” to protection by the meas-&#xD;
ure had entered the public domain in this country. To&#xD;
cushion the impact of their placement in protected status,&#xD;
Congress included in §514 ameliorating accommodations&#xD;
for parties who had exploited affected works before the&#xD;
URAA was enacted.&#xD;
   Petitioners include orchestra conductors, musicians, pub-&#xD;
lishers, and others who formerly enjoyed free access to&#xD;
works §514 removed from the public domain. They main-&#xD;
tain that the Constitution’s Copyright and Patent Clause,&#xD;
Art. I, §8, cl. 8, and First Amendment both decree the&#xD;
invalidity of §514. Under those prescriptions of our high-&#xD;
est law, petitioners assert, a work that has entered the&#xD;
public domain, for whatever reason, must forever remain&#xD;
there.&#xD;
   In accord with the judgment of the Tenth Circuit, we&#xD;
conclude that §514 does not transgress constitutional&#xD;
limitations on Congress’ authority. Neither the Copyright&#xD;
and Patent Clause nor the First Amendment, we hold,&#xD;
makes the public domain, in any and all cases, a territory&#xD;
that works may never exit.&#xD;
                          I&#xD;
                          A&#xD;
  Members of the Berne Union agree to treat authors from&#xD;
other member countries as well as they treat their own.&#xD;
                      Cite as: 565 U. S. ____ (2012)                      3&#xD;
&#xD;
                           Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
Berne Convention, Sept. 9, 1886, as revised at Stockholm&#xD;
on July 14, 1967, Art. 1, 5(1), 828 U. N. T. S. 221, 225,&#xD;
231–233. Nationals of a member country, as well as any&#xD;
author who publishes in one of Berne’s 164 member states,&#xD;
thus enjoy copyright protection in nations across the globe.&#xD;
Art. 2(6), 3. Each country, moreover, must afford at least&#xD;
the minimum level of protection specified by Berne. The&#xD;
copyright term must span the author’s lifetime, plus at&#xD;
least 50 additional years, whether or not the author has&#xD;
complied with a member state’s legal formalities. Art.&#xD;
5(2), 7(1). And, as relevant here, a work must be protected&#xD;
abroad unless its copyright term has expired in either the&#xD;
country where protection is claimed or the country of&#xD;
origin. Art. 18(1)–(2).1&#xD;
  A different system of transnational copyright protection&#xD;
long prevailed in this country. Until 1891, foreign works&#xD;
were categorically excluded from Copyright Act protection.&#xD;
Throughout most of the 20th century, the only eligible&#xD;
foreign authors were those whose countries granted recip-&#xD;
rocal rights to U. S. authors and whose works were print&#xD;
&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  1 Article  18 of the Berne Convention provides:&#xD;
   “(1) This Convention shall apply to all works which, at the moment of&#xD;
its coming into force, have not yet fallen into the public domain in the&#xD;
country of origin through the expiry of the term of protection.&#xD;
   “(2) If, however, through the expiry of the term of protection which&#xD;
was previously granted, a work has fallen into the public domain of the&#xD;
country where protection is claimed, that work shall not be protected&#xD;
anew.&#xD;
   “(3) The application of this principle shall be subject to any provisions&#xD;
contained in special conventions to that effect existing or to be conclud-&#xD;
ed between countries of the Union. In the absence of such provisions,&#xD;
the respective countries shall determine, each in so far as it is con-&#xD;
cerned, the conditions of application of this principle.&#xD;
   “(4) The preceding provisions shall also apply in the case of new&#xD;
accessions to the Union and to cases in which protection is extended by&#xD;
the application of Article 7 or by the abandonment of reservations.”&#xD;
828 U. N. T. S. 251.&#xD;
4                        GOLAN v. HOLDER&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
ed in the United States. See Act of Mar. 3, 1891, §3, 13, 26&#xD;
Stat. 1107, 1110; Patry, The United States and Inter-&#xD;
national Copyright Law, 40 Houston L. Rev. 749, 750&#xD;
(2003).2 For domestic and foreign authors alike, protection&#xD;
hinged on compliance with notice, registration, and re-&#xD;
newal formalities.&#xD;
  The United States became party to Berne’s multilateral,&#xD;
formality-free copyright regime in 1989. Initially, Con-&#xD;
gress adopted a “minimalist approach” to compliance with&#xD;
the Convention. H. R. Rep. No. 100–609, p. 7 (1988) (here-&#xD;
inafter BCIA House Report). The Berne Convention Im-&#xD;
plementation Act of 1988 (BCIA), 102 Stat. 2853, made&#xD;
“only those changes to American copyright law that [were]&#xD;
clearly required under the treaty’s provisions,” BCIA&#xD;
House Report, at 7. Despite Berne’s instruction that&#xD;
member countries—including “new accessions to the Union”—&#xD;
protect foreign works under copyright in the country&#xD;
of origin, Art. 18(1) and (4), 828 U. N. T. S., at 251, the&#xD;
BCIA accorded no protection for “any work that is in the&#xD;
public domain in the United States,” §12, 102 Stat. 2860.&#xD;
Protection of future foreign works, the BCIA indicated,&#xD;
satisfied Article 18. See §2(3), 102 Stat. 2853 (“The&#xD;
amendments made by this Act, together with the law as it&#xD;
exists on the date of the enactment of this Act, satisfy the&#xD;
obligations of the United States in adhering to the Berne&#xD;
Convention . . . .”). Congress indicated, however, that it&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
——————&#xD;
   2 As noted by the Government’s amici, the United States excluded&#xD;
&#xD;
foreign works from copyright not to swell the number of unprotected&#xD;
works available to the consuming public, but to favor domestic publish-&#xD;
ing interests that escaped paying royalties to foreign authors. See Brief&#xD;
for International Publishers Association et al. as Amici Curiae 8–15.&#xD;
This free-riding, according to Senator Jonathan Chace, champion of the&#xD;
1891 Act, made the United States “the Barbary coast of literature” and&#xD;
its people “the buccaneers of books.” S. Rep. No. 622, 50th Cong., 1st&#xD;
Sess., p. 2 (1888).&#xD;
                     Cite as: 565 U. S. ____ (2012)                   5&#xD;
&#xD;
                         Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
had not definitively rejected “retroactive” protection for&#xD;
preexisting foreign works; instead it had punted on this&#xD;
issue of Berne’s implementation, deferring consideration&#xD;
until “a more thorough examination of Constitutional,&#xD;
commercial, and consumer considerations is possible.”&#xD;
BCIA House Report, at 51, 52.3&#xD;
  The minimalist approach essayed by the United States&#xD;
did not sit well with other Berne members.4 While negoti-&#xD;
——————&#xD;
   3 See also S. Rep. No. 103–412, p. 225 (1994) (“While the United&#xD;
&#xD;
States declared its compliance with the Berne Convention in 1989, it&#xD;
never addressed or enacted legislation to implement Article 18 of&#xD;
the Convention.”); Memorandum from Chris Schroeder, Counselor to the&#xD;
Assistant Attorney General, Office of Legal Counsel, Dept. of Justice&#xD;
(DOJ), to Ira S. Shapiro, General Counsel, Office of the U. S. Trade&#xD;
Representative (July 29, 1994), in W. Patry, Copyright and the GATT,&#xD;
p. C–15 (1995) (“At the time Congress was debating the BCIA, it&#xD;
reserved the issue of removing works from the public domain.”); Gen-&#xD;
eral Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT): Intellectual Property&#xD;
Provisions, Joint Hearing before the Subcommittee on Intellectual&#xD;
Property and Judicial Administration of the House Committee on the&#xD;
Judiciary and the Subcommittee on Patents, Copyrights and Trade-&#xD;
marks of the Senate Committee on the Judiciary, 103d Cong., 2d&#xD;
Sess., p. 120 (1994) (URAA Joint Hearing) (app. to statement of Bruce&#xD;
A. Lehman, Assistant Secretary of Commerce and Commissioner of&#xD;
Patents and Trademarks (Commerce Dept.)) (“When the United States&#xD;
adhered to the Berne Convention, Congress . . . acknowledged that the&#xD;
possibility of restoring copyright protection for foreign works that had&#xD;
fallen into the public domain in the United States for failure to comply&#xD;
with formalities was an issue that merited further discussion.”).&#xD;
   4 The dissent implicitly agrees that, whatever tentative conclusion&#xD;
&#xD;
Congress reached in 1988, Article 18 requires the United States to&#xD;
“protect the foreign works at issue,” at least absent a special conven-&#xD;
tion the United States did not here negotiate. Post, at 22. See&#xD;
also post, at 23 (citing Gervais, Golan v. Holder: A Look at the Con-&#xD;
straints Imposed by the Berne Convention, 64 Vand. L. Rev. En Banc&#xD;
147, 151–152 (2011)); id., at 152 (“[T]he Convention clearly requires&#xD;
that some level of protection be given to foreign authors whose works&#xD;
have entered the public domain (other than by expiration of previous&#xD;
copyright).”). Accord S. Ricketson, The Berne Convention for the&#xD;
Protection of Literary and Artistic Works 1886–1986, p. 675 (1987)&#xD;
6                         GOLAN v. HOLDER&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
ations were ongoing over the North American Free Trade&#xD;
Agreement (NAFTA), Mexican authorities complained&#xD;
about the United States’ refusal to grant protection, in&#xD;
accord with Article 18, to Mexican works that remained&#xD;
under copyright domestically. See Intellectual Property&#xD;
and International Issues, Hearings before the Subcommit-&#xD;
tee on Intellectual Property and Judicial Administration,&#xD;
House Committee on the Judiciary, 102d Cong., 1st Sess.,&#xD;
168 (1991) (statement of Ralph Oman, U. S. Register of&#xD;
Copyrights).5 The Register of Copyrights also reported&#xD;
“questions” from Turkey, Egypt, and Austria. Ibid. Thai-&#xD;
land and Russia balked at protecting U. S. works, copy-&#xD;
righted here but in those countries’ public domains, until&#xD;
the United States reciprocated with respect to their au-&#xD;
thors’ works. URAA Joint Hearing 137 (statement of Ira&#xD;
S. Shapiro, General Counsel, Office of the U. S. Trade&#xD;
Representative (USTR)); id., at 208 (statement of Profes-&#xD;
sor Shira Perlmutter); id., at 291 (statement of Jason S.&#xD;
Berman, Recording Industry Association of America&#xD;
(RIAA)).6&#xD;
——————&#xD;
(“There is no basis on which [protection of existing works under Article&#xD;
18] can be completely denied. The conditions and reservations,” au-&#xD;
thorized by Article 18(3) [and stressed by the dissent, post, at 23–24]&#xD;
are of “limited” and “transitional” duration and “would not be permitted&#xD;
to deny [protection] altogether in relation to a particular class . . . of&#xD;
works.”).&#xD;
  5 NAFTA ultimately included a limited retroactivity provision—a&#xD;
&#xD;
precursor to §514 of the URAA—granting U. S. copyright protection to&#xD;
certain Mexican and Canadian films. These films had fallen into the&#xD;
public domain, between 1978 and 1988, for failure to meet U. S. notice&#xD;
requirements. See North American Free Trade Agreement Implemen-&#xD;
tation Act, §334, 107 Stat. 2115; Brief for Franklin Pierce Center for&#xD;
Intellectual Property as Amicus Curiae 14–16. One year later, Con-&#xD;
gress replaced this provision with the version of 17 U. S. C. §104A at&#xD;
issue here. See 3 M. Nimmer &amp; D. Nimmer, Copyright §9A.03, 9A.04,&#xD;
pp. 9A–17, 9A–22 (2011) (hereinafter Nimmer).&#xD;
  6 This tension between the United States and its new Berne counter&#xD;
                     Cite as: 565 U. S. ____ (2012)                     7&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
   Berne, however, did not provide a potent enforcement&#xD;
mechanism. The Convention contemplates dispute resolu-&#xD;
tion before the International Court of Justice. Art. 33(1).&#xD;
But it specifies no sanctions for noncompliance and allows&#xD;
parties, at any time, to declare themselves “not . . . bound”&#xD;
by the Convention’s dispute resolution provision. Art.&#xD;
33(2)–(3) 828 U. N. T. S., at 277. Unsurprisingly, no en-&#xD;
forcement actions were launched before 1994. D. Gervais,&#xD;
The TRIPS Agreement 213, and n. 134 (3d ed. 2008).&#xD;
Although “several Berne Union Members disagreed with&#xD;
[our] interpretation of Article 18,” the USTR told Con-&#xD;
gress, the Berne Convention did “not provide a meaningful&#xD;
dispute resolution process.” URAA Joint Hearing 137&#xD;
(statement of Shapiro). This shortcoming left Congress&#xD;
“free to adopt a minimalist approach and evade Article&#xD;
18.” Karp, Final Report, Berne Article 18 Study on Retro-&#xD;
active United States Copyright Protection for Berne and&#xD;
other Works, 20 Colum.-VLA J. L. &amp; Arts 157, 172 (1996).&#xD;
   The landscape changed in 1994. The Uruguay round of&#xD;
multilateral trade negotiations produced the World Trade&#xD;
Organization (WTO) and the Agreement on Trade-Related&#xD;
Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights (TRIPS).7 The&#xD;
United States joined both. TRIPS mandates, on pain of&#xD;
WTO enforcement, implementation of Berne’s first 21&#xD;
articles. TRIPS, Art. 9.1, 33 I. L. M. 1197, 1201 (requiring&#xD;
adherence to all but the “moral rights” provisions of Arti-&#xD;
cle 6bis). The WTO gave teeth to the Convention’s re-&#xD;
quirements: Noncompliance with a WTO ruling could&#xD;
&#xD;
——————&#xD;
parties calls into question the dissent’s assertion that, despite the 1988&#xD;
Act’s minimalist approach, “[t]he United States obtained the benefits of&#xD;
Berne for many years.” Post, at 22–23. During this six-year period,&#xD;
Congress had reason to doubt that U. S. authors enjoyed the full&#xD;
benefits of Berne membership.&#xD;
  7 Marrakesh Agreement Establishing the World Trade Organization,&#xD;
&#xD;
Apr. 15, 1994, 1867 U. N. T. S. 154.&#xD;
8                         GOLAN v. HOLDER&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
subject member countries to tariffs or cross-sector retalia-&#xD;
tion. See Gervais, supra, at 213; 7 W. Patry, Copyright&#xD;
§24:1, pp. 24–8 to 24–9 (2011). The specter of WTO en-&#xD;
forcement proceedings bolstered the credibility of our&#xD;
trading partners’ threats to challenge the United States&#xD;
for inadequate compliance with Article 18. See URAA&#xD;
Joint Hearing 137 (statement of Shapiro, USTR) (“It is&#xD;
likely that other WTO members would challenge the&#xD;
current U. S. implementation of Berne Article 18 under&#xD;
[WTO] procedures.”).8&#xD;
   Congress’ response to the Uruguay agreements put to&#xD;
rest any questions concerning U. S. compliance with Arti-&#xD;
cle 18. Section 514 of the URAA, 108 Stat. 4976 (codified&#xD;
at 17 U. S. C. §104A, 109(a)),9 extended copyright to works&#xD;
that garnered protection in their countries of origin,10 but&#xD;
——————&#xD;
   8 Proponents of prompt congressional action urged that avoiding a&#xD;
&#xD;
trade enforcement proceeding—potentially the WTO’s first—would be&#xD;
instrumental in preserving the United States’ “reputation as a world&#xD;
leader in the copyright field.” URAA Joint Hearing 241 (statement of&#xD;
Eric Smith, International Intellectual Property Alliance (IIPA)). In this&#xD;
regard, U. S. negotiators reported that widespread perception of U. S.&#xD;
noncompliance was undermining our leverage in copyright negotia-&#xD;
tions. Unimpeachable adherence to Berne, Congress was told, would&#xD;
help ensure enhanced foreign protection, and hence profitable dissemi-&#xD;
nation, for existing and future U. S. works. See id., at 120 (app. to&#xD;
statement of Lehman, Commerce Dept.) (“Clearly, providing for [retro-&#xD;
active] protection for existing works in our own law will improve our&#xD;
position in future negotiations.”); id., at 268 (statement of Berman,&#xD;
RIAA).&#xD;
   9 Title 17 U. S. C. §104A is reproduced in full in an appendix to this&#xD;
&#xD;
opinion.&#xD;
   10 Works from most, but not all, foreign countries are eligible for pro-&#xD;
&#xD;
tection under §514. The provision covers only works that have “at least&#xD;
one author or rightholder who was, at the time the work was created,&#xD;
a national or domiciliary of an eligible country.”            17 U. S. C.&#xD;
§104A(h)(6)(D). An “eligible country” includes any “nation, other than&#xD;
the United States, that—(A) becomes a WTO member country after the&#xD;
date of the enactment of the [URAA]; [or] (B) on such date of enactment&#xD;
                     Cite as: 565 U. S. ____ (2012)                     9&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
had no right to exclusivity in the United States for any&#xD;
of three reasons: lack of copyright relations between the&#xD;
country of origin and the United States at the time of&#xD;
publication; lack of subject-matter protection for sound&#xD;
recordings fixed before 1972; and failure to comply with&#xD;
U. S. statutory formalities (e.g., failure to provide notice of&#xD;
copyright status, or to register and renew a copyright).&#xD;
See §104A(h)(6)(B)–(C).11&#xD;
  Works that have fallen into the public domain after the&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
——————&#xD;
is, or after such date of enactment becomes, a nation adhering to&#xD;
the Berne Convention.” §104A(h)(3). As noted above, see supra,&#xD;
at 3, 164 countries adhere to the Berne Convention. World Intellec-&#xD;
tual Property Organization, Contracting Parties: Berne Convention,&#xD;
www.wipo.int/treaties (as visited Jan. 13, 2012, and in Clerk of Court’s&#xD;
case file).&#xD;
   11 From the first Copyright Act until late in the 20th century, Con-&#xD;
&#xD;
gress conditioned copyright protection on compliance with certain&#xD;
statutory formalities. The most notable required an author to register&#xD;
her work, renew that registration, and affix to published copies notice&#xD;
of copyrighted status. The formalities drew criticism as a trap for the&#xD;
unwary. See, e.g., 2 Nimmer §7.01[A], p. 7–8; Doyle, Cary, McCannon,&#xD;
&amp; Ringer, Notice of Copyright, Study No. 7, p. 46 (1957), reprinted in&#xD;
1 Studies on Copyright 229, 272 (1963).&#xD;
   In 1976, Congress eliminated the registration renewal requirement&#xD;
for future works. Copyright Act of 1976, §302, 408, 90 Stat. 2572, 2580.&#xD;
In 1988, it repealed the mandatory notice prerequisite. BCIA §7, 102&#xD;
Stat. 2857. And in 1992, Congress made renewal automatic for works&#xD;
still in their first term of protection. Copyright Amendments Act of&#xD;
1992, 106 Stat. 264–266. The Copyright Act retains, however, incen-&#xD;
tives for authors to register their works and provide notice of the works’&#xD;
copyrighted status. See, e.g., 17 U. S. C. §405(b) (precluding actual and&#xD;
statutory damages against “innocent infringers” of a work that lacked&#xD;
notice of copyrighted status); §411(a) (requiring registration of U. S.&#xD;
“work[s],” but not foreign works, before an owner may sue for infringe-&#xD;
ment). The revisions successively made accord with Berne Convention&#xD;
Article 5(2), which proscribes application of copyright formalities to&#xD;
foreign authors. Berne, however, affords domestic authors no escape&#xD;
from domestic formalities. See Art. 5(3) (protection within country of&#xD;
origin is a matter of domestic law).&#xD;
10                        GOLAN v. HOLDER&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
expiration of a full copyright term—either in the United&#xD;
States or the country of origin—receive no further protec-&#xD;
tion under §514. Ibid.12 Copyrights “restored”13 under&#xD;
URAA §514 “subsist for the remainder of the term of&#xD;
copyright that the work would have otherwise been grant-&#xD;
ed . . . if the work never entered the public domain.”&#xD;
§104A(a)(1)(B). Prospectively, restoration places foreign&#xD;
works on an equal footing with their U. S. counterparts;&#xD;
assuming a foreign and domestic author died the same&#xD;
day, their works will enter the public domain simultane-&#xD;
ously. See §302(a) (copyrights generally expire 70 years&#xD;
after the author’s death). Restored works, however, re-&#xD;
ceive no compensatory time for the period of exclusivity&#xD;
they would have enjoyed before §514’s enactment, had&#xD;
they been protected at the outset in the United States.&#xD;
Their total term, therefore, falls short of that available to&#xD;
similarly situated U. S. works.&#xD;
   The URAA’s disturbance of the public domain hardly&#xD;
escaped Congress’ attention. Section 514 imposed no&#xD;
liability for any use of foreign works occurring before&#xD;
restoration. In addition, anyone remained free to copy and&#xD;
use restored works for one year following §514’s enact-&#xD;
ment. See 17 U. S. C. §104A(h)(2)(A). Concerns about&#xD;
§514’s compatibility with the Fifth Amendment’s Takings&#xD;
&#xD;
——————&#xD;
   12 Title 17 U. S. C. §104A(h)(6)(B) defines a “restored work” to exclude&#xD;
&#xD;
“an original work of authorship” that is “in the public domain in its&#xD;
source country through expiration of [its] term of protection.” This&#xD;
provision tracks Berne’s denial of protection for any work that has&#xD;
“fallen into the public domain in the country of origin through the&#xD;
expiry of the term of protection.” Art. 18(1), 828 U. N. T. S., at 251.&#xD;
   13 Restoration is a misnomer insofar as it implies that all works&#xD;
&#xD;
protected under §104A previously enjoyed protection. Each work in&#xD;
the public domain because of lack of national eligibility or subject-&#xD;
matter protection, and many that failed to comply with formalities,&#xD;
never enjoyed U. S. copyright protection.           See, e.g., 3 Nimmer&#xD;
§9A.04[A][1][b][iii], at 9A–26, and n. 29.4.&#xD;
                     Cite as: 565 U. S. ____ (2012)                   11&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
Clause led Congress to include additional protections for&#xD;
“reliance parties”—those who had, before the URAA’s&#xD;
enactment, used or acquired a foreign work then in the&#xD;
public domain. See §104A(h)(3)–(4).14 Reliance parties&#xD;
may continue to exploit a restored work until the owner of&#xD;
the restored copyright gives notice of intent to enforce—&#xD;
either by filing with the U. S. Copyright Office within two&#xD;
years of restoration, or by actually notifying the reliance&#xD;
party. §104A(c), (d)(2)(A)(i), and (B)(i). After that, reli-&#xD;
ance parties may continue to exploit existing copies for a&#xD;
grace period of one year. §104A(d)(2)(A)(ii), and (B)(ii).&#xD;
Finally, anyone who, before the URAA’s enactment, creat-&#xD;
ed a “derivative work” based on a restored work may&#xD;
indefinitely exploit the derivation upon payment to the&#xD;
copyright holder of “reasonable compensation,” to be set by&#xD;
a district judge if the parties cannot agree. §104A(d)(3).&#xD;
                             B&#xD;
  In 2001, petitioners filed this lawsuit challenging §514.&#xD;
They maintain that Congress, when it passed the URAA,&#xD;
exceeded its authority under the Copyright Clause and&#xD;
transgressed First Amendment limitations.15 The District&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  14 A reliance party must have used the work in a manner that would&#xD;
&#xD;
constitute infringement had a valid copyright been in effect. See&#xD;
§104A(h)(4)(A). After restoration, the reliance party is limited to her&#xD;
previous uses. A performer of a restored work, for example, cannot,&#xD;
post-restoration, venture to sell copies of the script. See 3 Nimmer&#xD;
§9A.04[C][1][a], at 9A–45 to 9A–46.&#xD;
  15 Petitioners’ complaint also challenged the constitutionality of the&#xD;
&#xD;
Copyright Term Extension Act, 112 Stat. 2827, which added 20 years to&#xD;
the duration of existing and future copyrights. After this Court rejected&#xD;
a similar challenge in Eldred v. Ashcroft, 537 U. S. 186 (2003), the&#xD;
District Court dismissed this portion of petitioners’ suit on the plead-&#xD;
ings, Golan v. Ashcroft, &lt;/pre&gt;&lt;span class="citation"&gt;&lt;a href="#"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;310&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;F. Supp. 2d&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;1215&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;pre class="inline"&gt; (D. Colo. 2004). The&#xD;
Tenth Circuit affirmed, Golan v. Gonzales, 501 F. 3d 1179 (2007), and&#xD;
petitioners do not attempt to revive that claim in this Court, Pet. for&#xD;
Cert. 7, n. 2. Neither have petitioners challenged the District Court’s&#xD;
12                      GOLAN v. HOLDER&#xD;
&#xD;
                        Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
Court granted the Attorney General’s motion for summary&#xD;
judgment. Golan v. Gonzales, No. Civ. 01–B–1854, 2005&#xD;
WL 914754 (D. Colo., Apr. 20, 2005). In rejecting petition-&#xD;
ers’ Copyright Clause argument, the court stated that&#xD;
Congress “has historically demonstrated little compunc-&#xD;
tion about removing copyrightable materials from the&#xD;
public domain.” Id., at *14. The court next declined to&#xD;
part from “the settled rule that private censorship via&#xD;
copyright enforcement does not implicate First Amend-&#xD;
ment concerns.” Id., at *17.&#xD;
   The Court of Appeals for the Tenth Circuit affirmed in&#xD;
part. Golan v. Gonzales, 501 F. 3d 1179 (2007). The&#xD;
public domain, it agreed, was not a “threshold that Con-&#xD;
gress” was powerless to “traverse in both directions.” Id.,&#xD;
at 1187 (internal quotations marks omitted). But §514, as&#xD;
the Court of Appeals read our decision in Eldred v. Ash-&#xD;
croft, 537 U. S. 186 (2003), required further First Amend-&#xD;
ment inspection, 501 F. 3d, at 1187. The measure “ ‘al-&#xD;
tered the traditional contours of copyright protection,’ ” the&#xD;
court said—specifically, the “bedrock principle” that once&#xD;
works enter the public domain, they do not leave. Ibid.&#xD;
(quoting Eldred, 537 U. S., at 221). The case was remand-&#xD;
ed with an instruction to the District Court to address the&#xD;
First Amendment claim in light of the Tenth Circuit’s&#xD;
opinion.&#xD;
   On remand, the District Court’s starting premise was&#xD;
uncontested: Section 514 does not regulate speech on the&#xD;
basis of its content; therefore the law would be upheld if&#xD;
“narrowly tailored to serve a significant government inter-&#xD;
est.” &lt;/pre&gt;&lt;span class="citation"&gt;&lt;a href="#"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;611&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;F. Supp. 2d&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;1165&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;pre class="inline"&gt;, 1170–1171 (Colo. 2009) (quot-&#xD;
ing Ward v. Rock Against Racism, 491 U. S. 781, 791&#xD;
(1989)). Summary judgment was due petitioners, the&#xD;
&#xD;
—————— &#xD;
&#xD;
entry of summary judgment for the Government on the claim that §514&#xD;
&#xD;
violates the substantive component of the Due Process Clause. &#xD;
&#xD;
                  Cite as: 565 U. S. ____ (2012)           13&#xD;
&#xD;
                      Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
court concluded, because §514’s constriction of the public&#xD;
domain was not justified by any of the asserted federal&#xD;
interests: compliance with Berne, securing greater protec-&#xD;
tion for U. S. authors abroad, or remediation of the inequi-&#xD;
table treatment suffered by foreign authors whose works&#xD;
lacked protection in the United States. 611 F. Supp. 2d, at&#xD;
1172–1177.&#xD;
   The Tenth Circuit reversed. Deferring to Congress’&#xD;
predictive judgments in matters relating to foreign affairs,&#xD;
the appellate court held that §514 survived First Amend-&#xD;
ment scrutiny. Specifically, the court determined that the&#xD;
law was narrowly tailored to fit the important government&#xD;
aim of protecting U. S. copyright holders’ interests abroad.&#xD;
609 F. 3d 1076 (2010).&#xD;
   We granted certiorari to consider petitioners’ challenge&#xD;
to §514 under both the Copyright Clause and the First&#xD;
Amendment, 562 U. S. ___ (2011), and now affirm.&#xD;
                               II&#xD;
   We first address petitioners’ argument that Congress&#xD;
lacked authority, under the Copyright Clause, to enact&#xD;
§514. The Constitution states that “Congress shall have&#xD;
Power . . . [t]o promote the Progress of Science . . . by&#xD;
securing for limited Times to Authors . . . the exclusive&#xD;
Right to their . . . Writings.” Art. I, §8, cl. 8. Petitioners&#xD;
find in this grant of authority an impenetrable barrier to&#xD;
the extension of copyright protection to authors whose&#xD;
writings, for whatever reason, are in the public domain.&#xD;
We see no such barrier in the text of the Copyright Clause,&#xD;
historical practice, or our precedents.&#xD;
                             A&#xD;
  The text of the Copyright Clause does not exclude appli-&#xD;
cation of copyright protection to works in the public do-&#xD;
main. Symposium, Congressional Power and Limitations&#xD;
Inherent in the Copyright Clause, 30 Colum. J. L. &amp; Arts&#xD;
14                    GOLAN v. HOLDER&#xD;
&#xD;
                      Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
259, 266 (2007). Petitioners’ contrary argument relies&#xD;
primarily on the Constitution’s confinement of a copy-&#xD;
right’s lifespan to a “limited Tim[e].” “Removing works&#xD;
from the public domain,” they contend, “violates the ‘lim-&#xD;
ited [t]imes’ restriction by turning a fixed and predictable&#xD;
period into one that can be reset or resurrected at any&#xD;
time, even after it expires.” Brief for Petitioners 22.&#xD;
   Our decision in Eldred is largely dispositive of petition-&#xD;
ers’ limited-time argument. There we addressed the&#xD;
question whether Congress violated the Copyright Clause&#xD;
when it extended, by 20 years, the terms of existing copy-&#xD;
rights. 537 U. S., at 192–193 (upholding Copyright Term&#xD;
Extension Act (CTEA)). Ruling that Congress acted with-&#xD;
in constitutional bounds, we declined to infer from the text&#xD;
of the Copyright Clause “the command that a time pre-&#xD;
scription, once set, becomes forever ‘fixed’ or ‘inalterable.’ ”&#xD;
Id., at 199. “The word ‘limited,’ ” we observed, “does not&#xD;
convey a meaning so constricted.” Ibid. Rather, the term&#xD;
is best understood to mean “confine[d] within certain&#xD;
bounds,” “restrain[ed],” or “circumscribed.” Ibid. (internal&#xD;
quotation marks omitted). The construction petitioners&#xD;
tender closely resembles the definition rejected in Eldred&#xD;
and is similarly infirm.&#xD;
   The terms afforded works restored by §514 are no less&#xD;
“limited” than those the CTEA lengthened. In light of&#xD;
Eldred, petitioners do not here contend that the term&#xD;
Congress has granted U. S. authors—their lifetimes, plus&#xD;
70 years—is unlimited. See 17 U. S. C. §302(a). Nor do&#xD;
petitioners explain why terms of the same duration, as&#xD;
applied to foreign works, are not equally “circumscribed”&#xD;
and “confined.” See Eldred, 537 U. S., at 199. Indeed, as&#xD;
earlier noted, see supra, at 2, 10, the copyrights of restored&#xD;
foreign works typically last for fewer years than those of&#xD;
their domestic counterparts.&#xD;
   The difference, petitioners say, is that the limited time&#xD;
had already passed for works in the public domain. What&#xD;
                   Cite as: 565 U. S. ____ (2012)               15&#xD;
&#xD;
                       Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
was that limited term for foreign works once excluded&#xD;
from U. S. copyright protection? Exactly “zero,” petition-&#xD;
ers respond. Brief for Petitioners 22 (works in question&#xD;
“received a specific term of protection . . . sometimes ex-&#xD;
pressly set to zero”; “at the end of that period,” they “en-&#xD;
tered the public domain”); Tr. of Oral Arg. 52 (by “refusing&#xD;
to provide any protection for a work,” Congress “set[s] the&#xD;
term at zero,” and thereby “tell[s] us when the end has&#xD;
come”). We find scant sense in this argument, for surely a&#xD;
“limited time” of exclusivity must begin before it may&#xD;
end.16&#xD;
   Carried to its logical conclusion, petitioners persist, the&#xD;
Government’s position would allow Congress to institute a&#xD;
second “limited” term after the first expires, a third after&#xD;
that, and so on. Thus, as long as Congress legislated in&#xD;
installments, perpetual copyright terms would be achieva-&#xD;
ble. As in Eldred, the hypothetical legislative misbehavior&#xD;
petitioners posit is far afield from the case before us. See&#xD;
537 U. S., at 198–200, 209–210. In aligning the United&#xD;
States with other nations bound by the Berne Convention,&#xD;
and thereby according equitable treatment to once dis-&#xD;
favored foreign authors, Congress can hardly be charged&#xD;
with a design to move stealthily toward a regime of per-&#xD;
petual copyrights.&#xD;
                             B&#xD;
  Historical practice corroborates our reading of the Copy-&#xD;
right Clause to permit full U. S. compliance with Berne.&#xD;
Undoubtedly, federal copyright legislation generally has&#xD;
not affected works in the public domain. Section 514’s&#xD;
disturbance of that domain, petitioners argue, distin-&#xD;
&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  16 Cf.3 Nimmer §9A.02[A][2], at 9A–11, n. 28 (“[I]t stretches the&#xD;
language of the Berne Convention past the breaking point to posit&#xD;
that following ‘expiry of the zero term’ the . . . work need not be&#xD;
resurrected.”).&#xD;
16                       GOLAN v. HOLDER&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
guishes their suit from Eldred’s. In adopting the CTEA,&#xD;
petitioners note, Congress acted in accord with “an unbro-&#xD;
ken congressional practice” of granting pre-expiration&#xD;
term extensions, 537 U. S., at 200. No comparable prac-&#xD;
tice, they maintain, supports §514.&#xD;
   On occasion, however, Congress has seen fit to protect&#xD;
works once freely available. Notably, the Copyright Act of&#xD;
1790 granted protection to many works previously in the&#xD;
public domain. Act of May 31, 1790 (1790 Act), §1, 1 Stat.&#xD;
124 (covering “any map, chart, book, or books already&#xD;
printed within these United States”). Before the Act&#xD;
launched a uniform national system, three States provided&#xD;
no statutory copyright protection at all.17 Of those that&#xD;
did afford some protection, seven failed to protect maps;18&#xD;
eight did not cover previously published books;19 and all&#xD;
ten denied protection to works that failed to comply with&#xD;
formalities.20 The First Congress, it thus appears, did not&#xD;
view the public domain as inviolate. As we have recog-&#xD;
nized, the “construction placed upon the Constitution by&#xD;
[the drafters of] the first [copyright] act of 1790 and the&#xD;
act of 1802 . . . men who were contemporary with [the&#xD;
Constitution’s] formation, many of whom were members of&#xD;
the convention which framed it, is of itself entitled to very&#xD;
great weight.” Burrow-Giles Lithographic Co. v. Sarony,&#xD;
&#xD;
——————&#xD;
   17 See B. Bugbee, Genesis of American Patent and Copyright Law&#xD;
&#xD;
123–124 (1967) (hereinafter Bugbee) (Delaware, Maryland, and&#xD;
Pennsylvania).&#xD;
   18 See 1783 Mass. Acts p. 236; 1783 N. J. Laws p. 47; 1783 N. H. Laws&#xD;
&#xD;
p. 521; 1783 R. I. Laws pp. 6–7; 1784 S. C. Acts p. 49; 1785 Va. Acts ch.&#xD;
VI; 1786 N. Y. Laws p. 298.&#xD;
   19 1783 Conn. Pub. Acts no. 617; 1783 N. J. Laws p. 47; 1785 N. C.&#xD;
&#xD;
Laws p. 563; 1786 Ga. Laws p. 323. In four States, copyright enforce-&#xD;
ment was restricted to works “not yet printed” or “hereinafter pub-&#xD;
lished.” 1783 Mass. Acts p. 236; 1783 N. H. Laws p. 521; 1783 R. I.&#xD;
Laws pp. 6–7; 1784 S. C. Acts p. 49.&#xD;
   20 See Bugbee 109–123.&#xD;
                     Cite as: 565 U. S. ____ (2012)                  17&#xD;
&#xD;
                         Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
111 U. S. 53, 57 (1884).21&#xD;
   Subsequent actions confirm that Congress has not un-&#xD;
derstood the Copyright Clause to preclude protection for&#xD;
existing works. Several private bills restored the copy-&#xD;
rights of works that previously had been in the public&#xD;
domain. See Act of Feb. 19, 1849 (Corson Act), ch. 57, 9&#xD;
Stat. 763; Act of June 23, 1874 (Helmuth Act), ch. 534, 18&#xD;
Stat. 618; Act of Feb. 17, 1898 (Jones Act), ch. 29, 30 Stat.&#xD;
1396. These bills were unchallenged in court.&#xD;
   Analogous patent statutes, however, were upheld in&#xD;
litigation.22 In 1808, Congress passed a private bill restor-&#xD;
ing patent protection to Oliver Evans’ flour mill. When&#xD;
Evans sued for infringement, first Chief Justice Marshall&#xD;
in the Circuit Court, Evans v. Jordan, 8 F. Cas. 872 (No.&#xD;
4,564) (Va. 1813), and then Justice Bushrod Washington&#xD;
for this Court, Evans v. Jordan, 9 Cranch 199 (1815),&#xD;
upheld the restored patent’s validity. After the patent’s&#xD;
expiration, the Court said, “a general right to use [Evans’]&#xD;
discovery was not so vested in the public” as to allow the&#xD;
defendant to continue using the machinery, which he had&#xD;
&#xD;
——————&#xD;
   21 The parties debate the extent to which the First Congress removed&#xD;
&#xD;
works from the public domain. We have held, however, that at least&#xD;
some works protected by the 1790 Act previously lacked protection. In&#xD;
Wheaton v. Peters, 8 Pet. 591 (1834), the Court ruled that before enact-&#xD;
ment of the 1790 Act, common-law copyright protection expired upon&#xD;
first publication. Id., at 657, 663. Thus published works covered by the&#xD;
1790 Act previously would have been in the public domain unless&#xD;
protected by state statute. Had the founding generation perceived the&#xD;
constitutional boundary petitioners advance today, the First Congress&#xD;
could have designed a prospective scheme that left the public domain&#xD;
undisturbed. Accord Luck’s Music Library, Inc. v. Gonzales, 407 F. 3d&#xD;
1262, 1265 (CADC 2005) (Section 514 does not offend the Copyright&#xD;
Clause because, inter alia, “evidence from the First Congress,” as&#xD;
confirmed by Wheaton, “points toward constitutionality.”).&#xD;
   22 Here, as in Eldred, “[b]ecause the Clause empowering Congress to&#xD;
&#xD;
confer copyrights also authorizes patents, congressional practice with&#xD;
respect to patents informs our inquiry.” 537 U. S., at 201.&#xD;
18                       GOLAN v. HOLDER&#xD;
&#xD;
                         Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
constructed between the patent’s expiration and the bill’s&#xD;
passage. Id., at 202. See also Blanchard v. Sprague, 3&#xD;
F. Cas. 648, 650 (No. 1,518) (CC Mass. 1839) (Story, J.) (“I&#xD;
never have entertained any doubt of the constitutional&#xD;
authority of congress” to “give a patent for an invention,&#xD;
which . . . was in public use and enjoyed by the community&#xD;
at the time of the passage of the act.”).&#xD;
   This Court again upheld Congress’ restoration of an&#xD;
invention to protected status in McClurg v. Kingsland, 1&#xD;
How. 202 (1843). There we enforced an 1839 amendment&#xD;
that recognized a patent on an invention despite its prior&#xD;
use by the inventor’s employer. Absent such dispensation,&#xD;
the employer’s use would have rendered the invention&#xD;
unpatentable, and therefore open to exploitation without&#xD;
the inventor’s leave. Id., at 206–209.&#xD;
   Congress has also passed generally applicable legisla-&#xD;
tion granting patents and copyrights to inventions and&#xD;
works that had lost protection. An 1832 statute author-&#xD;
ized a new patent for any inventor whose failure, “by&#xD;
inadvertence, accident, or mistake,” to comply with statu-&#xD;
tory formalities rendered the original patent “invalid or&#xD;
inoperative.” Act of July 3, §3, 4 Stat. 559. An 1893&#xD;
measure similarly allowed authors who had not timely&#xD;
deposited their work to receive “all the rights and privileg-&#xD;
es” the Copyright Act affords, if they made the required&#xD;
deposit by March 1, 1893. Act of Mar. 3, ch. 215, 27 Stat.&#xD;
743.23 And in 1919 and 1941, Congress authorized the&#xD;
President to issue proclamations granting protection to&#xD;
foreign works that had fallen into the public domain dur-&#xD;
ing World Wars I and II. See Act of Dec. 18, 1919, ch. 11,&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  23 Section 514 is in line with these measures; like them, it accords&#xD;
protection to works that had lapsed into the public domain because of&#xD;
failure to comply with U. S. statutory formalities. See supra, at 9, and&#xD;
n. 11.&#xD;
                      Cite as: 565 U. S. ____ (2012)                    19&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
41 Stat. 368; Act of Sept. 25, 1941, ch. 421, 55 Stat. 732.24&#xD;
   Pointing to dictum in Graham v. John Deere Co. of&#xD;
Kansas City, 383 U. S. 1 (1966), petitioners would have us&#xD;
look past this history. In Graham, we stated that “Con-&#xD;
gress may not authorize the issuance of patents whose&#xD;
effects are to remove existent knowledge from the public&#xD;
domain, or to restrict free access to materials already&#xD;
available.” Id., at 6; post, at 15. But as we explained in&#xD;
Eldred, this passage did not speak to the constitutional&#xD;
limits on Congress’ copyright and patent authority. Ra-&#xD;
ther, it “addressed an invention’s very eligibility for patent&#xD;
protection.” 537 U. S., at 202, n. 7.&#xD;
   Installing a federal copyright system and ameliorating&#xD;
the interruptions of global war, it is true, presented Con-&#xD;
gress with extraordinary situations. Yet the TRIPS ac-&#xD;
cord, leading the United States to comply in full measure&#xD;
with Berne, was also a signal event. See supra, at 7–8; cf.&#xD;
Eldred, 537 U. S., at 259, 264–265 (BREYER, J., dissenting)&#xD;
(acknowledging importance of international uniformity&#xD;
advanced by U. S. efforts to conform to the Berne Conven-&#xD;
tion). Given the authority we hold Congress has, we will&#xD;
not second-guess the political choice Congress made be-&#xD;
tween leaving the public domain untouched and embrac-&#xD;
ing Berne unstintingly. Cf. id., at 212–213.&#xD;
&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  24 Legislation of this order, petitioners argue, is best understood as an&#xD;
&#xD;
exercise of Congress’ power to remedy excusable neglect. Even so, the&#xD;
remedy sheltered creations that, absent congressional action, would&#xD;
have been open to free exploitation. Such action, according to petition-&#xD;
ers’ dominant argument, see supra, at 13–14, is ever and always&#xD;
impermissible. Accord Luck’s Music Library, 407 F. 3d, at 1265–1266&#xD;
(“Plaintiffs urge that [the 1790 Act and the wartime legislation] simply&#xD;
extended the time limits for filing and [did] not purport to modify the&#xD;
prohibition on removing works from the public domain. But to the&#xD;
extent that potential copyright holders failed to satisfy procedural&#xD;
requirements, such works”—like those protected by §514—“would&#xD;
necessarily have already entered the public domain . . . .”).&#xD;
20                       GOLAN v. HOLDER&#xD;
&#xD;
                         Opinion of the Court &#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
                              C&#xD;
&#xD;
   Petitioners’ ultimate argument as to the Copyright and&#xD;
Patent Clause concerns its initial words. Congress is&#xD;
empowered to “promote the Progress of Science and useful&#xD;
Arts” by enacting systems of copyright and patent protec-&#xD;
tion. U. S. Const., Art. I, §8, cl. 8. Perhaps counterintui-&#xD;
tively for the contemporary reader, Congress’ copyright&#xD;
authority is tied to the progress of science; its patent&#xD;
authority, to the progress of the useful arts. See Graham,&#xD;
383 U. S., at 5, and n. 1; Evans, 8 F. Cas., at 873&#xD;
(Marshall, J.).&#xD;
   The “Progress of Science,” petitioners acknowledge,&#xD;
refers broadly to “the creation and spread of knowledge&#xD;
and learning.” Brief for Petitioners 21; accord post, at 1.&#xD;
They nevertheless argue that federal legislation cannot&#xD;
serve the Clause’s aim unless the legislation “spur[s] the&#xD;
creation of . . . new works.” Brief for Petitioners 24; accord&#xD;
post, at 1–2, 8, 17. Because §514 deals solely with works&#xD;
already created, petitioners urge, it “provides no plausible&#xD;
incentive to create new works” and is therefore invalid.&#xD;
Reply Brief 4.25&#xD;
   The creation of at least one new work, however, is not&#xD;
the sole way Congress may promote knowledge and learn-&#xD;
ing. In Eldred, we rejected an argument nearly identical&#xD;
to the one petitioners rehearse. The Eldred petitioners&#xD;
urged that the “CTEA’s extension of existing copyrights&#xD;
categorically fails to ‘promote the Progress of Science,’ . . .&#xD;
because it does not stimulate the creation of new works.”&#xD;
537 U. S., at 211–212. In response to this argument, we&#xD;
&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  25 But see Brief for Motion Picture Association of America as Amicus&#xD;
&#xD;
Curiae 27 (observing that income from existing works can finance the&#xD;
creation and publication of new works); Eldred, 537 U. S., at 208, n. 15&#xD;
(noting that Noah Webster “supported his entire family from the&#xD;
earnings on his speller and grammar during the twenty years he took&#xD;
to complete his dictionary” (internal quotation marks omitted)).&#xD;
                    Cite as: 565 U. S. ____ (2012)                 21&#xD;
&#xD;
                        Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
held that the Copyright Clause does not demand that each&#xD;
copyright provision, examined discretely, operate to induce&#xD;
new works. Rather, we explained, the Clause “empowers&#xD;
Congress to determine the intellectual property regimes&#xD;
that, overall, in that body’s judgment, will serve the ends&#xD;
of the Clause.” Id., at 222. And those permissible ends,&#xD;
we held, extended beyond the creation of new works. See&#xD;
id., at 205–206 (rejecting the notion that “ ‘the only way to&#xD;
promote the progress of science [is] to provide incentives&#xD;
to create new works’ ” (quoting Perlmutter, Participation in&#xD;
the International Copyright System as a Means to Pro-&#xD;
mote the Progress of Science and Useful Arts, 36 Loyola&#xD;
(LA) L. Rev. 323, 332 (2002))).26&#xD;
   Even were we writing on a clean slate, petitioners’&#xD;
argument would be unavailing. Nothing in the text of the&#xD;
Copyright Clause confines the “Progress of Science” exclu-&#xD;
sively to “incentives for creation.” Id., at 324, n. 5 (inter-&#xD;
nal quotation marks omitted). Evidence from the found-&#xD;
ing, moreover, suggests that inducing dissemination—as&#xD;
opposed to creation—was viewed as an appropriate means&#xD;
to promote science. See Nachbar, Constructing Copy-&#xD;
right’s Mythology, 6 Green Bag 2d 37, 44 (2002) (“The&#xD;
scope of copyright protection existing at the time of the&#xD;
framing,” trained as it was on “publication, not creation,”&#xD;
“is inconsistent with claims that copyright must promote&#xD;
creative activity in order to be valid.” (internal quotation&#xD;
marks omitted)). Until 1976, in fact, Congress made&#xD;
“federal copyright contingent on publication[,] [thereby]&#xD;
&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  26 The dissent also suggests, more tentatively, that at least where&#xD;
&#xD;
copyright legislation extends protection to works previously in the&#xD;
public domain, Congress must counterbalance that restriction with new&#xD;
incentives to create. Post, at 8. Even assuming the public domain were&#xD;
a category of constitutional significance, contra supra, at 13–19, we&#xD;
would not understand “the Progress of Science” to have this contingent&#xD;
meaning.&#xD;
22                       GOLAN v. HOLDER&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
providing incentives not primarily for creation,” but for&#xD;
dissemination. Perlmutter, supra, at 324, n. 5. Our deci-&#xD;
sions correspondingly recognize that “copyright supplies&#xD;
the economic incentive to create and disseminate ideas.”&#xD;
Harper &amp; Row, Publishers, Inc. v. Nation Enterprises, 471&#xD;
U. S. 539, 558 (1985) (emphasis added). See also Eldred,&#xD;
537 U. S., at 206.27&#xD;
   Considered against this backdrop, §514 falls comfortably&#xD;
within Congress’ authority under the Copyright Clause.&#xD;
Congress rationally could have concluded that adherence&#xD;
to Berne “promotes the diffusion of knowledge,” Brief for&#xD;
Petitioners 4. A well-functioning international copyright&#xD;
system would likely encourage the dissemination of exist-&#xD;
ing and future works. See URAA Joint Hearing 189&#xD;
(statement of Professor Perlmutter). Full compliance with&#xD;
Berne, Congress had reason to believe, would expand the&#xD;
foreign markets available to U. S. authors and invigorate&#xD;
protection against piracy of U. S. works abroad, S. Rep.&#xD;
No. 103–412, pp. 224, 225 (1994); URAA Joint Hearing&#xD;
291 (statement of Berman, RIAA); id., at 244, 247 (state-&#xD;
ment of Smith, IIPA), thereby benefitting copyright-&#xD;
intensive industries stateside and inducing greater&#xD;
investment in the creative process.&#xD;
   The provision of incentives for the creation of new works&#xD;
is surely an essential means to advance the spread of&#xD;
knowledge and learning. We hold, however, that it is not&#xD;
the sole means Congress may use “[t]o promote the Pro-&#xD;
gress of Science.” See Perlmutter, supra, at 332 (United&#xD;
States would “lose all flexibility” were the provision of&#xD;
incentives to create the exclusive way to promote the&#xD;
&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  27 That the same economic incentives might also induce the dissemi-&#xD;
&#xD;
nation of futons, fruit, or Bibles, see post, at 20, is no answer to this&#xD;
evidence that legislation furthering the dissemination of literary&#xD;
property has long been thought a legitimate way to “promote the&#xD;
Progress of Science.”&#xD;
                     Cite as: 565 U. S. ____ (2012)                    23&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
progress of science).28 Congress determined that exem-&#xD;
plary adherence to Berne would serve the objectives of the&#xD;
Copyright Clause. We have no warrant to reject the ra-&#xD;
tional judgment Congress made.&#xD;
                             III&#xD;
&#xD;
                              A&#xD;
&#xD;
   We next explain why the First Amendment does not&#xD;
inhibit the restoration authorized by §514. To do so, we&#xD;
first recapitulate the relevant part of our pathmarking&#xD;
decision in Eldred. The petitioners in Eldred, like those&#xD;
here, argued that Congress had violated not only the&#xD;
“limited Times” prescription of the Copyright Clause. In&#xD;
addition, and independently, the Eldred petitioners&#xD;
charged, Congress had offended the First Amendment’s&#xD;
freedom of expression guarantee. The CTEA’s 20-year&#xD;
enlargement of a copyright’s duration, we held in Eldred,&#xD;
offended neither provision.&#xD;
   Concerning the First Amendment, we recognized that&#xD;
some restriction on expression is the inherent and in-&#xD;
tended effect of every grant of copyright. Noting that the&#xD;
“Copyright Clause and the First Amendment were adopted&#xD;
close in time,” 537 U. S., at 219, we observed that the&#xD;
Framers regarded copyright protection not simply as a&#xD;
limit on the manner in which expressive works may be&#xD;
used. They also saw copyright as an “engine of free ex-&#xD;
pression[:] By establishing a marketable right to the use of&#xD;
&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  28 The dissent suggests that the “utilitarian view of copyrigh[t]” em-&#xD;
&#xD;
braced by Jefferson, Madison, and our case law sets us apart from&#xD;
continental Europe and inhibits us from harmonizing our copyright&#xD;
laws with those of countries in the civil-law tradition. See post, at 5–6,&#xD;
22. For persuasive refutation of that suggestion, see Austin, Does the&#xD;
Copyright Clause Mandate Isolationism? 26 Colum. J. L. &amp; Arts 17, 59&#xD;
(2002) (cautioning against “an isolationist reading of the Copyright&#xD;
Clause that is in tension with . . . America’s international copyright&#xD;
relations over the last hundred or so years”).&#xD;
24                       GOLAN v. HOLDER&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
one’s expression, copyright supplies the economic incentive&#xD;
to create and disseminate ideas.” Ibid. (quoting Harper &amp;&#xD;
Row, 471 U. S., at 558 (internal quotation marks omit-&#xD;
ted)); see id., at 546 (“rights conferred by copyright are&#xD;
designed to assure contributors to the store of knowledge a&#xD;
fair return for their labors”).&#xD;
   We then described the “traditional contours” of copy-&#xD;
right protection, i.e., the “idea/expression dichotomy” and&#xD;
the “fair use” defense.29 Both are recognized in our juris-&#xD;
prudence as “built-in First Amendment accommodations.”&#xD;
Eldred, 537 U. S., at 219; see Harper &amp; Row, 471 U. S., at&#xD;
560 (First Amendment protections are “embodied in the&#xD;
Copyright Act’s distinction between copyrightable expres-&#xD;
sion and uncopyrightable facts and ideas,” and in the&#xD;
“latitude for scholarship and comment” safeguarded by the&#xD;
fair use defense).&#xD;
   The idea/expression dichotomy is codified at 17 U. S. C.&#xD;
§102(b): “In no case does copyright protec[t] . . . any idea,&#xD;
procedure, process, system, method of operation, concept,&#xD;
principle, or discovery . . . described, explained, illustrat-&#xD;
ed, or embodied in [the copyrighted] work.” “Due to this&#xD;
[idea/expression] distinction, every idea, theory, and fact&#xD;
in a copyrighted work becomes instantly available for&#xD;
public exploitation at the moment of publication”; the&#xD;
author’s expression alone gains copyright protection.&#xD;
Eldred, 537 U. S., at 219; see Harper &amp; Row, 471 U. S., at&#xD;
556 (“idea/expression dichotomy strike[s] a definitional&#xD;
balance between the First Amendment and the Copyright&#xD;
Act by permitting free communication of facts while still&#xD;
protecting an author’s expression” (internal quotation&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  29 On the initial appeal in this case, the Tenth Circuit gave an uncon-&#xD;
fined reading to our reference in Eldred to “traditional contours of&#xD;
copyright.” 501 F. 3d, at 1187–1196. That reading was incorrect, as we&#xD;
here clarify.&#xD;
                     Cite as: 565 U. S. ____ (2012)                   25&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
marks omitted)).&#xD;
   The second “traditional contour,” the fair use defense, is&#xD;
codified at 17 U. S. C. §107: “[T]he fair use of a copyright-&#xD;
ed work, including such use by reproduction in copies . . . ,&#xD;
for purposes such as criticism, comment, news reporting,&#xD;
teaching (including multiple copies for classroom use),&#xD;
scholarship, or research, is not an infringement of copy-&#xD;
right.” This limitation on exclusivity “allows the public to&#xD;
use not only facts and ideas contained in a copyrighted&#xD;
work, but also [the author’s] expression itself in certain&#xD;
circumstances.” Eldred, 537 U. S., at 219; see id., at 220&#xD;
(“fair use defense affords considerable latitude for scholar-&#xD;
ship and comment, . . . even for parody” (internal quota-&#xD;
tion marks omitted)).&#xD;
   Given the “speech-protective purposes and safeguards”&#xD;
embraced by copyright law, see id., at 219, we concluded&#xD;
in Eldred that there was no call for the heightened review&#xD;
petitioners sought in that case.30 We reach the same&#xD;
conclusion here.31 Section 514 leaves undisturbed the&#xD;
“idea/expression” distinction and the “fair use” defense.&#xD;
Moreover, Congress adopted measures to ease the transi-&#xD;
tion from a national scheme to an international copyright&#xD;
regime: It deferred the date from which enforcement runs,&#xD;
and it cushioned the impact of restoration on “reliance&#xD;
parties” who exploited foreign works denied protection&#xD;
before §514 took effect. See supra, at 10–11 (describing 17&#xD;
U. S. C. §104A(c), (d), and (h)). See also Eldred, 537 U. S.,&#xD;
at 220 (describing supplemental allowances and exemp-&#xD;
&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  30 See Eldred, 537 U. S., at 221 (“Protection of [an author’s original&#xD;
&#xD;
expression from unrestricted exploitation] does not raise the free speech&#xD;
concerns present when the government compels or burdens the com-&#xD;
munication of particular facts or ideas.”).&#xD;
  31Focusing narrowly on the specific problem of orphan works,&#xD;
&#xD;
the dissent overlooks these principal protections against “the&#xD;
dissemination-restricting harms of copyright.” Post, at 14.&#xD;
26                   GOLAN v. HOLDER&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
tions available to certain users to mitigate the CTEA’s&#xD;
impact).&#xD;
                              B&#xD;
  Petitioners attempt to distinguish their challenge from&#xD;
the one turned away in Eldred. First Amendment inter-&#xD;
ests of a higher order are at stake here, petitioners say,&#xD;
because they—unlike their counterparts in Eldred—&#xD;
enjoyed “vested rights” in works that had already entered&#xD;
the public domain. The limited rights they retain under&#xD;
copyright law’s “built-in safeguards” are, in their view, no&#xD;
substitute for the unlimited use they enjoyed before §514’s&#xD;
enactment. Nor, petitioners urge, does §514’s “unprece-&#xD;
dented” foray into the public domain possess the historical&#xD;
pedigree that supported the term extension at issue in&#xD;
Eldred. Brief for Petitioners 42–43.&#xD;
  However spun, these contentions depend on an argu-&#xD;
ment we considered and rejected above, namely, that the&#xD;
Constitution renders the public domain largely untouch-&#xD;
able by Congress. Petitioners here attempt to achieve&#xD;
under the banner of the First Amendment what they could&#xD;
not win under the Copyright Clause: On their view of the&#xD;
Copyright Clause, the public domain is inviolable; as they&#xD;
read the First Amendment, the public domain is policed&#xD;
through heightened judicial scrutiny of Congress’ means&#xD;
and ends. As we have already shown, see supra, at 13–19,&#xD;
the text of the Copyright Clause and the historical record&#xD;
scarcely establish that “once a work enters the public&#xD;
domain,” Congress cannot permit anyone—“not even the&#xD;
creator—[to] copyright it,” 501 F. 3d, at 1184. And noth-&#xD;
ing in the historical record, congressional practice, or our&#xD;
own jurisprudence warrants exceptional First Amendment&#xD;
solicitude for copyrighted works that were once in the&#xD;
                      Cite as: 565 U. S. ____ (2012)                  27&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
public domain.32 Neither this challenge nor that raised in&#xD;
Eldred, we stress, allege Congress transgressed a gener-&#xD;
ally applicable First Amendment prohibition; we are not&#xD;
faced, for example, with copyright protection that hinges&#xD;
on the author’s viewpoint.&#xD;
  The Tenth Circuit’s initial opinion determined that&#xD;
petitioners marshaled a stronger First Amendment chal-&#xD;
lenge than did their predecessors in Eldred, who never&#xD;
“possessed unfettered access to any of the works at issue.”&#xD;
501 F. 3d, at 1193. See also id., at 1194 (“[O]nce the works&#xD;
at issue became free for anyone to copy, [petitioners] had&#xD;
vested First Amendment interests in the expressions,&#xD;
[thus] §514’s interference with [petitioners’] rights is&#xD;
subject to First Amendment scrutiny.”). As petitioners put&#xD;
it in this Court, Congress impermissibly revoked their&#xD;
right to exploit foreign works that “belonged to them” once&#xD;
the works were in the public domain. Brief for Petitioners&#xD;
44–45.&#xD;
  To copyright lawyers, the “vested rights” formulation&#xD;
&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  32 “[R]equir[ing]works that have already fallen into the public do-&#xD;
main to stay there” might, as the dissent asserts, supply an “easily&#xD;
administrable standard.” Post, at 14. However attractive this bright-&#xD;
line rule might be, it is not a rule rooted in the constitutional text or&#xD;
history. Nor can it fairly be gleaned from our case law. The dissent&#xD;
cites three decisions to document its assertion that “this Court has&#xD;
assumed the particular importance of public domain material in rough-&#xD;
ly analogous circumstances.” Post, at 15. The dictum in Graham v.&#xD;
John Deere Co. of Kansas City, 383 U. S. 1, 6 (1966), noted earlier, did&#xD;
not treat the public domain as a constitutional limit—certainly not&#xD;
under the rubric of the First Amendment. See supra, at 19. The other&#xD;
two decisions the dissent cites considered whether the federal Patent&#xD;
Act preempted a state trade-secret law, Kewanee Oil Co. v. Bicron&#xD;
Corp., 416 U. S. 470, 479–484 (1974), and whether the freedom of the&#xD;
press shielded reporters from liability for publishing material drawn&#xD;
from public court documents, Cox Broadcasting Corp. v. Cohn, 420 U. S.&#xD;
469, 495–497 (1975). Neither decision remotely ascribed constitutional&#xD;
significance to a work’s public domain status.&#xD;
28                      GOLAN v. HOLDER&#xD;
&#xD;
                        Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
might sound exactly backwards: Rights typically vest at&#xD;
the outset of copyright protection, in an author or&#xD;
rightholder. See, e.g., 17 U. S. C. §201(a) (“Copyright in a&#xD;
work protected . . . vests initially in the author . . . .”).&#xD;
Once the term of protection ends, the works do not revest&#xD;
in any rightholder. Instead, the works simply lapse into&#xD;
the public domain. See, e.g., Berne, Art. 18(1), 828&#xD;
U. N. T. S., at 251 (“This Convention shall apply to all&#xD;
works which . . . have not yet fallen into the public do-&#xD;
main . . . .”). Anyone has free access to the public domain,&#xD;
but no one, after the copyright term has expired, acquires&#xD;
ownership rights in the once-protected works.&#xD;
   Congress recurrently adjusts copyright law to protect&#xD;
categories of works once outside the law’s compass. For&#xD;
example, Congress broke new ground when it extended&#xD;
copyright protection to foreign works in 1891, Act of Mar.&#xD;
3, §13, 26 Stat. 1110; to dramatic works in 1856, Act of&#xD;
Aug. 18, 11 Stat. 138; to photographs and photographic&#xD;
negatives in 1865, Act of Mar. 3, §1, 13 Stat. 540; to mo-&#xD;
tion pictures in 1912, Act of Aug. 24, 37 Stat. 488; to fixed&#xD;
sound recordings in 1972, Act of Oct. 15, 1971, 85 Stat.&#xD;
391; and to architectural works in 1990, Architectural&#xD;
Works Copyright Protection Act, 104 Stat. 5133. And on&#xD;
several occasions, as recounted above, Congress protected&#xD;
works previously in the public domain, hence freely usable&#xD;
by the public. See supra, at 15–19. If Congress could&#xD;
grant protection to these works without hazarding height-&#xD;
ened First Amendment scrutiny, then what free speech&#xD;
principle disarms it from protecting works prematurely&#xD;
cast into the public domain for reasons antithetical to the&#xD;
Berne Convention? 33&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  33 It was the Fifth Amendment’s Takings Clause—not the First&#xD;
&#xD;
Amendment—that Congress apparently perceived to be a potential&#xD;
check on its authority to protect works then freely available to the&#xD;
                    Cite as: 565 U. S. ____ (2012)                  29&#xD;
&#xD;
                         Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
   Section 514, we add, does not impose a blanket prohibi-&#xD;
tion on public access. Petitioners protest that fair use and&#xD;
the idea/expression dichotomy “are plainly inadequate to&#xD;
protect the speech and expression rights that Section 514&#xD;
took from petitioners, or . . . the public”—that is, “the&#xD;
unrestricted right to perform, copy, teach and distribute&#xD;
the entire work, for any reason.” Brief for Petitioners 46–&#xD;
47. “Playing a few bars of a Shostakovich symphony,”&#xD;
petitioners observe, “is no substitute for performing the&#xD;
entire work.” Id., at 47.34&#xD;
   But Congress has not put petitioners in this bind. The&#xD;
question here, as in Eldred, is whether would-be users&#xD;
must pay for their desired use of the author’s expression,&#xD;
or else limit their exploitation to “fair use” of that work.&#xD;
Prokofiev’s Peter and the Wolf could once be performed&#xD;
free of charge; after §514 the right to perform it must be&#xD;
obtained in the marketplace. This is the same market-&#xD;
place, of course, that exists for the music of Prokofiev’s&#xD;
U. S. contemporaries: works of Copland and Bernstein, for&#xD;
example, that enjoy copyright protection, but nevertheless&#xD;
appear regularly in the programs of U. S. concertgoers.&#xD;
   Before we joined Berne, domestic works and some for-&#xD;
eign works were protected under U. S. statutes and bilat-&#xD;
eral international agreements, while other foreign works&#xD;
were available at an artificially low (because royalty-free)&#xD;
&#xD;
——————&#xD;
public. See URAA Joint Hearing 3 (statement of Rep. Hughes); id., at&#xD;
121 (app. to statement of Lehman, Commerce Dept.); id., at 141 (state-&#xD;
ment of Shapiro, USTR); id., at 145 (statement of Christopher Schroe-&#xD;
der, DOJ). The reliance-party protections supplied by §514, see supra,&#xD;
at 10–11, were meant to address such concerns. See URAA Joint&#xD;
Hearing 148–149 (prepared statement of Schroeder).&#xD;
  34 Because Shostakovich was a pre-1973 Russian composer, his works&#xD;
&#xD;
were not protected in the United States. See U. S. Copyright Office,&#xD;
Circular No. 38A: The International Copyright Relations of the United&#xD;
States 9, 11, n. 2 (2010) (copyright relations between the Soviet Union&#xD;
and the United States date to 1973).&#xD;
30                        GOLAN v. HOLDER&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
cost. By fully implementing Berne, Congress ensured that&#xD;
most works, whether foreign or domestic, would be gov-&#xD;
erned by the same legal regime. The phenomenon to&#xD;
which Congress responded is not new: Distortions of the&#xD;
same order occurred with greater frequency—and to the&#xD;
detriment of both foreign and domestic authors—when,&#xD;
before 1891, foreign works were excluded entirely from&#xD;
U. S. copyright protection. See Kampelman, The United&#xD;
States and International Copyright, 41 Am. J. Int’l L. 406,&#xD;
413 (1947) (“American readers were less inclined to read&#xD;
the novels of Cooper or Hawthorne for a dollar when they&#xD;
could buy a novel of Scott or Dickens for a quarter.”).&#xD;
Section 514 continued the trend toward a harmonized&#xD;
copyright regime by placing foreign works in the position&#xD;
they would have occupied if the current regime had been&#xD;
in effect when those works were created and first pub-&#xD;
lished. Authors once deprived of protection are spared the&#xD;
continuing effects of that initial deprivation; §514 gives&#xD;
them nothing more than the benefit of their labors during&#xD;
whatever time remains before the normal copyright term&#xD;
expires.35&#xD;
   Unlike petitioners, the dissent makes much of the so-&#xD;
called “orphan works” problem. See post, at 11–14, 23–24.&#xD;
We readily acknowledge the difficulties would-be users of&#xD;
copyrightable materials may face in identifying or locating&#xD;
copyright owners. See generally U. S. Copyright Office,&#xD;
Report on Orphan Works 21–40 (2006). But as the dissent&#xD;
concedes, see post, at 13, this difficulty is hardly peculiar&#xD;
to works restored under §514. It similarly afflicts, for&#xD;
&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  35 Persistently deploring “ ‘restored copyright’ protection [because it]&#xD;
&#xD;
removes material from the public domain,” post, at 14, the dissent does&#xD;
not pause to consider when and why the material came to be lodged in&#xD;
that domain. Most of the works affected by §514 got there after a term&#xD;
of zero or a term cut short by failure to observe U. S. formalities. See&#xD;
supra, at 9.&#xD;
                     Cite as: 565 U. S. ____ (2012)                  31&#xD;
&#xD;
                         Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
instance, U. S. libraries that attempt to catalogue U. S.&#xD;
books. See post, at 12. See also Brief for American Li-&#xD;
brary Association et al. as Amici Curiae 22 (Section 514&#xD;
“exacerbated,” but did not create, the problem of orphan&#xD;
works); U. S. Copyright Office, supra, at 41–44 (tracing&#xD;
orphan-works problem to Congress’ elimination of formali-&#xD;
ties, commencing with the 1976 Copyright Act).36&#xD;
   Nor is this a matter appropriate for judicial, as opposed&#xD;
to legislative, resolution. Cf. Authors Guild v. Google, Inc.,&#xD;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;span class="citation"&gt;&lt;a href="#"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;770&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;F. Supp. 2d&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;666&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;pre class="inline"&gt;, 677–678 (SDNY 2011) (rejecting&#xD;
proposed “Google Books” class settlement because, inter&#xD;
alia, “the establishment of a mechanism for exploiting&#xD;
unclaimed books is a matter more suited for Congress&#xD;
than this Court” (citing Eldred, 537 U. S., at 212)). In-&#xD;
deed, the host of policy and logistical questions identified&#xD;
by the dissent speak for themselves. Post, at 12. Despite&#xD;
“longstanding efforts,” see Authors Guild, 770 F. Supp. 2d,&#xD;
at 678 (quoting statement of Marybeth Peters), Congress&#xD;
has not yet passed ameliorative orphan-works legislation&#xD;
of the sort enacted by other Berne members, see, e.g.,&#xD;
Canada Copyright Act, R. S. C., 1985, c. C–42, §77 (au-&#xD;
thorizing Copyright Board to license use of orphan works&#xD;
by persons unable, after making reasonable efforts, to&#xD;
locate the copyright owner). Heretofore, no one has sug-&#xD;
gested that the orphan-works issue should be addressed&#xD;
through our implementation of Berne, rather than&#xD;
through overarching legislation of the sort proposed in&#xD;
Congress and cited by the dissent. See post, at 23–24;&#xD;
U. S. Copyright Office, Legal Issues in Mass Digitization&#xD;
25–29 (2011) (discussing recent legislative efforts). Our&#xD;
unstinting adherence to Berne may add impetus to calls&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  36 The pervasive problem of copyright piracy, noted post, at 13, like-&#xD;
&#xD;
wise is scarcely limited to protected foreign works formerly in the&#xD;
public domain.&#xD;
32                  GOLAN v. HOLDER&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
for the enactment of such legislation. But resistance to&#xD;
Berne’s prescriptions surely is not a necessary or proper&#xD;
response to the pervasive question, what should Congress&#xD;
do about orphan works.&#xD;
                             IV&#xD;
   Congress determined that U. S. interests were best&#xD;
served by our full participation in the dominant system of&#xD;
international copyright protection. Those interests in-&#xD;
clude ensuring exemplary compliance with our interna-&#xD;
tional obligations, securing greater protection for U. S.&#xD;
authors abroad, and remedying unequal treatment of&#xD;
foreign authors. The judgment §514 expresses lies well&#xD;
within the ken of the political branches. It is our obliga-&#xD;
tion, of course, to determine whether the action Congress&#xD;
took, wise or not, encounters any constitutional shoal. For&#xD;
the reasons stated, we are satisfied it does not. The judg-&#xD;
ment of the Court of Appeals for the Tenth Circuit is&#xD;
therefore&#xD;
                                                  Affirmed.&#xD;
&#xD;
  JUSTICE KAGAN took no part in the consideration or&#xD;
decision of this case.&#xD;
                 Cite as: 565 U. S. ____ (2012)          33&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
                Appendix to opinion of the Court &#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
                         APPENDIX&#xD;
&#xD;
Title 17 U. S. C. §104A provides:&#xD;
“(a) AUTOMATIC PROTECTION AND TERM.—&#xD;
   “(1) TERM.—&#xD;
      “(A) Copyright subsists, in accordance with this sec-&#xD;
tion, in restored works, and vests automatically on the&#xD;
date of restoration.&#xD;
      “(B) Any work in which copyright is restored under&#xD;
this section shall subsist for the remainder of the term of&#xD;
copyright that the work would have otherwise been grant-&#xD;
ed in the United States if the work never entered the&#xD;
public domain in the United States.&#xD;
   “(2) EXCEPTION.—Any work in which the copyright was&#xD;
ever owned or administered by the Alien Property Custo-&#xD;
dian and in which the restored copyright would be owned&#xD;
by a government or instrumentality thereof, is not a re-&#xD;
stored work.&#xD;
“(b) OWNERSHIP OF RESTORED COPYRIGHT.—A restored&#xD;
work vests initially in the author or initial rightholder of&#xD;
the work as determined by the law of the source country of&#xD;
the work.&#xD;
“(c) FILING OF NOTICE OF INTENT TO ENFORCE RESTORED&#xD;
COPYRIGHT AGAINST RELIANCE PARTIES.—On or after the&#xD;
date of restoration, any person who owns a copyright in a&#xD;
restored work or an exclusive right therein may file with&#xD;
the Copyright Office a notice of intent to enforce that&#xD;
person’s copyright or exclusive right or may serve such a&#xD;
notice directly on a reliance party. Acceptance of a notice&#xD;
by the Copyright Office is effective as to any reliance&#xD;
parties but shall not create a presumption of the validity&#xD;
of any of the facts stated therein. Service on a reliance&#xD;
party is effective as to that reliance party and any other&#xD;
reliance parties with actual knowledge of such service and&#xD;
of the contents of that notice.&#xD;
“(d) REMEDIES FOR INFRINGEMENT OF RESTORED&#xD;
COPYRIGHTS.—&#xD;
34                    GOLAN v. HOLDER&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
                Appendix to opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
   “(1) ENFORCEMENT OF COPYRIGHT IN RESTORED WORKS&#xD;
IN THE ABSENCE OF A RELIANCE PARTY.—As against any&#xD;
party who is not a reliance party, the remedies provided in&#xD;
chapter 5 of this title shall be available on or after the&#xD;
date of restoration of a restored copyright with respect&#xD;
to an act of infringement of the restored copyright that is&#xD;
commenced on or after the date of restoration.&#xD;
   “(2) ENFORCEMENT OF COPYRIGHT IN RESTORED WORKS&#xD;
AS AGAINST RELIANCE PARTIES.—As against a reliance&#xD;
party, except to the extent provided in paragraphs (3) and&#xD;
(4), the remedies provided in chapter 5 of this title shall be&#xD;
available, with respect to an act of infringement of a re-&#xD;
stored copyright, on or after the date of restoration of&#xD;
the restored copyright if the requirements of either of the&#xD;
following subparagraphs are met:&#xD;
        “(A)(i) The owner of the restored copyright (or such&#xD;
owner’s agent) or the owner of an exclusive right therein&#xD;
(or such owner’s agent) files with the Copyright Office,&#xD;
during the 24-month period beginning on the date of res-&#xD;
toration, a notice of intent to enforce the restored copy-&#xD;
right; and&#xD;
        “(ii)(I) the act of infringement commenced after the&#xD;
end of the 12-month period beginning on the date of publi-&#xD;
cation of the notice in the Federal Register;&#xD;
        “(II) the act of infringement commenced before the&#xD;
end of the 12-month period described in subclause (I) and&#xD;
continued after the end of that 12-month period, in which&#xD;
case remedies shall be available only for infringement&#xD;
occurring after the end of that 12-month period; or&#xD;
        “(III) copies or phonorecords of a work in which&#xD;
copyright has been restored under this section are made&#xD;
after publication of the notice of intent in the Federal&#xD;
Register.&#xD;
        “(B)(i) The owner of the restored copyright (or such&#xD;
owner’s agent) or the owner of an exclusive right therein&#xD;
(or such owner’s agent) serves upon a reliance party a&#xD;
                 Cite as: 565 U. S. ____ (2012)          35&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
                Appendix to opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
notice of intent to enforce a restored copyright; and&#xD;
        “(ii)(I) the act of infringement commenced after&#xD;
the end of the 12-month period beginning on the date the&#xD;
notice of intent is received;&#xD;
        “(II) the act of infringement commenced before the&#xD;
end of the 12-month period described in subclause (I) and&#xD;
continued after the end of that 12-month period, in which&#xD;
case remedies shall be available only for the infringement&#xD;
occurring after the end of that 12-month period; or&#xD;
        “(III) copies or phonorecords of a work in which&#xD;
copyright has been restored under this section are made&#xD;
after receipt of the notice of intent.&#xD;
“In the event that notice is provided under both subpara-&#xD;
graphs (A) and (B), the 12-month period referred to in&#xD;
such subparagraphs shall run from the earlier of publica-&#xD;
tion or service of notice.&#xD;
   “(3) EXISTING DERIVATIVE WORKS.—(A) In the case of a&#xD;
derivative work that is based upon a restored work and is&#xD;
created—&#xD;
        “(i) before the date of the enactment of the Uruguay&#xD;
Round Agreements Act, if the source country of the re-&#xD;
stored work is an eligible country on such date, or&#xD;
        “(ii) before the date on which the source country of&#xD;
the restored work becomes an eligible country, if that&#xD;
country is not an eligible country on such date of&#xD;
enactment,&#xD;
“a reliance party may continue to exploit that derivative&#xD;
work for the duration of the restored copyright if the&#xD;
reliance party pays to the owner of the restored copyright&#xD;
reasonable compensation for conduct which would be&#xD;
subject to a remedy for infringement but for the provisions&#xD;
of this paragraph.&#xD;
   “(B) In the absence of an agreement between the parties,&#xD;
the amount of such compensation shall be determined by&#xD;
an action in United States district court, and shall reflect&#xD;
any harm to the actual or potential market for or value of&#xD;
36                    GOLAN v. HOLDER&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
                Appendix to opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
the restored work from the reliance party’s continued&#xD;
exploitation of the work, as well as compensation for the&#xD;
relative contributions of expression of the author of the&#xD;
restored work and the reliance party to the derivative&#xD;
work.&#xD;
   “(4) COMMENCEMENT OF INFRINGEMENT FOR RELIANCE&#xD;
PARTIES.—For purposes of section 412, in the case of reli-&#xD;
ance parties, infringement shall be deemed to have com-&#xD;
menced before registration when acts which would have&#xD;
constituted infringement had the restored work been&#xD;
subject to copyright were commenced before the date of&#xD;
restoration.&#xD;
“(e) NOTICES OF INTENT TO ENFORCE A RESTORED&#xD;
COPYRIGHT.—&#xD;
   “(1) NOTICES OF INTENT FILED WITH THE COPYRIGHT&#xD;
OFFICE.—(A)(i) A notice of intent filed with the Copyright&#xD;
Office to enforce a restored copyright shall be signed by&#xD;
the owner of the restored copyright or the owner of an&#xD;
exclusive right therein, who files the notice under subsec-&#xD;
tion (d)(2)(A)(i) (hereafter in this paragraph referred to as&#xD;
the “owner”), or by the owner’s agent, shall identify the&#xD;
title of the restored work, and shall include an English&#xD;
translation of the title and any other alternative titles&#xD;
known to the owner by which the restored work may be&#xD;
identified, and an address and telephone number at which&#xD;
the owner may be contacted. If the notice is signed by an&#xD;
agent, the agency relationship must have been constituted&#xD;
in a writing signed by the owner before the filing of the&#xD;
notice. The Copyright Office may specifically require in&#xD;
regulations other information to be included in the notice,&#xD;
but failure to provide such other information shall not&#xD;
invalidate the notice or be a basis for refusal to list the&#xD;
restored work in the Federal Register.&#xD;
   “(ii) If a work in which copyright is restored has no&#xD;
formal title, it shall be described in the notice of intent in&#xD;
detail sufficient to identify it.&#xD;
                  Cite as: 565 U. S. ____ (2012)            37&#xD;
&#xD;
                      Opinion of the Court&#xD;
                 Appendix to opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
   “(iii) Minor errors or omissions may be corrected by&#xD;
further notice at any time after the notice of intent is filed.&#xD;
Notices of corrections for such minor errors or omissions&#xD;
shall be accepted after the period established in subsection&#xD;
(d)(2)(A)(i). Notices shall be published in the Federal&#xD;
Register pursuant to subparagraph (B).&#xD;
   “(B)(i) The Register of Copyrights shall publish in the&#xD;
Federal Register, commencing not later than 4 months&#xD;
after the date of restoration for a particular nation and&#xD;
every 4 months thereafter for a period of 2 years, lists&#xD;
identifying restored works and the ownership thereof if&#xD;
a notice of intent to enforce a restored copyright has been&#xD;
filed.&#xD;
   “(ii) Not less than 1 list containing all notices of intent&#xD;
to enforce shall be maintained in the Public Information&#xD;
Office of the Copyright Office and shall be available for&#xD;
public inspection and copying during regular business&#xD;
hours pursuant to sections 705 and 708.&#xD;
   “(C) The Register of Copyrights is authorized to fix&#xD;
reasonable fees based on the costs of receipt, processing,&#xD;
recording, and publication of notices of intent to enforce a&#xD;
restored copyright and corrections thereto.&#xD;
   “(D)(i) Not later than 90 days before the date the&#xD;
Agreement on Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Prop-&#xD;
erty referred to in section 101(d)(15) of the Uruguay&#xD;
Round Agreements Act enters into force with respect to&#xD;
the United States, the Copyright Office shall issue and&#xD;
publish in the Federal Register regulations governing the&#xD;
filing under this subsection of notices of intent to enforce a&#xD;
restored copyright.&#xD;
   “(ii) Such regulations shall permit owners of restored&#xD;
copyrights to file simultaneously for registration of the&#xD;
restored copyright.&#xD;
   “(2) NOTICES OF INTENT SERVED ON A RELIANCE PARTY.—&#xD;
(A) Notices of intent to enforce a restored copyright may be&#xD;
served on a reliance party at any time after the date of&#xD;
38                   GOLAN v. HOLDER&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
                Appendix to opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
restoration of the restored copyright.&#xD;
   “(B) Notices of intent to enforce a restored copyright&#xD;
served on a reliance party shall be signed by the owner or&#xD;
the owner’s agent, shall identify the restored work and the&#xD;
work in which the restored work is used, if any, in detail&#xD;
sufficient to identify them, and shall include an English&#xD;
translation of the title, any other alternative titles known&#xD;
to the owner by which the work may be identified, the use&#xD;
or uses to which the owner objects, and an address and&#xD;
telephone number at which the reliance party may contact&#xD;
the owner. If the notice is signed by an agent, the agency&#xD;
relationship must have been constituted in writing and&#xD;
signed by the owner before service of the notice.&#xD;
   “(3) EFFECT OF MATERIAL FALSE STATEMENTS.—Any&#xD;
material false statement knowingly made with respect to&#xD;
any restored copyright identified in any notice of intent&#xD;
shall make void all claims and assertions made with&#xD;
respect to such restored copyright.&#xD;
“(f) IMMUNITY FROM WARRANTY AND RELATED&#xD;
LIABILITY.—&#xD;
   “(1) IN GENERAL.—Any person who warrants, promises,&#xD;
or guarantees that a work does not violate an exclusive&#xD;
right granted in section 106 shall not be liable for legal,&#xD;
equitable, arbitral, or administrative relief if the war-&#xD;
ranty, promise, or guarantee is breached by virtue of the&#xD;
restoration of copyright under this section, if such warran-&#xD;
ty, promise, or guarantee is made before January 1, 1995.&#xD;
   “(2) PERFORMANCES.—No person shall be required to&#xD;
perform any act if such performance is made infringing by&#xD;
virtue of the restoration of copyright under the provisions&#xD;
of this section, if the obligation to perform was undertaken&#xD;
before January 1, 1995.&#xD;
“(g) PROCLAMATION OF COPYRIGHT RESTORATION.—&#xD;
Whenever the President finds that a particular foreign&#xD;
nation extends, to works by authors who are nationals&#xD;
or domiciliaries of the United States, restored copyright&#xD;
                  Cite as: 565 U. S. ____ (2012)           39&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
                Appendix to opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
protection on substantially the same basis as provided&#xD;
under this section, the President may by proclamation&#xD;
extend restored protection provided under this section to&#xD;
any work—&#xD;
   “(1) of which one or more of the authors is, on the date of&#xD;
first publication, a national, domiciliary, or sovereign&#xD;
authority of that nation; or&#xD;
   “(2) which was first published in that nation.&#xD;
“The President may revise, suspend, or revoke any such&#xD;
proclamation or impose any conditions or limitations on&#xD;
protection under such a proclamation.&#xD;
“(h) DEFINITIONS.—For purposes of this section and sec-&#xD;
tion 109(a):&#xD;
   “(1) The term “date of adherence or proclamation”&#xD;
means the earlier of the date on which a foreign nation&#xD;
which, as of the date the WTO Agreement enters into force&#xD;
with respect to the United States, is not a nation adhering&#xD;
to the Berne Convention or a WTO member country,&#xD;
becomes—&#xD;
      “(A) a nation adhering to the Berne Convention;&#xD;
      “(B) a WTO member country;&#xD;
      “(C) a nation adhering to the WIPO Copyright Treaty;&#xD;
      “(D) a nation adhering to the WIPO Performances and&#xD;
Phonograms Treaty; or&#xD;
      “(E) subject to a Presidential proclamation under&#xD;
subsection (g).&#xD;
   “(2) The “date of restoration” of a restored copyright is—&#xD;
      “(A) January 1, 1996, if the source country of the&#xD;
restored work is a nation adhering to the Berne Conven-&#xD;
tion or a WTO member country on such date, or&#xD;
      “(B) the date of adherence or proclamation, in the case&#xD;
of any other source country of the restored work.&#xD;
   “(3) The term “eligible country” means a nation, other&#xD;
than the United States, that—&#xD;
      “(A) becomes a WTO member country after the date of&#xD;
the enactment of the Uruguay Round Agreements Act;&#xD;
40                    GOLAN v. HOLDER&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
                Appendix to opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
     “(B) on such date of enactment is, or after such date&#xD;
of enactment becomes, a nation adhering to the Berne&#xD;
Convention;&#xD;
     “(C) adheres to the WIPO Copyright Treaty;&#xD;
     “(D) adheres to the WIPO Performances and Phono-&#xD;
grams Treaty; or&#xD;
     “(E) after such date of enactment becomes subject to a&#xD;
proclamation under subsection (g).&#xD;
  “(4) The term “reliance party” means any person who—&#xD;
     “(A) with respect to a particular work, engages in acts,&#xD;
before the source country of that work becomes an eligible&#xD;
country, which would have violated section 106 if the&#xD;
restored work had been subject to copyright protection,&#xD;
and who, after the source country becomes an eligible&#xD;
country, continues to engage in such acts;&#xD;
     “(B) before the source country of a particular work&#xD;
becomes an eligible country, makes or acquires 1 or more&#xD;
copies or phonorecords of that work; or&#xD;
     “(C) as the result of the sale or other disposition of a&#xD;
derivative work covered under subsection (d)(3), or signifi-&#xD;
cant assets of a person described in subparagraph (A) or&#xD;
(B), is a successor, assignee, or licensee of that person.&#xD;
  “(5) The term “restored copyright” means copyright in a&#xD;
restored work under this section.&#xD;
  “(6) The term “restored work” means an original work of&#xD;
authorship that—&#xD;
     “(A) is protected under subsection (a);&#xD;
     “(B) is not in the public domain in its source country&#xD;
through expiration of term of protection;&#xD;
     “(C) is in the public domain in the United States due&#xD;
to—&#xD;
        “(i) noncompliance with formalities imposed at any&#xD;
time by United States copyright law, including failure of&#xD;
renewal, lack of proper notice, or failure to comply with&#xD;
any manufacturing requirements;&#xD;
        “(ii) lack of subject matter protection in the case of&#xD;
                  Cite as: 565 U. S. ____ (2012)           41&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
                Appendix to opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
sound recordings fixed before February 15, 1972; or&#xD;
        “(iii) lack of national eligibility;&#xD;
      “(D) has at least one author or rightholder who was, at&#xD;
the time the work was created, a national or domiciliary of&#xD;
an eligible country, and if published, was first published in&#xD;
an eligible country and not published in the United States&#xD;
during the 30-day period following publication in such&#xD;
eligible country; and&#xD;
      “(E) if the source country for the work is an eligible&#xD;
country solely by virtue of its adherence to the WIPO&#xD;
Performances and Phonograms Treaty, is a sound&#xD;
recording.&#xD;
   “(7) The term “rightholder” means the person—&#xD;
      “(A) who, with respect to a sound recording, first fixes&#xD;
a sound recording with authorization, or&#xD;
      “(B) who has acquired rights from the person de-&#xD;
scribed in subparagraph (A) by means of any conveyance&#xD;
or by operation of law.&#xD;
   “(8) The “source country” of a restored work is—&#xD;
      “(A) a nation other than the United States&#xD;
      “(B) in the case of an unpublished work—&#xD;
        “(i) the eligible country in which the author or&#xD;
rightholder is a national or domiciliary, or, if a restored&#xD;
work has more than 1 author or rightholder, of which the&#xD;
majority of foreign authors or rightholders are nationals or&#xD;
domiciliaries; or&#xD;
        “(ii) if the majority of authors or rightholders are&#xD;
not foreign, the nation other than the United States which&#xD;
has the most significant contacts with the work; and&#xD;
      “(C) in the case of a published work—&#xD;
        “(i) the eligible country in which the work is first&#xD;
published, or&#xD;
        “(ii) if the restored work is published on the same&#xD;
day in 2 or more eligible countries, the eligible country&#xD;
which has the most significant contacts with the work.”&#xD;
                 Cite as: 565 U. S. ____ (2012)            1&#xD;
&#xD;
                    BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES&#xD;
                         _________________&#xD;
&#xD;
                          No. 10–545&#xD;
                         _________________&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
LAWRENCE GOLAN, ET AL., PETITIONERS v. ERIC H.&#xD;
   HOLDER, JR., ATTORNEY GENERAL, ET AL.&#xD;
 ON WRIT OF CERTIORARI TO THE UNITED STATES COURT OF&#xD;
            APPEALS FOR THE TENTH CIRCUIT&#xD;
                      [January 18, 2012]&#xD;
&#xD;
  JUSTICE BREYER, with whom JUSTICE ALITO joins,&#xD;
dissenting.&#xD;
  In order “[t]o promote the Progress of Science” (by which&#xD;
term the Founders meant “learning” or “knowledge”),&#xD;
the Constitution’s Copyright Clause grants Congress the&#xD;
power to “secur[e] for limited Times to Authors . . . the&#xD;
exclusive Right to their . . . Writings.” Art. I, §8, cl. 8.&#xD;
This “exclusive Right” allows its holder to charge a fee to&#xD;
those who wish to use a copyrighted work, and the ability&#xD;
to charge that fee encourages the production of new mate­&#xD;
rial. In this sense, a copyright is, in Macaulay’s words, a&#xD;
“tax on readers for the purpose of giving a bounty to writ­&#xD;
ers”—a bounty designed to encourage new production. As&#xD;
the Court said in Eldred, “ ‘[t]he economic philosophy&#xD;
behind the [Copyright] [C]lause . . . is the conviction that&#xD;
encouragement of individual effort by personal gain is the&#xD;
best way to advance public welfare through the talents of&#xD;
authors and inventors.’ ” Eldred v. Ashcroft, 537 U. S. 186,&#xD;
212, n. 18 (2003) (quoting Mazer v. Stein, 347 U. S. 201,&#xD;
219 (1954)). See T. Macaulay, Speeches on Copyright 25&#xD;
(E. Miller ed. 1913); E. Walterscheid, The Nature of the&#xD;
Intellectual Property Clause: A Study in Historical Per­&#xD;
spective 125–126 (2002) (hereinafter Walterscheid).&#xD;
  The statute before us, however, does not encourage&#xD;
anyone to produce a single new work. By definition, it&#xD;
bestows monetary rewards only on owners of old works—&#xD;
2                    GOLAN v. HOLDER&#xD;
&#xD;
                     BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
works that have already been created and already are in&#xD;
the American public domain. At the same time, the stat­&#xD;
ute inhibits the dissemination of those works, foreign&#xD;
works published abroad after 1923, of which there are&#xD;
many millions, including films, works of art, innumerable&#xD;
photographs, and, of course, books—books that (in the&#xD;
absence of the statute) would assume their rightful places&#xD;
in computer-accessible databases, spreading knowledge&#xD;
throughout the world. See infra, at 10–13. In my view,&#xD;
the Copyright Clause does not authorize Congress to enact&#xD;
this statute. And I consequently dissent.&#xD;
                                I&#xD;
   The possibility of eliciting new production is, and always&#xD;
has been, an essential precondition for American copyright&#xD;
protection. The Constitution’s words, “exclusive Right,”&#xD;
“limited Times,” “Progress of Science,” viewed through the&#xD;
lens of history underscore the legal significance of what&#xD;
the Court in Eldred referred to as the “economic philoso­&#xD;
phy behind the Copyright Clause.” 537 U. S., at 212, n. 18&#xD;
(brackets omitted). That philosophy understands copy­&#xD;
right’s grants of limited monopoly privileges to authors as&#xD;
private benefits that are conferred for a public reason—to&#xD;
elicit new creation.&#xD;
   Yet, as the Founders recognized, monopoly is a two­&#xD;
edged sword. On the one hand, it can encourage produc­&#xD;
tion of new works. In the absence of copyright protection,&#xD;
anyone might freely copy the products of an author’s&#xD;
creative labor, appropriating the benefits without incur­&#xD;
ring the nonrepeatable costs of creation, thereby deterring&#xD;
authors from exerting themselves in the first place. On&#xD;
the other hand, copyright tends to restrict the dissemina­&#xD;
tion (and use) of works once produced either because the&#xD;
absence of competition translates directly into higher&#xD;
consumer prices or because the need to secure copying&#xD;
permission sometimes imposes administrative costs that&#xD;
make it difficult for potential users of a copyrighted work&#xD;
to find its owner and strike a bargain. See W. Landes &amp;&#xD;
                  Cite as: 565 U. S. ____ (2012)            3&#xD;
&#xD;
                     BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
R. Posner, The Economic Structure of Intellectual Proper­&#xD;
ty Law 68–70, 213–214 (2003). Consequently, the original&#xD;
British copyright statute, the Constitution’s Framers, and&#xD;
our case law all have recognized copyright’s resulting&#xD;
and necessary call for balance.&#xD;
   At the time the Framers wrote the Constitution, they&#xD;
were well aware of Britain’s 18th-century copyright stat­&#xD;
ute, the Statute of Anne, 8 Anne, ch. 19 (1710), and they&#xD;
were aware of the legal struggles that produced it. That&#xD;
statute sought in part to control, and to limit, preexisting&#xD;
monopolies that had emerged in the book trade as a result&#xD;
of the Crown’s having previously granted special privileg­&#xD;
es to royal favorites. The Crown, for example, had char­&#xD;
tered the Stationers’ Company, permitting it to regulate&#xD;
and to censor works on the government’s behalf. The&#xD;
Stationers had thereby acquired control over the disposi­&#xD;
tion of copies of published works, from which emerged&#xD;
the Stationers’ copyright—a right conferred on company&#xD;
members, not authors, that was deemed to exist in perpe­&#xD;
tuity. See L. Patterson, Copyright in Historical Perspec­&#xD;
tive 1–16, 114–150 (1968) (hereinafter Patterson); Walter­&#xD;
scheid 59–65; Gómez-Arostegui, The Untold Story of the&#xD;
First Copyright Suit Under the Statute of Anne in 1710,&#xD;
25 Berkeley Tech. L. J. 1247, 1250–1256 (2010).&#xD;
   To prevent the continuation of the booksellers’ monopoly&#xD;
and to encourage authors to write new books, Parliament&#xD;
enacted the Statute of Anne. It bore the title: “An Act for&#xD;
the Encouragement of Learning, by vesting the Copies of&#xD;
printed Books in the Authors or Purchasers of such Cop­&#xD;
ies, during the Times therein mentioned.” And it granted&#xD;
authors (not publishers) and their assignees the “sole&#xD;
Right and Liberty of printing” their works for limited&#xD;
periods of time in order to encourage them “to compose and&#xD;
write useful Books.” 8 Anne, ch. 19, §1 (emphasis added).&#xD;
As one historian has put it, “[t]he central plank of the . . .&#xD;
Act was . . . a cultural quid pro quo. To encourage&#xD;
4                    GOLAN v. HOLDER&#xD;
&#xD;
                     BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
‘learned Men to compose and write useful Books’ the state&#xD;
would provide a guaranteed, if temporally limited, right&#xD;
to print and reprint those works.” Deazley, The Myth of&#xD;
Copyright at Common Law, 62 Camb. L. J. 106, 108&#xD;
(2003). At first, in their attempts to minimize their losses,&#xD;
the booksellers argued that authors had a perpetual com­&#xD;
mon-law copyright in their works deriving from their&#xD;
natural rights as creators. But the House of Lords ulti­&#xD;
mately held in Donaldson v. Beckett, 1 Eng. Rep. 837&#xD;
(1774), that the Statute of Anne had transformed any such&#xD;
perpetual common-law copyright into a copyright of a&#xD;
limited term designed to serve the public interest. Patter­&#xD;
son 15–16, 153, 158–179; Deazley, supra, at 114–126.&#xD;
   Many early colonial copyright statutes, patterned after&#xD;
the Statute of Anne, also stated that copyright’s objective&#xD;
was to encourage authors to produce new works and&#xD;
thereby improve learning. See U. S. Copyright Office,&#xD;
Copyright Enactments, Bulletin No. 3, pp. 1, 6, 10, 11, 17,&#xD;
19 (rev. 1963) (statutes of Connecticut, New Jersey, Penn­&#xD;
sylvania, South Carolina, Georgia, and New York); Wal­&#xD;
terscheid 74–75; Bracha, The Adventures of the Statute of&#xD;
Anne in the Land of Unlimited Possibilities: The Life of a&#xD;
Legal Transplant, 25 Berkeley Tech. L. J. 1427, 1444–&#xD;
1450 (2010).&#xD;
   At least, that was the predominant view expressed to,&#xD;
or by, the Founders. Patterson 93. Thomas Jefferson, for&#xD;
example, initially expressed great uncertainty as to&#xD;
whether the Constitution should authorize the grant of&#xD;
copyrights and patents at all, writing that “the benefit&#xD;
even of limited monopolies is too doubtful” to warrant&#xD;
anything other than their “suppression.” Letter from&#xD;
Thomas Jefferson to James Madison (July 31, 1788), in 13&#xD;
Papers of Thomas Jefferson 440, 443 (J. Boyd ed. 1956).&#xD;
James Madison also thought that “Monopolies . . . are&#xD;
justly classed among the greatest nu[i]sances in Govern­&#xD;
ment.” Letter from James Madison to Thomas Jefferson&#xD;
                 Cite as: 565 U. S. ____ (2012)            5&#xD;
&#xD;
                     BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
(Oct. 17, 1788), in 14 id., at 16, 21 (J. Boyd ed. 1958). But&#xD;
he argued that “in certain cases” such as copyright, mo­&#xD;
nopolies should “be granted” (“with caution, and guarded&#xD;
with strictness agst abuse”) to serve as “compensation&#xD;
for a benefit actually gained to the community . . . which&#xD;
the owner might otherwise withhold from public use.” Mo­&#xD;
nopolies. Perpetuities. Corporations. Ecclesiastical En­&#xD;
dowments. in J. Madison, Writings 756 (J. Rakove ed.&#xD;
1999) (emphasis added). Jefferson eventually came to&#xD;
agree with Madison, supporting a limited conferral of&#xD;
monopoly rights but only “as an encouragement to men to&#xD;
pursue ideas which may produce utility.” Letter from&#xD;
Thomas Jefferson to Isaac McPherson (Aug. 13, 1813), in 6&#xD;
Papers of Thomas Jefferson, at 379, 383 (J. Looney ed.&#xD;
2009) (emphasis added).&#xD;
   This utilitarian view of copyrights and patents, em­&#xD;
braced by Jefferson and Madison, stands in contrast to the&#xD;
“natural rights” view underlying much of continental&#xD;
European copyright law—a view that the English&#xD;
booksellers promoted in an effort to limit their losses&#xD;
following the enactment of the Statute of Anne and that in&#xD;
part motivated the enactment of some of the colonial&#xD;
statutes. Patterson 158–179, 183–192. Premised on the&#xD;
idea that an author or inventor has an inherent right to&#xD;
the fruits of his labor, it mythically stems from a legend­&#xD;
ary 6th-century statement of King Diarmed “ ‘to every cow&#xD;
her calf, and accordingly to every book its copy.’ ” A.&#xD;
Birrell, Seven Lectures on the Law and History of Copy­&#xD;
right in Books 42 (1899). That view, though perhaps&#xD;
reflected in the Court’s opinion, ante, at 30, runs contrary&#xD;
to the more utilitarian views that influenced the writing of&#xD;
our own Constitution’s Copyright Clause. See S. Rick­&#xD;
etson, The Berne Convention for the Protection of Literary&#xD;
and Artistic Works: 1886–1986, pp. 5–6 (1987) (The first&#xD;
French copyright laws “placed authors’ rights on a more&#xD;
elevated basis than the Act of Anne had done,” on the&#xD;
6                      GOLAN v. HOLDER&#xD;
&#xD;
                      BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
understanding that they were “simply according formal&#xD;
recognition to what was already inherent in the ‘very&#xD;
nature of things’ ”); S. Stewart, International Copyright&#xD;
and Neighbouring Rights 6–7 (2d ed. 1989) (describing the&#xD;
European system of droit d’auteur).&#xD;
    This utilitarian understanding of the Copyright Clause&#xD;
has long been reflected in the Court’s case law. In Mazer,&#xD;
for example, the Court refers to copyright as embodying&#xD;
the view that “encouragement of individual effort by per-&#xD;
sonal gain is the best way to advance public welfare&#xD;
through the talents of authors and inventors.” 347 U. S.,&#xD;
at 219 (emphasis added). In Twentieth Century Music&#xD;
Corp. v. Aiken, 422 U. S. 151 (1975), the Court says that&#xD;
underlying copyright is the understanding that “[c]reative&#xD;
work is to be encouraged and rewarded, but private moti-&#xD;
vation must ultimately serve the cause of promoting broad&#xD;
public availability of literature, music, and the other arts.”&#xD;
Id., at 156 (emphasis added). And in Sony Corp. of Amer-&#xD;
ica v. Universal City Studios, Inc., 464 U. S. 417 (1984), the&#xD;
Court, speaking of both copyrights and patents, points out&#xD;
that the “monopoly privileges that Congress may author­&#xD;
ize are . . . [not] primarily designed to provide a special&#xD;
private benefit. Rather, the limited grant is a means by&#xD;
which an important public purpose may be achieved. It is&#xD;
intended to motivate the creative activity of authors . . . by&#xD;
the provision of a special reward.” Id., at 429 (emphasis&#xD;
added); see also, e.g., Graham v. John Deere Co. of Kansas&#xD;
City, 383 U. S. 1, 6 (1966) (The “constitutional command&#xD;
. . . ‘[to] promote the Progress [of Science]’ . . . is the stand-&#xD;
ard expressed in the Constitution and it may not be ig­&#xD;
nored”); Fox Film Corp. v. Doyal, 286 U. S. 123, 127 (1932)&#xD;
(“The sole interest of the United States . . . lie[s] in the&#xD;
general benefits derived by the public from the labors of&#xD;
authors”).&#xD;
    Congress has expressed similar views in congressional&#xD;
Reports on copyright legislation. Thus, for example, an&#xD;
                  Cite as: 565 U. S. ____ (2012)             7&#xD;
&#xD;
                     BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
1892 House Report states:&#xD;
    “The object to be attained and the reason for the con­&#xD;
    stitutional grant of power are imbedded in the grant&#xD;
    itself. They are ‘to promote the progress of science&#xD;
    and the useful arts.’ . . . [The Clause says] nothing . . .&#xD;
    about any desire or purpose to secure to the author or&#xD;
    inventor his ‘natural right to his property.’ ” H. R.&#xD;
    Rep. No. 1494, 52d Cong., 1st Sess., 2.&#xD;
Similarly, the congressional authors of the landmark 1909&#xD;
Copyright Act wrote:&#xD;
    “The Constitution . . . provides that Congress shall&#xD;
    have the power to grant [copyrights] . . . [n]ot primari­&#xD;
    ly for the benefit of the author, . . . but because the&#xD;
    policy is believed to be for the benefit of the great body&#xD;
    of people, in that it will stimulate writing and inven-&#xD;
    tion, to give some bonus to authors and inventors.”&#xD;
    H. R. Rep. No. 2222, 60th Cong., 2d Sess., 7 (1909).&#xD;
And they went on to say:&#xD;
    “Congress must consider . . . two questions: First, how&#xD;
    much will the legislation stimulate the producer and&#xD;
    so benefit the public; and, second, how much will the&#xD;
    monopoly granted be detrimental to the public? The&#xD;
    granting of such exclusive rights, under the proper&#xD;
    terms and conditions, confers a benefit upon the pub­&#xD;
    lic that outweighs the evils of the temporary monop­&#xD;
    oly.” Ibid.&#xD;
   The upshot is that text, history, and precedent demon­&#xD;
strate that the Copyright Clause places great value on the&#xD;
power of copyright to elicit new production. Congress in&#xD;
particular cases may determine that copyright’s ability to&#xD;
do so outweighs any concomitant high prices, administra­&#xD;
tive costs, and restrictions on dissemination. And when it&#xD;
does so, we must respect its judgment. See Eldred, 537&#xD;
8                    GOLAN v. HOLDER&#xD;
&#xD;
                     BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
U. S., at 222. But does the Clause empower Congress to&#xD;
enact a statute that withdraws works from the public&#xD;
domain, brings about higher prices and costs, and in doing&#xD;
so seriously restricts dissemination, particularly to those&#xD;
who need it for scholarly, educational, or cultural pur-&#xD;
poses—all without providing any additional incentive for&#xD;
the production of new material? That is the question&#xD;
before us. And, as I have said, I believe the answer is no.&#xD;
Congress in this statute has exceeded what are, under any&#xD;
plausible reading of the Copyright Clause, its permissible&#xD;
limits.&#xD;
                              II&#xD;
   The Act before us says that it “restores” American copy­&#xD;
right to a set of works, which, for the most part, did not&#xD;
previously enjoy American copyright protection. These&#xD;
works had fallen into America’s public domain, but as of&#xD;
the “restoration” date, they had not yet fallen into the pub­&#xD;
lic domain of the foreign country where they originated.&#xD;
   The statute covers works originating almost anywhere&#xD;
outside the United States. See 17 U. S. C. §104A(h)(3)&#xD;
(setting out eligibility criteria); U. S. Copyright Office,&#xD;
Circular No. 38A: International Copyright Relations of the&#xD;
United States (2010). The relevant set of works consists&#xD;
primarily of works originating abroad that did not obtain,&#xD;
or at some point lost, American copyright protection be­&#xD;
cause (1) the author failed to comply with applicable&#xD;
American copyright formalities (such as notice or renew­&#xD;
al), or (2) the nation in which they were first published&#xD;
then lacked copyright relations with the United States, or&#xD;
(3) they are sound recordings fixed before February 15,&#xD;
1972. §104A(h)(6)(C). A work must also satisfy other&#xD;
technical requirements: It must have had a rightholder&#xD;
who was a national or resident of an eligible country on&#xD;
the day it was created; and it cannot have been published&#xD;
in the United States within 30 days of its first publication.&#xD;
                 Cite as: 565 U. S. ____ (2012)           9&#xD;
&#xD;
                    BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
§104A(h)(6)(D). The Act grants these works a copyright&#xD;
that expires at the time it would have expired had the&#xD;
author obtained a full American copyright term starting&#xD;
from the date on which the work was first published (in&#xD;
the foreign country). §104A(a)(1)(B).&#xD;
   The Act mainly applies to works first published abroad&#xD;
between 1923 and 1989. It does not apply significantly to&#xD;
earlier works because any work published before 1921&#xD;
would have fallen into the public domain before 1977 had&#xD;
it received a full American copyright term, while works&#xD;
published between 1921 and 1923 obtained a “restored”&#xD;
copyright that expired before the 1998 Sonny Bono Copy­&#xD;
right Term Extension Act, and so could have lasted two&#xD;
years at most. See Tit. I, §101, 90 Stat. 2574 (extending&#xD;
the copyright term of works still under copyright in 1977&#xD;
to 75 years); 17 U. S. C. §304(b) (extending the copyright&#xD;
term of works still under copyright in 1998 to 95 years). It&#xD;
has less impact on more recent works because in 1989&#xD;
the United States became a Berne member, abolished the&#xD;
copyright notice requirement, and thenceforth provided&#xD;
prospective copyright protection throughout the Berne&#xD;
Union. See R. Schechter &amp; J. Thomas, Intellectual Prop­&#xD;
erty: The Law of Copyrights, Patents and Trademarks 75–&#xD;
77 (2003); §7, 102 Stat. 2857–2858 (codified as amended at&#xD;
17 U. S. C. §§401–406).&#xD;
   Despite these temporal limitations, the Act covers vast&#xD;
numbers of works. The first category includes works&#xD;
published in countries that had copyright relations with&#xD;
the United States during this time period, such as most of&#xD;
Western Europe and Latin America, Australia, and Japan,&#xD;
see Circular No. 38A, supra, at 2–10, whose authors did&#xD;
not satisfy American copyright formalities, perhaps be­&#xD;
cause the author, who may not have sought an American&#xD;
copyright, published the book abroad without proper&#xD;
American notice, or perhaps because the author obtained a&#xD;
valid American copyright but failed to renew it.&#xD;
10                   GOLAN v. HOLDER&#xD;
&#xD;
                     BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
   The second category (works that entered the public&#xD;
domain due to a lack of copyright relations) includes,&#xD;
among others, all works published in Russia and other&#xD;
countries of the former Soviet Union before May 1973&#xD;
(when the U. S. S. R. joined the Universal Copyright Con­&#xD;
vention (UCC)), all works published in the People’s Repub­&#xD;
lic of China before March 1992 (when bilateral copyright&#xD;
relations between the People’s Republic and the United&#xD;
States were first established), all South Korean works&#xD;
published before October 1987 (when South Korea joined&#xD;
the UCC), and all Egyptian and Turkish works published&#xD;
before March 1989 (when the United States joined Berne).&#xD;
See id., at 2–10, and 11, nn. 2, 5, 6.&#xD;
   The third category covers all sound recordings from&#xD;
eligible foreign countries published after February 15,&#xD;
1972. The practical significance of federal copyright resto­&#xD;
ration to this category of works is less clear, since these&#xD;
works received, and continued to receive, copyright protec­&#xD;
tion under state law. See 17 U. S. C. §301(c).&#xD;
   Apparently there are no precise figures about the num­&#xD;
ber of works the Act affects, but in 1996 the then-Register&#xD;
of Copyrights, Marybeth Peters, thought that they “proba­&#xD;
bly number in the millions.” The Year in Review: Accom­&#xD;
plishments and Objectives of the U. S. Copyright Office, 7&#xD;
Ford. Intellectual Property Media &amp; Entertainment L. J.&#xD;
25, 31 (1996).&#xD;
                              A&#xD;
  The provision before us takes works from the public&#xD;
domain, at least as of January 1, 1996. See §104A(h)(2)(A)&#xD;
(setting “restoration” dates). It then restricts the dissemi­&#xD;
nation of those works in two ways.&#xD;
  First, “restored copyright” holders can now charge fees&#xD;
for works that consumers previously used for free. The&#xD;
price of a score of Shostakovich’s Preludes and Fugues Op.&#xD;
87, for example, has risen by a multiple of seven. Brief for&#xD;
                 Cite as: 565 U. S. ____ (2012)           11&#xD;
&#xD;
                     BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
Conductors Guild et al. as Amici Curiae 11. And, as the&#xD;
Court recognizes, an orchestra that once could perform&#xD;
“Peter and the Wolf . . . free of charge” will now have to&#xD;
buy the “right to perform it . . . in the marketplace.” Ante,&#xD;
at 29. But for the case of certain “derivative” works,&#xD;
§104A(d)(3), the “restored copyright” holder, like other&#xD;
copyright holders, can charge what the market will bear.&#xD;
If a school orchestra or other nonprofit organization can­&#xD;
not afford the new charges, so be it. They will have to do&#xD;
without—aggravating the already serious problem of&#xD;
cultural education in the United States. See Brief for&#xD;
Conductors Guild et al. as Amici Curiae 4–5, 7–8 (describ­&#xD;
ing the inability of many orchestras to pay for the rental of&#xD;
sheet music covered by “restored copyright[s]”).&#xD;
   Second, and at least as important, the statute creates&#xD;
administrative costs, such as the costs of determining&#xD;
whether a work is the subject of a “restored copyright,”&#xD;
searching for a “restored copyright” holder, and negotiat­&#xD;
ing a fee. Congress has tried to ease the administrative&#xD;
burden of contacting copyright holders and negotiating&#xD;
prices for those whom the statute calls “reliance part[ies],”&#xD;
namely those who previously had used such works when&#xD;
they were freely available in the public domain.&#xD;
§104A(h)(4). But Congress has done nothing to ease the&#xD;
administrative burden of securing permission from copy­&#xD;
right owners that is placed upon those who want to use a&#xD;
work that they did not previously use, and this is a partic­&#xD;
ular problem when it comes to “orphan works”—older and&#xD;
more obscure works with minimal commercial value that&#xD;
have copyright owners who are difficult or impossible to&#xD;
track down. Unusually high administrative costs threaten&#xD;
to limit severely the distribution and use of those works—&#xD;
works which, despite their characteristic lack of economic&#xD;
value, can prove culturally invaluable.&#xD;
   There are millions of such works. For example, accord­&#xD;
ing to European Union figures, there are 13 million or­&#xD;
12                   GOLAN v. HOLDER&#xD;
&#xD;
                     BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
phan books in the European Union (13% of the total&#xD;
number of books in-copyright there), 225,000 orphan films in&#xD;
European film archives, and 17 million orphan photo­&#xD;
graphs in United Kingdom museums. A. Vuopala, As­&#xD;
sessment of the Orphan works issue and Costs for Rights&#xD;
Clearance 19, 25 (2010), online at http://ec.europa.eu/&#xD;
information_society/activities/digital_libraries/doc/reports_&#xD;
orphan/anna_report.pdf (all Internet materials as visited&#xD;
Jan. 13, 2012, and available in Clerk of Court’s case file).&#xD;
How is a university, a film collector, a musician, a data­&#xD;
base compiler, or a scholar now to obtain permission to&#xD;
use any such lesser known foreign work previously in&#xD;
the American public domain? Consider the questions that&#xD;
any such individual, group, or institution usually must&#xD;
answer: Is the work eligible for restoration under the&#xD;
statute? If so, who now holds the copyright—the author?&#xD;
an heir? a publisher? an association? a long-lost cousin?&#xD;
Whom must we contact? What is the address? Suppose&#xD;
no one answers? How do we conduct a negotiation?&#xD;
   To find answers to these, and similar questions, costs&#xD;
money. The cost to the University of Michigan and the&#xD;
Institute of Museum and Library Services, for example, to&#xD;
determine the copyright status of books contained in the&#xD;
HathiTrust Digital Library that were published in the&#xD;
United States from 1923 to 1963 will exceed $1 million.&#xD;
Brief for American Library Assn. et al. as Amici Curiae 15.&#xD;
   It is consequently not surprising to learn that the Los&#xD;
Angeles Public Library has been unable to make its collec­&#xD;
tion of Mexican folk music publicly available because of&#xD;
problems locating copyright owners, that a Jewish cultural&#xD;
organization has abandoned similar efforts to make avail­&#xD;
able Jewish cultural music and other materials, or that&#xD;
film preservers, museums, universities, scholars, database&#xD;
compilers, and others report that the administrative costs&#xD;
associated with trying to locate foreign copyright owners&#xD;
have forced them to curtail their cultural, scholarly, or&#xD;
                 Cite as: 565 U. S. ____ (2012)           13&#xD;
&#xD;
                     BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
other work-preserving efforts. See, e.g., Comments of the&#xD;
Library Copyright Alliance in Response to the U. S. Copy­&#xD;
right Office’s Inquiry on Orphan Works 5 (Mar. 25, 2005),&#xD;
online at http://www.arl.org/bm~doc/lcacomment0305.pdf;&#xD;
Comments of Creative Commons and Save The Music&#xD;
in Response to the U. S. Copyright Office’s Inquiry on&#xD;
Orphan Works (Mar. 25, 2005), online at http://&#xD;
www.copyright.gov/orphan/comments/OW0643-STM-&#xD;
CreativeCommons.pdf; General Agreement on Tariffs and&#xD;
Trade (GATT): Intellectual Property Provisions, Joint&#xD;
Hearing before the Subcommittee on Intellectual Property&#xD;
and Judicial Administration of the House Committee on&#xD;
the Judiciary and the Subcommittee on Patents, Copy­&#xD;
rights and Trademarks of the Senate Committee on the&#xD;
Judiciary, 103d Cong., 2d Sess., 131, 273 (1994) (hereinaf­&#xD;
ter Joint Hearing) (statement of Larry Urbanski, Chair­&#xD;
man of the Fairness in Copyright Coalition and President&#xD;
of Moviecraft, Inc.); Brief for American Library Assn. et al.&#xD;
as Amici Curiae 6–23; Brief for Creative Commons Corp.&#xD;
as Amicus Curiae 7–8; Brief for Project Petrucci, LLC, as&#xD;
Amicus Curiae 10–11.&#xD;
   These high administrative costs can prove counterpro­&#xD;
ductive in another way. They will tempt some potential&#xD;
users to “steal” or “pirate” works rather than do without.&#xD;
And piracy often begets piracy, breeding the destructive&#xD;
habit of taking copyrighted works without paying for&#xD;
them, even where payment is possible. Such habits&#xD;
ignore the critical role copyright plays in the creation&#xD;
of new works, while reflecting a false belief that new&#xD;
creation appears by magic without thought or hope of&#xD;
compensation.&#xD;
                          B&#xD;
  I recognize that ordinary copyright protection also&#xD;
comes accompanied with dissemination-restricting royalty&#xD;
charges and administrative costs. But here the re­&#xD;
14                  GOLAN v. HOLDER&#xD;
&#xD;
                    BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
strictions work special harm. For one thing, the foreign&#xD;
location of restored works means higher than ordinary&#xD;
administrative costs. For another, the statute’s technical&#xD;
requirements make it very difficult to establish whether a&#xD;
work has had its copyright restored by the statute. Gard,&#xD;
In the Trenches with §104A: An Evaluation of the Parties’&#xD;
Arguments in Golan v. Holder as It Heads to the Supreme&#xD;
Court, 64 Vand. L. Rev. En Banc 199, 216–220 (2011)&#xD;
(describing difficulties encountered in compiling the in­&#xD;
formation necessary to create an online tool to determine&#xD;
whether the statute applies in any given case).&#xD;
   Worst of all, “restored copyright” protection removes&#xD;
material from the public domain. In doing so, it reverses&#xD;
the payment expectations of those who used, or intended&#xD;
to use, works that they thought belonged to them. Were&#xD;
Congress to act similarly with respect to well-established&#xD;
property rights, the problem would be obvious. This stat­&#xD;
ute analogously restricts, and thereby diminishes, Ameri­&#xD;
cans’ preexisting freedom to use formerly public domain&#xD;
material in their expressive activities.&#xD;
   Thus, while the majority correctly observes that the&#xD;
dissemination-restricting harms of copyright normally&#xD;
present problems appropriate for legislation to resolve,&#xD;
ante, at 31–32, the question is whether the Copyright&#xD;
Clause permits Congress seriously to exacerbate such a&#xD;
problem by taking works out of the public domain without&#xD;
a countervailing benefit. This question is appropriate for&#xD;
judicial resolution. Indeed, unlike Eldred where the Court&#xD;
had to decide a complicated line-drawing question—when&#xD;
is a copyright term too long?—here an easily administra­&#xD;
ble standard is available—a standard that would require&#xD;
works that have already fallen into the public domain to&#xD;
stay there.&#xD;
   The several, just mentioned features of the present&#xD;
statute are important, for they distinguish it from other&#xD;
copyright laws. By removing material from the public&#xD;
                 Cite as: 565 U. S. ____ (2012)           15&#xD;
&#xD;
                     BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
domain, the statute, in literal terms, “abridges” a preexist­&#xD;
ing freedom to speak. In practical terms, members of the&#xD;
public might well have decided what to say, as well as&#xD;
when and how to say it, in part by reviewing with a view&#xD;
to repeating, expression that they reasonably believed&#xD;
was, or would be, freely available. Given these speech&#xD;
implications, it is not surprising that Congress has long&#xD;
sought to protect public domain material when revising&#xD;
the copyright laws. See infra, at 19 (listing instances).&#xD;
And this Court has assumed the particular importance of&#xD;
public domain material in roughly analogous circumstanc­&#xD;
es. See Graham, 383 U. S., at 6 (“Congress may not au­&#xD;
thorize the issuance of patents whose effects are to remove&#xD;
existent knowledge from the public domain”); Kewanee Oil&#xD;
Co. v. Bicron Corp., 416 U. S. 470, 484 (1974) (trade secret&#xD;
protection is not incompatible with “policy that matter&#xD;
once in the public domain must remain in the public do­&#xD;
main”); Cox Broadcasting Corp. v. Cohn, 420 U. S. 469,&#xD;
496 (1975) (First Amendment prohibits sanctioning press&#xD;
for publishing material disclosed in public court docu­&#xD;
ments); see also Dastar Corp. v. Twentieth Century Fox&#xD;
Film Corp., 539 U. S. 23, 33 (2003) (“The right to copy . . .&#xD;
once a copyright has expired . . . passes to the public”&#xD;
(internal quotation marks omitted)).&#xD;
   Moreover, whereas forward-looking copyright laws tend&#xD;
to benefit those whose identities are not yet known (the&#xD;
writer who has not yet written a book, the musician who&#xD;
has not yet composed a song), when a copyright law is&#xD;
primarily backward looking the risk is greater that Con­&#xD;
gress is trying to help known beneficiaries at the expense&#xD;
of badly organized unknown users who find it difficult to&#xD;
argue and present their case to Congress. In Eldred, I&#xD;
thought this problem was severe. See generally 537 U. S.,&#xD;
at 243–266 (dissenting opinion). And in light of the fact&#xD;
that Congress, with one minor exception, heard testimony&#xD;
only from the representatives of existing copyright hold­&#xD;
16                   GOLAN v. HOLDER&#xD;
&#xD;
                    BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
ers, who hoped that passage of the statute would enable&#xD;
them to benefit from reciprocal treatment of American&#xD;
authors abroad, infra, at 21, I cannot say that even here&#xD;
the problem, while much diminished, was nonexistent.&#xD;
   I agree with the majority that, in doing so, this statute&#xD;
does not discriminate among speakers based on their&#xD;
viewpoints or subject matter. Ante, at 27. But such con­&#xD;
siderations do not exhaust potential First Amendment&#xD;
problems. Cf. Sorrell v. IMS Health Inc., 564 U. S. ___,&#xD;
___ (2011) (slip op., at 8) (finding First Amendment prob­&#xD;
lem in statute that prohibits drug manufacturers from&#xD;
using publicly available prescriber-identifying information&#xD;
in their marketing efforts in part because it “disfavor[ed]&#xD;
specific speakers”); Turner Broadcasting System, Inc. v.&#xD;
FCC, 512 U. S. 622, 659 (1994) (“Regulations that discrim­&#xD;
inate among media, or among different speakers within a&#xD;
single medium, often present serious First Amendment&#xD;
concerns”).&#xD;
   Taken together, these speech-related harms (e.g., re­&#xD;
stricting use of previously available material; reversing&#xD;
payment expectations; rewarding rent-seekers at the&#xD;
public’s expense) at least show the presence of a First&#xD;
Amendment interest. And that is enough. For present&#xD;
purposes, I need not decide whether the harms to that&#xD;
interest show a violation of the First Amendment. I need&#xD;
only point to the importance of interpreting the Constitu­&#xD;
tion as a single document—a document that we should not&#xD;
read as setting the Copyright Clause and the First&#xD;
Amendment at cross-purposes. Nor need I advocate the&#xD;
application here of strict or specially heightened review. I&#xD;
need only find that the First Amendment interest is im­&#xD;
portant enough to require courts to scrutinize with some&#xD;
care the reasons claimed to justify the Act in order to&#xD;
determine whether they constitute reasonable copyright­&#xD;
related justifications for the serious harms, including&#xD;
speech-related harms, which the Act seems likely to&#xD;
                  Cite as: 565 U. S. ____ (2012)           17&#xD;
&#xD;
                     BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
impose.&#xD;
                               C&#xD;
                               1&#xD;
   This statute does not serve copyright’s traditional public&#xD;
ends, namely the creation of monetary awards that “moti­&#xD;
vate the creative activity of authors,” Sony, 464 U. S.,&#xD;
at 429, “encourag[e] individual effort,” Mazer, 347 U. S.,&#xD;
at 219, and thereby “serve the cause of promoting broad&#xD;
public availability of literature, music, and the other arts,”&#xD;
Twentieth Century Music, 422 U. S., at 156. The statute&#xD;
grants its “restored copyright[s]” only to works already&#xD;
produced. It provides no monetary incentive to produce&#xD;
anything new. Unlike other American copyright statutes&#xD;
from the time of the Founders onwards, including the&#xD;
statute at issue in Eldred, it lacks any significant copy­&#xD;
right-related quid pro quo.&#xD;
   The majority seeks to avoid this awkward fact by refer­&#xD;
ring to past congressional practice that mostly suggests&#xD;
that Congress may provide new or increased protection&#xD;
both to newly created and to previously created, works.&#xD;
Ante, at 16, 18; Act of May 31, 1790, §1, 1 Stat. 124 (con­&#xD;
ferring its new federal copyright on new works as well as&#xD;
old); Act of July 3, 1832, §3, 4 Stat. 559 (authorizing new&#xD;
patents for past and future inventors who inadvertently&#xD;
failed to comply with applicable statutory formalities);&#xD;
McClurg v. Kingsland, 1 How. 202 (1843) (applying an act&#xD;
deeming a past or future inventor’s patent valid despite it&#xD;
being briefly used by, for example, the inventor’s employ­&#xD;
er). I do not dispute that copyright power. Insofar as such&#xD;
a statute does the former, i.e., extends protection to newly&#xD;
created material, it embodies copyright’s traditional justi­&#xD;
fication—eliciting new production. And I do not doubt&#xD;
that Congress may then also include existing works within&#xD;
the scope of, say, increased protection for equitable and&#xD;
administrative reasons. See Eldred, 537 U. S. at 204,&#xD;
18                    GOLAN v. HOLDER&#xD;
&#xD;
                     BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
214–215 (describing equitable reasons for applying newly&#xD;
extended copyright terms to future and existing copyrights&#xD;
alike). The statute before us, however, does not directly&#xD;
elicit any new production. Compare id., at 204–208; (ma­&#xD;
jority opinion) (noting that statute’s extended term would&#xD;
apply to newly created material, and finding that the&#xD;
determination of the likelihood of its eliciting new produc­&#xD;
tion in practice was a matter for Congress to determine),&#xD;
with id., at 243–267 (BREYER, J., dissenting) (expressing&#xD;
the view that there is little likelihood, in practice, that the&#xD;
statute would elicit new material). See also Walterscheid&#xD;
219 (the 1790 Congress likely thought it was substituting&#xD;
federal protection for preexisting state common-law pro­&#xD;
tections); Maher, Copyright Term, Retrospective Exten­&#xD;
sion, and the Copyright Law of 1790 in Historical Context,&#xD;
49 J. Copyright Soc. USA 1021, 1023–1024, and n. 8&#xD;
(2002) (numerical estimate suggesting that 1790 Act&#xD;
removed only a small number of books from public&#xD;
domain).&#xD;
   The other statutes to which the majority refers are&#xD;
private bills, statutes retroactively granting protection in&#xD;
wartime, or the like. Ante, at 16–19; Act of Feb. 19, 1849,&#xD;
ch. 57, 9 Stat. 763 (Levi Corson); Act of June 23, 1874, ch.&#xD;
534, 18 Stat., pt. 3, p. 618 (Tod Helmuth); Act of Feb. 17,&#xD;
1898, ch. 29, 30 Stat. 1396 (Judson Jones); Act of Dec. 18,&#xD;
1919, ch. 11, 41 Stat. 368; Act of Sept. 25, 1941, ch. 421, 55&#xD;
Stat. 732; see also Evans v. Jordan, 9 Cranch 199 (1815)&#xD;
(upholding a private bill restoring patent protection to a&#xD;
flour mill). But special circumstances, like wars, hurri­&#xD;
canes, earthquakes, and other disasters, prevent the&#xD;
realization in practice of a reasonable expectation of secur­&#xD;
ing or maintaining a preexisting right. Private bills are&#xD;
designed to provide special exceptions for comparable&#xD;
equitable reasons. See also Act of Mar. 3, 1893, ch. 215,&#xD;
27 Stat. 743 (similar, as far as I can tell). To find in these&#xD;
laws an important analogy to the present law, which for&#xD;
                 Cite as: 565 U. S. ____ (2012)          19&#xD;
&#xD;
                    BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
the most part covers works that the author did not expect&#xD;
to protect in America (and often did not particularly want&#xD;
to protect), seems somewhat farfetched.&#xD;
  In fact, Congressional practice shows the contrary. It&#xD;
consists of a virtually unbroken string of legislation pre­&#xD;
venting the withdrawal of works from the public domain.&#xD;
See, e.g., Berne Convention Implementation Act of 1988,&#xD;
§12, 102 Stat. 2860 (the Act “does not provide copyright&#xD;
protection for any work that is in the public domain in the&#xD;
United States”); Copyright Act of 1976, Tit. I, §101, 90&#xD;
Stat. 2573 (declining to extend copyright protection to any&#xD;
work that is in the public domain prior to the Act taking&#xD;
effect); Copyright Act of 1909, §7, 35 Stat. 1077 (“[N]o&#xD;
copyright shall subsist in the original text of any work&#xD;
which is in the public domain, or in any work which was&#xD;
published in this country or any foreign country prior to&#xD;
the going into effect of this Act and has not been already&#xD;
copyrighted in the United States”); Act to Amend the&#xD;
Several Acts Respecting Copy Rights §16, 4 Stat. 439 (the&#xD;
Act “shall not extend to any copyright heretofore secured,&#xD;
the term of which has already expired”); see also H. R.&#xD;
Rep. No. 1742, 87th Cong., 2d Sess., 3 (1962) (expressing&#xD;
concern that because “it is not possible to revive expired&#xD;
terms of copyright, it seems to the committee to be desira­&#xD;
ble to suspend further expiration of copyright for a period&#xD;
long enough to enable the working out of remaining obsta­&#xD;
cles to the overall revision of the copyright law”).&#xD;
                             2&#xD;
  The majority makes several other arguments. First, it&#xD;
argues that the Clause does not require the “creation of at&#xD;
least one new work,” ante, at 20, but may instead “promote&#xD;
the Progress of Science” in other ways. And it specifically&#xD;
mentions the “dissemination of existing and future works”&#xD;
as determinative here. Ante, at 20–23, and n. 25. The&#xD;
industry experts to whom the majority refers argue that&#xD;
20                   GOLAN v. HOLDER&#xD;
&#xD;
                     BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
copyright protection of already existing works can help,&#xD;
say, music publishers or film distributers raise prices,&#xD;
produce extra profits and consequently lead them to pub­&#xD;
lish or distribute works they might otherwise have ig­&#xD;
nored. But ordinarily a copyright—since it is a monopoly&#xD;
on copying—restricts dissemination of a work once pro­&#xD;
duced compared to a competitive market. And simply&#xD;
making the industry richer does not mean that the indus­&#xD;
try, when it makes an ordinary forward-looking economic&#xD;
calculus, will distribute works not previously distributed.&#xD;
The industry experts might mean that temporary extra&#xD;
profits will lead them to invest in the development of a&#xD;
market, say, by advertising. But this kind of argument,&#xD;
which can be made by distributers of all sorts of goods,&#xD;
ranging from kiwi fruit to Swedish furniture, has little&#xD;
if anything to do with the nonrepeatable costs of initial&#xD;
creation, which is the special concern of copyright protec­&#xD;
tion. See supra, at 2–3.&#xD;
   Moreover, the argument proves too much. It is the kind&#xD;
of argument that the Stationers’ Company might well&#xD;
have made and which the British Parliament rejected. Cf.&#xD;
Patterson 154–155 (describing failed booksellers’ bill&#xD;
seeking protection from foreign competition through an&#xD;
extension of the copyright term). It is the kind of argu­&#xD;
ment that could justify a legislature’s withdrawing from&#xD;
the public domain the works, say, of Hawthorne or of Swift&#xD;
or for that matter the King James Bible in order to en­&#xD;
courage further publication of those works; and, it could&#xD;
even more easily justify similar action in the case of lesser&#xD;
known early works, perhaps those of the Venerable Bede.&#xD;
The Court has not, to my knowledge, previously accepted&#xD;
such a rationale—a rationale well removed from the spe­&#xD;
cial economic circumstances that surround the nonrepeat­&#xD;
able costs of the initial creation of a “Writing.” Supra, at&#xD;
2. And I fear that doing so would read the Copyright&#xD;
Clause as if it were a blank check made out in favor of&#xD;
                  Cite as: 565 U. S. ____ (2012)           21&#xD;
&#xD;
                     BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
those who are not themselves creators.&#xD;
   It is not surprising that the copyright holders’ repre­&#xD;
sentatives who appeared before Congress did not empha­&#xD;
size this argument. (With one minor exception only those&#xD;
representatives appeared, see generally Joint Hearing; the&#xD;
Copyright Office did not testify, id., at 239.) Rather, they&#xD;
focused on the Berne Convention itself. By that time,&#xD;
Congress had already protected all new works of Berne&#xD;
members. But it had not provided additional protection to&#xD;
preexisting foreign works that were then in the American&#xD;
public domain. Industry witnesses testified that with­&#xD;
drawing such works from the American public domain&#xD;
would permit foreign copyright owners to charge American&#xD;
consumers more for their products; and that, as a result,&#xD;
the United States would be able to persuade foreign coun­&#xD;
tries to allow American holders of preexisting copyrights&#xD;
to charge foreign customers more money for their prod­&#xD;
ucts. See id., at 241 (statement of Eric Smith, Executive&#xD;
Director and General Counsel, International Intellectual&#xD;
Property Alliance) (“[F]ailure to [comply with Article 18]&#xD;
will . . . undermine the ability of the United States to press&#xD;
other countries to implement the same sort of protection in&#xD;
their implementing legislation currently pending in many&#xD;
legislatures around the globe”); id., at 253 (statement of&#xD;
Matt Gerson, Vice President for Congressional Affairs,&#xD;
Motion Picture Assn. of America) (similar). See also id., at&#xD;
85 (statement of Xavier Becerra, House Judiciary Commit­&#xD;
tee member) (“[R]etroactivity . . . is probably the best way&#xD;
to ensure that some of our older American works, any­&#xD;
thing from Motown, to ‘Star Trek,’ to ‘The Hardy Boys’ get&#xD;
the protection in some of these emerging foreign markets.&#xD;
It is important to ensure that countries no longer use our&#xD;
U. S. law as an excuse for not extending retroactive copy­&#xD;
right protections to some of our own works”). But see&#xD;
id., at 272–279 (statement of Larry Urbanski, Chairman&#xD;
of the Fairness in Copyright Coalition and President of&#xD;
22                   GOLAN v. HOLDER&#xD;
&#xD;
                     BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
Moviecraft Inc.) (testifying against restoration on grounds&#xD;
similar to those set out, supra, at 10–13).&#xD;
   This argument, whatever its intrinsic merits, is an ar­&#xD;
gument that directly concerns a private benefit: how to&#xD;
obtain more money from the sales of existing products. It&#xD;
is not an argument about a public benefit, such as how to&#xD;
promote or to protect the creative process.&#xD;
   Third, the majority points out that the statute “gives&#xD;
[authors] nothing more than the benefit of their labors&#xD;
during whatever time remains before the normal copyright&#xD;
term expires.” Ante, at 30. But insofar as it suggests that&#xD;
copyright should in general help authors obtain greater&#xD;
monetary rewards than needed to elicit new works, it rests&#xD;
upon primarily European, but not American, copyright&#xD;
concepts. See supra, at 5–6.&#xD;
   Fourth, the majority argues that this statutory provi­&#xD;
sion is necessary to fulfill our Berne Convention obliga­&#xD;
tions. Ante, at 4–8. The Treaty, in Article 18, says that&#xD;
the “Convention shall apply to all works which, at the&#xD;
moment of its coming into force [i.e., 1989 in the case of&#xD;
the United States] have not yet fallen into the public&#xD;
domain in the country of origin through the expiry of the&#xD;
term of protection.” Berne Convention for the Protection&#xD;
of Literary and Artistic Works, Art. 18(1), Sept. 9, 1886, as&#xD;
revised at Stockholm on July 14, 1967, 828 U. N. T. S. 221,&#xD;
251. The majority and Government say that this means&#xD;
we must protect the foreign works at issue here. And&#xD;
since the Berne Convention, taken as a whole, provides&#xD;
incentives for the creation of new works, I am willing to&#xD;
speculate, for argument’s sake, that the statute might&#xD;
indirectly encourage production of new works by making&#xD;
the United States’ place in the international copyright&#xD;
regime more secure.&#xD;
   Still, I cannot find this argument sufficient to save the&#xD;
statute. For one thing, this is a dilemma of the Govern­&#xD;
ment’s own making. The United States obtained the&#xD;
                  Cite as: 565 U. S. ____ (2012)           23&#xD;
&#xD;
                     BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
benefits of Berne for many years despite its failure to&#xD;
enact a statute implementing Article 18. But in 1994, the&#xD;
United States and other nations signed the Agreement on&#xD;
Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights,&#xD;
which enabled signatories to use World Trade Organiza­&#xD;
tion dispute resolution mechanisms to complain about&#xD;
other members’ Berne Convention violations. But at that&#xD;
time the Government, although it successfully secured&#xD;
reservations protecting other special features of American&#xD;
copyright law, made no effort to secure a reservation&#xD;
permitting the United States to keep some or all restored&#xD;
works in the American public domain. And it made no&#xD;
effort to do so despite the fact that Article 18 explicitly&#xD;
authorizes countries to negotiate exceptions to the Arti­&#xD;
cle’s retroactivity principle. See Art. 18(3), ibid. (“The&#xD;
application of [the retroactivity] principle shall be subject&#xD;
to any provisions contained in special conventions to that&#xD;
effect existing or to be concluded between countries of the&#xD;
Union” (emphasis added)); Gervais, Golan v. Holder: A&#xD;
Look at the Constraints Imposed by the Berne Conven­&#xD;
tion, 64 Vand. L. Rev. En Banc 147, 151–152 (2011); Gard,&#xD;
64 Vand. L. Rev. En Banc, at 206.&#xD;
   For another thing, the Convention does not require&#xD;
Congress to enact a statute that causes so much damage&#xD;
to public domain material. Article 18(3) also states that&#xD;
“the respective countries shall determine, each in so far as&#xD;
it is concerned, the conditions of application of this princi-&#xD;
ple.” 18 U. N. T. S., at 251 (emphasis added). Congress&#xD;
could have alleviated many of the costs that the statute&#xD;
imposes by, for example, creating forms of compulsory&#xD;
licensing, requiring “restored copyright” holders to provide&#xD;
necessary administrative information as a condition of&#xD;
protection, or insisting upon “reasonable royalties.” Cf.&#xD;
S. 2913, 110th Cong., 2d Sess. (2008) (legislation that&#xD;
would have limited judicial remedies against users of&#xD;
orphan works); H. R. 5889, 110th Cong., 2d Sess. (2008)&#xD;
24                    GOLAN v. HOLDER&#xD;
&#xD;
                     BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
(House version of same); American Society of Compos-&#xD;
ers, Authors and Publishers, http://www.ascap.com/&#xD;
licensing/termsdefined.aspx (society of music copyright&#xD;
owners offering blanket licenses that give users the unlim­&#xD;
ited right to perform any of its members’ songs for a fixed&#xD;
fee, thus reducing negotiation and enforcement costs).&#xD;
   To say this is not to criticize the Convention or our&#xD;
joining it. Rather, it is to argue that the other branches of&#xD;
Government should have tried to follow the Convention&#xD;
and in particular its provisions offering compliance flexi­&#xD;
bility. The fact that the statute has significant First&#xD;
Amendment costs is relevant in this respect, for that&#xD;
Amendment ordinarily requires courts to evaluate less&#xD;
restrictive, alternative possibilities. Doing so here, reveals&#xD;
that neither Congress nor the Executive took advantage of&#xD;
less-restrictive methods of compliance that the Convention&#xD;
itself provides. And that fact means that the Convention&#xD;
cannot provide the statute with a constitutionally suffi­&#xD;
cient justification that is otherwise lacking.&#xD;
                              III&#xD;
   The fact that, by withdrawing material from the public&#xD;
domain, the statute inhibits an important preexisting flow&#xD;
of information is sufficient, when combined with the other&#xD;
features of the statute that I have discussed, to convince&#xD;
me that the Copyright Clause, interpreted in the light of&#xD;
the First Amendment, does not authorize Congress to&#xD;
enact this statute.&#xD;
   I respectfully dissent from the Court’s contrary&#xD;
conclusion.&#xD;
&lt;/pre&gt;</opinion>