<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><opinion id="626208" path="/scotus/4d9G/faa-v-cooper/" sha1="736eeb18131de4daa697cfe73c841523044a1026" court="Supreme Court of the United States" download_URL="http://www.supremecourt.gov/opinions/11pdf/10-1024.pdf" time_retrieved="2012-03-28 14:21:19+00:00" date_filed="2012-03-28" precedential_status="Published" local_path="pdf/2012/03/28/Faa_v._Cooper.pdf" docket_number="10-1024" federal_cite_one="" lexis_cite="" case_name="FAA v. Cooper" judges="" nature_of_suit="" source="court website" blocked="False" date_blocked="None" extracted_by_ocr="False">&lt;pre class="inline"&gt;(Slip Opinion)              OCTOBER TERM, 2011                                       1&#xD;
&#xD;
                                       Syllabus&#xD;
&#xD;
         NOTE: Where it is feasible, a syllabus (headnote) will be released, as is&#xD;
       being done in connection with this case, at the time the opinion is issued.&#xD;
       The syllabus constitutes no part of the opinion of the Court but has been&#xD;
       prepared by the Reporter of Decisions for the convenience of the reader.&#xD;
       See United States v. Detroit Timber &amp; Lumber Co., 200 U. S. 321, 337.&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES&#xD;
&#xD;
                                       Syllabus&#xD;
&#xD;
    FEDERAL AVIATION ADMINISTRATION ET AL. v. &#xD;
&#xD;
                   COOPER &#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
CERTIORARI TO THE UNITED STATES COURT OF APPEALS FOR&#xD;
                  THE NINTH CIRCUIT&#xD;
&#xD;
  No. 10–1024. Argued November 30, 2011—Decided March 28, 2012&#xD;
Respondent Cooper, a licensed pilot, failed to disclose his human im-&#xD;
  munodeficiency virus (HIV) diagnosis to the Federal Aviation Admin-&#xD;
  istration (FAA) at a time when the agency did not issue medical cer-&#xD;
  tificates, which are required to operate an aircraft, to persons with&#xD;
  HIV. Subsequently, respondent applied to the Social Security Ad-&#xD;
  ministration (SSA) and received long-term disability benefits on the&#xD;
  basis of his HIV status. Thereafter, he renewed his certificate with&#xD;
  the FAA on several occasions, each time intentionally withholding in-&#xD;
  formation about his condition. The Department of Transportation&#xD;
  (DOT), the FAA’s parent agency, launched a joint criminal investiga-&#xD;
  tion with the SSA to identify medically unfit individuals who had ob-&#xD;
  tained FAA certifications. The DOT provided the SSA with the&#xD;
  names of licensed pilots, and the SSA, in turn, provided the DOT&#xD;
  with a spreadsheet containing information on those pilots who had&#xD;
  also received disability benefits. Respondent’s name appeared on the&#xD;
  spreadsheet, and an investigation led to his admission that he had&#xD;
  intentionally withheld information about his HIV status from the&#xD;
  FAA. His pilot certificate was revoked, and he was indicted for mak-&#xD;
  ing false statements to a Government agency. He pleaded guilty and&#xD;
  was fined and sentenced to probation. He then filed suit, alleging&#xD;
  that the FAA, DOT, and SSA violated the Privacy Act of 1974, which&#xD;
  contains a detailed set of requirements for the management of rec-&#xD;
  ords held by Executive Branch agencies. The Act allows an aggrieved&#xD;
  individual to sue for “actual damages,” 5 U. S. C. §552a(g)(4)(A), if&#xD;
  the Government intentionally or willfully violates the Act’s require-&#xD;
  ments in such a way as to adversely affect the individual. Specifical-&#xD;
  ly, respondent claimed that the unlawful disclosure to the DOT of his&#xD;
2                           FAA v. COOPER&#xD;
&#xD;
                                Syllabus&#xD;
&#xD;
    confidential medical information had caused him mental and emo-&#xD;
    tional distress. The District Court concluded that the Government&#xD;
    had violated the Act. But, finding the term “actual damages” ambig-&#xD;
    uous, the court relied on the sovereign immunity canon, which pro-&#xD;
    vides that sovereign immunity waivers must be strictly construed in&#xD;
    the Government’s favor, to hold that the Act does not authorize the&#xD;
    recovery of nonpecuniary damages. Reversing the District Court, the&#xD;
    Ninth Circuit concluded that “actual damages” in the Act is not am-&#xD;
    biguous and includes damages for mental and emotional distress.&#xD;
Held: The Privacy Act does not unequivocally authorize damages for&#xD;
 mental or emotional distress and therefore does not waive the Gov-&#xD;
 ernment’s sovereign immunity from liability for such harms. Pp. 4–&#xD;
 19.&#xD;
    (a) A waiver of sovereign immunity must be unequivocally ex-&#xD;
 pressed in statutory text, see e.g., Lane v. Peña, 518 U. S. 187, 192,&#xD;
 and any ambiguities are to be construed in favor of immunity, United&#xD;
 States v. Williams, 514 U. S. 527, 531. Ambiguity exists if there is a&#xD;
 plausible interpretation of the statute that would not allow money&#xD;
 damages against the Government. United States v. Nordic Village,&#xD;
 Inc., 503 U. S. 30, 37. Pp. 5–6.&#xD;
    (b) The term “actual damages” in the Privacy Act is a legal term of&#xD;
 art, and Congress, when it employs a term of art, “ ‘presumably&#xD;
 knows and adopts the cluster of ideas that were attached to each bor-&#xD;
 rowed word in the body of learning from which it was taken,’ ” Molzof&#xD;
 v. United States, 502 U. S. 301, 307. Even as a legal term, the precise&#xD;
 meaning of “actual damages” is far from clear. Although the term is&#xD;
 sometimes understood to include nonpecuniary harm, it has also been&#xD;
 used or construed more narrowly to cover damages for only pecuniary&#xD;
 harm. Because of the term’s chameleon-like quality, it must be con-&#xD;
 sidered in the particular context in which it appears. Pp. 6–9.&#xD;
    (c) The Privacy Act serves interests similar to those protected by&#xD;
 defamation and privacy torts. Its remedial provision, under which&#xD;
 plaintiffs can recover a minimum award of $1,000 if they first prove&#xD;
 at least some “actual damages,” “parallels” the common-law torts of&#xD;
 libel per quod and slander, under which plaintiffs can recover “gen-&#xD;
 eral damages” if they first prove “special damages.” Doe v. Chao, 540&#xD;
 U. S. 614, 625. “Special damages” are limited to actual pecuniary&#xD;
 loss, which must be specially pleaded and proved. “General damag-&#xD;
 es” cover nonpecuniary loss and need not be pleaded or proved. This&#xD;
 parallel suggests the possibility that Congress intended the term “ac-&#xD;
 tual damages” to mean “special damages,” thus barring Privacy Act&#xD;
 victims from any recovery unless they can first show some actual pe-&#xD;
 cuniary harm. That Congress would choose “actual damages” instead&#xD;
 of “special damages” is not without precedent, as the terms have oc-&#xD;
                     Cite as: 566 U. S. ____ (2012)                     3&#xD;
&#xD;
                                Syllabus&#xD;
&#xD;
  casionally been used interchangeably. Furthermore, any doubt about&#xD;
  the plausibility of construing “actual damages” as special damages in&#xD;
  the Privacy Act is put to rest by Congress’ deliberate refusal to allow&#xD;
  recovery for “general damages.” In common-law defamation and pri-&#xD;
  vacy cases, special damages is the only category of compensatory&#xD;
  damages other than general damages. Because Congress declined to&#xD;
  authorize general damages, it is reasonable to infer that Congress in-&#xD;
  tended the term “actual damages” in the Act to mean special damag-&#xD;
  es for proven pecuniary loss. Pp. 9–14.&#xD;
     (d) Although the contrary reading of the Privacy Act accepted by&#xD;
  the Ninth Circuit and advanced by respondent is not inconceivable, it&#xD;
  is plausible to read the Act as authorizing only damages for economic&#xD;
  loss. Because Congress did not speak unequivocally, the Court&#xD;
  adopts an interpretation of “actual damages” limited to proven pecu-&#xD;
  niary harm. To do otherwise would expand the scope of Congress’&#xD;
  sovereign immunity waiver beyond what the statutory text clearly&#xD;
  requires. P. 14.&#xD;
     (e) Respondent raises several counterarguments: (1) common-law&#xD;
  cases often define “actual damages” to mean all compensatory dam-&#xD;
  ages; (2) the elimination of “general damages” from the Privacy Act&#xD;
  means that there can be no recovery for presumed damages, but&#xD;
  plaintiffs can still recover for proven mental and emotional distress;&#xD;
  (3) because some courts have construed “actual damages” in similar&#xD;
  statutes to include mental and emotional distress, Congress must&#xD;
  have intended “actual damages” in the Act to include mental and&#xD;
  emotional distress as well; and (4) precluding nonpecuniary damages&#xD;
  would lead to absurd results, thereby frustrating the Act’s remedial&#xD;
  purpose. None of these arguments overcomes the sovereign immuni-&#xD;
  ty canon. Pp. 14–19.&#xD;
622 F. 3d 1016, reversed and remanded.&#xD;
&#xD;
   ALITO, J., delivered the opinion of the Court, in which ROBERTS, C. J.,&#xD;
and SCALIA, KENNEDY, and THOMAS, JJ., joined. SOTOMAYOR, J., filed a&#xD;
dissenting opinion, in which GINSBURG and BREYER, JJ., joined. KAGAN,&#xD;
J., took no part in the consideration or decision of the case.&#xD;
                        Cite as: 566 U. S. ____ (2012)                              1&#xD;
&#xD;
                             Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
     NOTICE: This opinion is subject to formal revision before publication in the&#xD;
     preliminary print of the United States Reports. Readers are requested to&#xD;
     notify the Reporter of Decisions, Supreme Court of the United States, Wash­&#xD;
     ington, D. C. 20543, of any typographical or other formal errors, in order&#xD;
     that corrections may be made before the preliminary print goes to press.&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES&#xD;
                                   _________________&#xD;
&#xD;
                                   No. 10–1024&#xD;
                                   _________________&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
   FEDERAL AVIATION ADMINISTRATION, ET AL., &#xD;
&#xD;
      PETITIONERS v. STANMORE CAWTHON &#xD;
&#xD;
                   COOPER &#xD;
&#xD;
 ON WRIT OF CERTIORARI TO THE UNITED STATES COURT OF&#xD;
&#xD;
            APPEALS FOR THE NINTH CIRCUIT&#xD;
&#xD;
                                [March 28, 2012]&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
  JUSTICE ALITO delivered the opinion of the Court.&#xD;
  The Privacy Act of 1974, codified in part at 5 U. S. C.&#xD;
§552a, contains a comprehensive and detailed set of re­&#xD;
quirements for the management of confidential records&#xD;
held by Executive Branch agencies. If an agency fails to&#xD;
comply with those requirements “in such a way as to have&#xD;
an adverse effect on an individual,” the Act authorizes the&#xD;
individual to bring a civil action against the agency.&#xD;
§552a(g)(1)(D). For violations found to be “intentional or&#xD;
willful,” the United States is liable for “actual damages.”&#xD;
§552a(g)(4)(A). In this case, we must decide whether the&#xD;
term “actual damages,” as used in the Privacy Act, in­&#xD;
cludes damages for mental or emotional distress. We hold&#xD;
that it does not.&#xD;
                                I&#xD;
   The Federal Aviation Administration (FAA) requires&#xD;
pilots to obtain a pilot certificate and medical certificate as&#xD;
a precondition for operating an aircraft. 14 CFR §§61.3(a),&#xD;
(c) (2011). Pilots must periodically renew their medical&#xD;
certificates to ensure compliance with FAA medical stand­&#xD;
2                     FAA v. COOPER&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
ards. See §61.23(d). When applying for renewal, pilots&#xD;
must disclose any illnesses, disabilities, or surgeries they&#xD;
have had, and they must identify any medications they are&#xD;
taking. See 14 CFR pt. 67.&#xD;
   Respondent Stanmore Cooper has been a private pilot&#xD;
since 1964. In 1985, he was diagnosed with a human im-&#xD;
munodeficiency virus (HIV) infection and began taking&#xD;
antiretroviral medication. At that time, the FAA did not&#xD;
issue medical certificates to persons with respondent’s&#xD;
condition. Knowing that he would not qualify for renewal&#xD;
of his medical certificate, respondent initially grounded&#xD;
himself and chose not to apply. In 1994, however, he ap-&#xD;
plied for and received a medical certificate, but he did so&#xD;
without disclosing his HIV status or his medication. He&#xD;
renewed his certificate in 1998, 2000, 2002, and 2004,&#xD;
each time intentionally withholding information about his&#xD;
condition.&#xD;
   When respondent’s health deteriorated in 1995, he&#xD;
applied for long-term disability benefits under Title II of&#xD;
the Social Security Act, 42 U. S. C. §401 et seq. To sub­&#xD;
stantiate his claim, he disclosed his HIV status to the&#xD;
Social Security Administration (SSA), which awarded him&#xD;
benefits for the year from August 1995 to August 1996.&#xD;
   In 2002, the Department of Transportation (DOT), the&#xD;
FAA’s parent agency, launched a joint criminal investiga­&#xD;
tion with the SSA, known as “Operation Safe Pilot,” to&#xD;
identify medically unfit individuals who had obtained FAA&#xD;
certifications to fly. The DOT gave the SSA a list of names&#xD;
and other identifying information of 45,000 licensed pilots&#xD;
in northern California. The SSA then compared the list&#xD;
with its own records of benefit recipients and compiled a&#xD;
spreadsheet, which it gave to the DOT.&#xD;
   The spreadsheet revealed that respondent had a current&#xD;
medical certificate but had also received disability bene­&#xD;
fits. After reviewing respondent’s FAA medical file and&#xD;
his SSA disability file, FAA flight surgeons determined in&#xD;
                    Cite as: 566 U. S. ____ (2012)                   3&#xD;
&#xD;
                         Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
2005 that the FAA would not have issued a medical cer-&#xD;
tificate to respondent had it known his true medical&#xD;
condition.&#xD;
   When investigators confronted respondent with what&#xD;
had been discovered, he admitted that he had intention-&#xD;
ally withheld from the FAA information about his HIV&#xD;
status and other relevant medical information. Because of&#xD;
these fraudulent omissions, the FAA revoked respondent’s&#xD;
pilot certificate, and he was indicted on three counts of&#xD;
making false statements to a Government agency, in&#xD;
violation of 18 U. S. C. §1001. Respondent ultimately&#xD;
pleaded guilty to one count of making and delivering a&#xD;
false official writing, in violation of §1018. He was sen­&#xD;
tenced to two years of probation and fined $1,000.1&#xD;
   Claiming that the FAA, DOT, and SSA (hereinafter&#xD;
Government) violated the Privacy Act by sharing his&#xD;
records with one another, respondent filed suit in the&#xD;
United States District Court for the Northern District of&#xD;
California. He alleged that the unlawful disclosure to the&#xD;
DOT of his confidential medical information, including his&#xD;
HIV status, had caused him “humiliation, embarrassment,&#xD;
mental anguish, fear of social ostracism, and other severe&#xD;
emotional distress.” App. to Pet. for Cert. 120a. Notably,&#xD;
he did not allege any pecuniary or economic loss.&#xD;
   The District Court granted summary judgment against&#xD;
respondent. &lt;/pre&gt;&lt;span class="citation"&gt;&lt;a href="#"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;816&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;F. Supp. 2d&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;778&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;pre class="inline"&gt;, 781 (2008). The court&#xD;
concluded that the Government had violated the Privacy&#xD;
Act and that there was a triable issue of fact as to whether&#xD;
the violation was intentional or willful.2 But the court&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  1 Respondent eventually applied for recertification as a pilot. After&#xD;
&#xD;
reviewing respondent’s medical records, including information about&#xD;
his HIV diagnosis and treatment, the FAA reissued his pilot certificate&#xD;
and medical certificate. Brief for Respondent 5, n. 1.&#xD;
  2 With certain exceptions, it is unlawful for an agency to disclose a&#xD;
&#xD;
record to another agency without the written consent of the person to&#xD;
whom the record pertains. 5 U. S. C. §552a(b). One exception to this&#xD;
4                         FAA v. COOPER&#xD;
&#xD;
                        Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
held that respondent could not recover damages because&#xD;
he alleged only mental and emotional harm, not economic&#xD;
loss. Finding that the term “actual damages” is “facially&#xD;
ambiguous,” id., at 791, and relying on the sovereign&#xD;
immunity canon, which provides that waivers of sovereign&#xD;
immunity must be strictly construed in favor of the Gov­&#xD;
ernment, the court concluded that the Act does not author­&#xD;
ize the recovery of damages from the Government for&#xD;
nonpecuniary mental or emotional harm.&#xD;
   The United States Court of Appeals for the Ninth Cir­&#xD;
cuit reversed and remanded. 622 F. 3d 1016, 1024 (2010).&#xD;
The court acknowledged that the term “actual damages”&#xD;
is a “ ‘chameleon’ ” in that “its meaning changes with the&#xD;
specific statute in which it is found.” Id., at 1029. But the&#xD;
court nevertheless held that, as used in the Privacy Act,&#xD;
the term includes damages for mental and emotional&#xD;
distress. Looking to what it described as “[i]ntrinsic” and&#xD;
“[e]xtrinsic” sources, id., at 1028, 1031, the court concluded&#xD;
that the meaning of “actual damages” in the Privacy&#xD;
Act is not ambiguous and that “a construction that limits&#xD;
recovery to pecuniary loss” is not “plausible,” id., at 1034.&#xD;
   The Government petitioned for rehearing or rehearing&#xD;
en banc, but a divided court denied the petition. Id., at&#xD;
1019. The Government then petitioned for certiorari, and&#xD;
we granted review. 564 U. S. ___ (2011).&#xD;
                          II&#xD;
  Because respondent seeks to recover monetary compen­&#xD;
sation from the Government for mental and emotional&#xD;
harm, we must decide whether the civil remedies provi­&#xD;
——————&#xD;
nondisclosure requirement applies when the head of an agency makes a&#xD;
written request for law enforcement purposes to the agency that&#xD;
maintains the record. See §552a(b)(7). The agencies in this case could&#xD;
easily have shared respondent’s medical records pursuant to the&#xD;
procedures prescribed by the Privacy Act, but the District Court con­&#xD;
cluded that they failed to do so.&#xD;
                 Cite as: 566 U. S. ____ (2012)           5&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
sion of the Privacy Act waives the Government’s sovereign&#xD;
immunity with respect to such a recovery.&#xD;
                             A&#xD;
   We have said on many occasions that a waiver of sover­&#xD;
eign immunity must be “unequivocally expressed” in&#xD;
statutory text. See, e.g., Lane v. Peña, 518 U. S. 187, 192&#xD;
(1996); United States v. Nordic Village, Inc., 503 U. S. 30,&#xD;
33 (1992); Irwin v. Department of Veterans Affairs, 498&#xD;
U. S. 89, 95 (1990). Legislative history cannot supply a&#xD;
waiver that is not clearly evident from the language of&#xD;
the statute. Lane, supra, at 192. Any ambiguities in the&#xD;
statutory language are to be construed in favor of immu-&#xD;
nity, United States v. Williams, 514 U. S. 527, 531 (1995),&#xD;
so that the Government’s consent to be sued is never en-&#xD;
larged beyond what a fair reading of the text requires,&#xD;
Ruckelshaus v. Sierra Club, 463 U. S. 680, 685–686 (1983)&#xD;
(citing Eastern Transp. Co. v. United States, 272 U. S. 675,&#xD;
686 (1927)). Ambiguity exists if there is a plausible inter­&#xD;
pretation of the statute that would not authorize money&#xD;
damages against the Government. Nordic Village, supra,&#xD;
at 34, 37.&#xD;
   The question that confronts us here is not whether&#xD;
Congress has consented to be sued for damages under the&#xD;
Privacy Act. That much is clear from the statute, which&#xD;
expressly authorizes recovery from the Government for&#xD;
“actual damages.” Rather, the question at issue concerns&#xD;
the scope of that waiver. For the same reason that we&#xD;
refuse to enforce a waiver that is not unambiguously&#xD;
expressed in the statute, we also construe any ambiguities&#xD;
in the scope of a waiver in favor of the sovereign. Lane,&#xD;
supra, at 192.&#xD;
   Although this canon of interpretation requires an un­&#xD;
mistakable statutory expression of congressional intent to&#xD;
waive the Government’s immunity, Congress need not&#xD;
state its intent in any particular way. We have never&#xD;
6                      FAA v. COOPER&#xD;
&#xD;
                      Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
required that Congress use magic words. To the contrary,&#xD;
we have observed that the sovereign immunity canon “is&#xD;
a tool for interpreting the law” and that it does not “dis­&#xD;
plac[e] the other traditional tools of statutory construc­&#xD;
tion.” Richlin Security Service Co. v. Chertoff, 553 U. S.&#xD;
571, 589 (2008). What we thus require is that the scope of&#xD;
Congress’ waiver be clearly discernable from the statutory&#xD;
text in light of traditional interpretive tools. If it is not,&#xD;
then we take the interpretation most favorable to the&#xD;
Government.&#xD;
                               B&#xD;
   The civil remedies provision of the Privacy Act provides&#xD;
that, for any “intentional or willful” refusal or failure to&#xD;
comply with the Act, the United States shall be liable for&#xD;
“actual damages sustained by the individual as a result of&#xD;
the refusal or failure, but in no case shall a person entitled&#xD;
to recovery receive less than the sum of $1,000.” 5 U. S. C.&#xD;
§552a(g)(4)(A). Because Congress did not define “actual&#xD;
damages,” respondent urges us to rely on the ordinary&#xD;
meaning of the word “actual” as it is defined in standard&#xD;
general-purpose dictionaries. But as the Court of Appeals&#xD;
explained, “actual damages” is a legal term of art, 622&#xD;
F. 3d, at 1028, and it is a “cardinal rule of statutory con­&#xD;
struction” that, when Congress employs a term of art, “ ‘it&#xD;
presumably knows and adopts the cluster of ideas that&#xD;
were attached to each borrowed word in the body of learn­&#xD;
ing from which it was taken,’ ” Molzof v. United States, 502&#xD;
U. S. 301, 307 (1992) (quoting Morissette v. United States,&#xD;
342 U. S. 246, 263 (1952)).&#xD;
   Even as a legal term, however, the meaning of “actual&#xD;
damages” is far from clear. The latest edition of Black’s&#xD;
Law Dictionary available when Congress enacted the&#xD;
Privacy Act defined “actual damages” as “[r]eal, substan­&#xD;
tial and just damages, or the amount awarded to a com­&#xD;
plainant in compensation for his actual and real loss or&#xD;
                  Cite as: 566 U. S. ____ (2012)            7&#xD;
&#xD;
                      Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
injury, as opposed on the one hand to ‘nominal’ damages,&#xD;
and on the other to ‘exemplary’ or ‘punitive’ damages.”&#xD;
Black’s Law Dictionary 467 (rev. 4th ed. 1968). But this&#xD;
general (and notably circular) definition is of little value&#xD;
here because, as the Court of Appeals accurately observed,&#xD;
the precise meaning of the term “changes with the specific&#xD;
statute in which it is found.” 622 F. 3d, at 1029.&#xD;
   The term is sometimes understood to include nonpecu­&#xD;
niary harm. Take, for instance, some courts’ interpreta­&#xD;
tions of the Fair Housing Act (FHA), 42 U. S. C. §3613(c),&#xD;
and the Fair Credit Reporting Act (FCRA), 15 U. S. C.&#xD;
§§1681n, 1681o. A number of courts have construed “ac­&#xD;
tual” damages in the remedial provisions of both statutes&#xD;
to include compensation for mental and emotional dis­&#xD;
tress. See, e.g., Seaton v. Sky Realty Co., 491 F. 2d 634,&#xD;
636–638 (CA7 1974) (authorizing compensatory damages&#xD;
under the FHA, 42 U. S. C. §3612, the predecessor to&#xD;
§3613, for humiliation); Steele v. Title Realty Co., 478 F. 2d&#xD;
380, 384 (CA10 1973) (stating that damages under the&#xD;
FHA “are not limited to out-of-pocket losses but may&#xD;
include an award for emotional distress and humiliation”);&#xD;
Thompson v. San Antonio Retail Merchants Assn., 682&#xD;
F. 2d 509, 513–514 (CA5 1982) (per curiam) (explaining&#xD;
that, “[e]ven when there are no out-of-pocket expenses,&#xD;
humiliation and mental distress do constitute recoverable&#xD;
elements of damage” under the FCRA); Millstone v.&#xD;
O’Hanlon Reports, Inc., 528 F. 2d 829, 834–835 (CA8 1976)&#xD;
(approving an award of damages under the FCRA for “loss&#xD;
of sleep, nervousness, frustration and mental anguish”).&#xD;
   In other contexts, however, the term has been used or&#xD;
construed more narrowly to authorize damages for only&#xD;
pecuniary harm. In the wrongful-death provision of the&#xD;
Federal Tort Claims Act (FTCA), for example, Congress&#xD;
authorized “actual or compensatory damages, measured&#xD;
by the pecuniary injuries resulting from such death.” 28&#xD;
U. S. C. §2674, ¶2. At least one court has defined “actual&#xD;
8                           FAA v. COOPER&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
damages” in the Copyright Act of 1909, 17 U. S. C. §101(b)&#xD;
(1970 ed.), as “the extent to which the market value of&#xD;
a copyrighted work has been injured or destroyed by an&#xD;
infringement.” Frank Music Corp. v. Metro-Goldwyn-&#xD;
Mayer, Inc., 772 F. 2d 505, 512 (CA9 1985); see also&#xD;
Mackie v. Rieser, 296 F. 3d 909, 917 (CA9 2002) (holding&#xD;
that “ ‘hurt feelings’ over the nature of the infringement”&#xD;
have no place in the actual damages calculus). And some&#xD;
courts have construed “actual damages” in the Securities&#xD;
Exchange Act of 1934, 15 U. S. C. §78bb(a), to mean “some&#xD;
form of economic loss.” Ryan v. Foster &amp; Marshall, Inc.,&#xD;
556 F. 2d 460, 464 (CA9 1977); see also Osofsky v. Zipf,&#xD;
645 F. 2d 107, 111 (CA2 1981) (stating that the purpose of&#xD;
§78bb(a) “is to compensate civil plaintiffs for economic loss&#xD;
suffered as a result of wrongs committed in violation of the&#xD;
1934 Act”); Herpich v. Wallace, 430 F. 2d 792, 810 (CA5&#xD;
1970) (noting that the “gist” of an action for damages&#xD;
under the Act is “economic injury”).3&#xD;
   Because the term “actual damages” has this chameleon­&#xD;
like quality, we cannot rely on any all-purpose definition&#xD;
but must consider the particular context in which the term&#xD;
——————&#xD;
   3 This narrow usage is reflected in contemporaneous state-court deci­&#xD;
&#xD;
sions as well. See, e.g., Reist v. Manwiller, 231 Pa. Super. 444, 449,&#xD;
n. 4, 332 A. 2d 518, 520, n. 4 (1974) (explaining that recovery for&#xD;
intentional infliction of emotional distress is allowed “despite the total&#xD;
absence of physical injury and actual damages”); Nalder v. Crest Corp.,&#xD;
93 Idaho 744, 749, 472 P. 2d 310, 315 (1970) (noting that damages for&#xD;
“mental anguish” due to the wrongful execution of a judgment “are&#xD;
allowable only as an element of punitive but not of actual damages”). It&#xD;
is also reflected in post-Privacy Act statutes and judicial decisions. See,&#xD;
e.g., 17 U. S. C. §1009(d)(1)(A)(ii) (defining “actual damages” in the&#xD;
Audio Home Recording Act of 1992 as “the royalty payments that&#xD;
should have been paid”); 18 U. S. C. §2318(e)(3) (2006 ed., Supp. IV)&#xD;
(calculating “actual damages” for purposes of a counterfeit labeling&#xD;
statute in terms of financial loss); Guzman v. Western State Bank of&#xD;
Devils Lake, 540 F. 2d 948, 953 (CA8 1976) (stating that compensatory&#xD;
damages in a civil rights suit “can be awarded for emotional and mental&#xD;
distress even though no actual damages are proven”).&#xD;
                     Cite as: 566 U. S. ____ (2012)                     9&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
appears.4&#xD;
                              C&#xD;
   The Privacy Act directs agencies to establish safeguards&#xD;
to protect individuals against the disclosure of confiden­&#xD;
tial records “which could result in substantial harm, em­&#xD;
barrassment, inconvenience, or unfairness to any indi-&#xD;
vidual on whom information is maintained.” 5 U. S. C.&#xD;
§552a(e)(10); see also §2(b), 88 Stat. 1896 (stating that the&#xD;
“purpose of this Act is to provide certain safeguards for&#xD;
an individual against an invasion of personal privacy”).&#xD;
Because the Act serves interests similar to those protected&#xD;
by defamation and privacy torts, there is good reason to&#xD;
infer that Congress relied upon those torts in drafting the&#xD;
Act.&#xD;
   In Doe v. Chao, 540 U. S. 614 (2004), we held that the&#xD;
Privacy Act’s remedial provision authorizes plaintiffs to&#xD;
recover a guaranteed minimum award of $1,000 for viola­&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  4 The  dissent criticizes us for noting that the dictionary definition&#xD;
contains an element of circularity. The dissent says that the defini­&#xD;
tion—“ ‘[a]ctual damages’ compensate for actual injury”—is “plain&#xD;
enough.” Post, at 3 (opinion of SOTOMAYOR, J.). But defining “actual”&#xD;
damages by reference to “actual” injury is hardly helpful when our task&#xD;
is to determine what Congress meant by “actual.” The dissent’s refer­&#xD;
ence to the current version of Black’s Law Dictionary, which provides&#xD;
that “actual damages” can mean “tangible damages,” only highlights&#xD;
the term’s ambiguity. See Black’s Law Dictionary 445 (9th ed. 2009).&#xD;
If “actual damages” can mean “tangible damages,” then it can be&#xD;
construed not to include intangible harm, like mental and emotional&#xD;
distress. Similarly unhelpful is the dissent’s citation to a general­&#xD;
purpose dictionary that defines “actual” as “existing in fact or reality”&#xD;
and “damages” as “compensation or satisfaction imposed by law for a&#xD;
wrong or injury.” Webster’s Third New International Dictionary 22,&#xD;
571 (2002) (emphasis added). Combining these two lay definitions says&#xD;
nothing about whether compensation for mental and emotional distress&#xD;
is in fact imposed by law. The definitions merely beg the question we&#xD;
are trying to answer. It comes as little surprise, therefore, that “actual&#xD;
damages” has taken on different meanings in different statutes, as our&#xD;
examples amply illustrate.&#xD;
10                         FAA v. COOPER&#xD;
&#xD;
                         Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
tions of the Act, but only if they prove at least some&#xD;
“actual damages.” Id., at 620, 627; see §552a(g)(4)(A).&#xD;
Although we did not address the meaning of “actual dam­&#xD;
ages,” id., at 622, n. 5, 627, n. 12, we observed that the&#xD;
provision “parallels” the remedial scheme for the common­&#xD;
law torts of libel per quod and slander, under which plain­&#xD;
tiffs can recover “general damages,” but only if they prove&#xD;
“special harm” (also known as “special damages”), id., at&#xD;
625; see also 3 Restatement of Torts §575, Comments a&#xD;
and b (1938) (hereinafter Restatement); D. Dobbs, Law of&#xD;
Remedies §7.2, pp. 511–513 (1973) (hereinafter Dobbs).5&#xD;
“Special damages” are limited to actual pecuniary loss,&#xD;
which must be specially pleaded and proved. 1 D. Hag­&#xD;
gard, Cooley on Torts §164, p. 580 (4th ed. 1932) (hereinaf­&#xD;
ter Cooley).6 “General damages,” on the other hand, cover&#xD;
“loss of reputation, shame, mortification, injury to the&#xD;
feelings and the like and need not be alleged in detail and&#xD;
require no proof.” Id., §164, at 579.7&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  5 Libel  per quod and slander (as opposed to libel and slander per se)&#xD;
apply to a communication that is not defamatory on its face but that is&#xD;
defamatory when coupled with some other extrinsic fact. Dobbs §7.2, at&#xD;
512–513.&#xD;
   6 See also 3 Restatement §575, Comment b (“Special harm . . . is harm&#xD;
&#xD;
of a material and generally of a pecuniary nature”); Dobbs §7.2, at 520&#xD;
(“Special damages in defamation cases mean pecuniary damages, or at&#xD;
least ‘material loss’ ” (footnote omitted)). Special damages do not&#xD;
include mental or emotional distress. See 3 Restatement §575, Com­&#xD;
ment c (“The emotional distress caused to the person slandered by his&#xD;
knowledge that he has been defamed is not special harm and this is so&#xD;
although the distress results in a serious illness”); Dobbs §7.2, at 520&#xD;
(“Even under the more modern approach, special damages in defama­&#xD;
tion cases must be economic in nature, and it is not enough that the&#xD;
plaintiff has suffered harm to reputation, mental anguish or other&#xD;
dignitary harm, unless he has also suffered the loss of something&#xD;
having economic value”).&#xD;
   7 See also id., §3.2, at 139 (explaining that noneconomic harms “are&#xD;
&#xD;
called general damages”); W. Prosser, Law of Torts §112, p. 761 (4th ed.&#xD;
1971) (noting that “ ‘general’ damages may be recovered for the injury&#xD;
to the plaintiff’s reputation, his wounded feelings and humiliation, and&#xD;
                     Cite as: 566 U. S. ____ (2012)                  11&#xD;
&#xD;
                         Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
    This parallel between the Privacy Act and the common­&#xD;
law torts of libel per quod and slander suggests the possi­&#xD;
bility that Congress intended the term “actual damages”&#xD;
in the Act to mean special damages. The basic idea is that&#xD;
Privacy Act victims, like victims of libel per quod or slan­&#xD;
der, are barred from any recovery unless they can first&#xD;
show actual—that is, pecuniary or material—harm. Upon&#xD;
showing some pecuniary harm, no matter how slight, they&#xD;
can recover the statutory minimum of $1,000, presumably&#xD;
for any unproven harm. That Congress would choose to&#xD;
use the term “actual damages” instead of “special damages”&#xD;
was not without precedent. The terms had occasionally&#xD;
been used interchangeably. See, e.g., Wetzel v. Gulf Oil&#xD;
Corp., 455 F. 2d 857, 862 (CA9 1972) (holding that plain­&#xD;
tiff could not establish libel per quod because he “did not&#xD;
introduce any valid and sufficient evidence of actual dam­&#xD;
age”); Electric Furnace Corp. v. Deering Milliken Research&#xD;
Corp., 325 F. 2d 761, 765 (CA6 1963) (stating that “libel&#xD;
per quod standing alone without proof of actual damages&#xD;
. . . will not support a verdict for the plaintiff ”); M &amp; S&#xD;
Furniture Sales Co. v. Edward J. De Bartolo Corp., 249&#xD;
Md. 540, 544, 241 A. 2d 126, 128 (1968) (“In the case of&#xD;
words or conduct actionable only per quod, the injurious&#xD;
effect must be established by allegations and proof of&#xD;
special damage and in such cases it is not only necessary&#xD;
to plead and show that the words or actions were defama­&#xD;
tory, but it must also appear that such words or conduct&#xD;
caused actual damage”); Clementson v. Minnesota Tribune&#xD;
Co., 45 Minn. 303, 47 N. W. 781 (1891) (distinguishing&#xD;
“actual, or, as they are sometimes termed, ‘special,’ dam­&#xD;
ages” from “general damages—that is, damages not pecu­&#xD;
——————&#xD;
resulting physical illness and pain, as well as estimated future dam­&#xD;
ages of the same kind” (footnotes omitted)); 3 Restatement §621, Com­&#xD;
ment a (stating that, in actions for defamation, a plaintiff may recover&#xD;
general damages for “impairment of his reputation or, through loss of&#xD;
reputation, to his other interests”).&#xD;
12                         FAA v. COOPER&#xD;
&#xD;
                         Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
niary in their nature”).8&#xD;
  Any doubt about the plausibility of construing “actual&#xD;
damages” in the Privacy Act synonymously with “special&#xD;
damages” is put to rest by Congress’ refusal to authorize&#xD;
“general damages.” In an uncodified section of the Act,&#xD;
Congress established the Privacy Protection Study Com­&#xD;
mission to consider, among other things, “whether the&#xD;
Federal Government should be liable for general dam-&#xD;
ages.” §5(c)(2)(B)(iii), 88 Stat. 1907, note following 5 U. S. C.&#xD;
§552a, p. 712. As we explained in Doe, “Congress left the&#xD;
question of general damages . . . for another day.” 540&#xD;
U. S., at 622. Although the Commission later recom-&#xD;
mended that general damages be allowed, ibid., n. 4,&#xD;
Congress never amended the Act to include them. For&#xD;
that reason, we held that it was “beyond serious doubt”&#xD;
that general damages are not available for violations of&#xD;
the Privacy Act. Id., at 622.&#xD;
  By authorizing recovery for “actual” but not for “gen­&#xD;
eral” damages, Congress made clear that it viewed those&#xD;
terms as mutually exclusive. In actions for defamation&#xD;
and related dignitary torts, two categories of compensa-&#xD;
tory damages are recoverable: general damages and special&#xD;
damages. Cooley §164, at 579; see also 4 Restatement&#xD;
§867, Comment d (1939) (noting that damages for inter­&#xD;
ference with privacy “can be awarded in the same way in&#xD;
which general damages are given for defamation”).9 Be­&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  8 The   dissent disregards these precedents as the product of careless&#xD;
imprecision. Post, at 8, n. 6. But just as we assume that Congress did&#xD;
not act carelessly, we should not be so quick to assume that the courts&#xD;
did. The better explanation for these precedents is not that the courts&#xD;
were careless, but that the term “actual damages” has a varied mean­&#xD;
ing that, depending on the context, can be limited to compensation for&#xD;
only pecuniary harm.&#xD;
    9 See also Moriarty v. Lippe, 162 Conn. 371, 382–383, 294 A. 2d 326,&#xD;
&#xD;
332–333 (1972) (“Having admittedly alleged or proven no special&#xD;
damages, the plaintiff here is limited to a recovery of general damages&#xD;
. . .”); Meyerle v. Pioneer Publishing Co., 45 N. D. 568, 574, 178 N. W.&#xD;
                     Cite as: 566 U. S. ____ (2012)                   13&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
cause Congress declined to authorize “general damages,”&#xD;
we think it likely that Congress intended “actual dam­&#xD;
ages” in the Privacy Act to mean special damages for&#xD;
proven pecuniary loss.&#xD;
  Not surprisingly, this interpretation was accepted by&#xD;
the Privacy Protection Study Commission, an expert body&#xD;
authorized by Congress and highly sensitive to the Act’s&#xD;
goals. The Commission understood “actual damages” in&#xD;
the Act to be “a synonym for special damages as that term&#xD;
is used in defamation cases.” Personal Privacy in an&#xD;
Information Society: The Report of the Privacy Protection&#xD;
Study Commission 530 (July 1977); see also ibid. (“The&#xD;
legislative history and language of the Act suggest that&#xD;
Congress meant to restrict recovery to specific pecuniary&#xD;
losses until the Commission could weigh the propriety of&#xD;
extending the standard of recovery”). Although we are not&#xD;
bound in any way by the Commission’s report, we think it&#xD;
confirms the reasonableness of interpreting “actual dam­&#xD;
ages” in the unique context of the Privacy Act as the&#xD;
equivalent of special damages.&#xD;
&#xD;
——————&#xD;
792, 794 (1920) (per curiam) (“Generally speaking, there are recognized&#xD;
two classes of damages in libel cases, general damages and special&#xD;
damages”); Winans v. Chapman, 104 Kan. 664, 666, 180 P. 266, 267&#xD;
(1919) (“Actual damages include both general and special damages”);&#xD;
Childers v. San Jose Mercury Printing &amp; Publishing Co., 105 Cal. 284,&#xD;
288–289, 38 P. 903, 904 (1894) (explaining that special damages, “as&#xD;
a branch of actual damages[,] may be recovered when actual pecuniary&#xD;
loss has been sustained” and that the “remaining branch of actual&#xD;
damages embraces recovery for loss of reputation, shame, mortification,&#xD;
injury to feelings, etc.”); see generally Dobbs §7.3, at 531 (“Though the&#xD;
dignitary torts often involve only general damages . . . , they sometimes&#xD;
produce actual pecuniary loss. When this happens, the plaintiff is&#xD;
usually entitled to recover any special damage he can prove . . . ”); 1&#xD;
F. Harper &amp; F. James, Law of Torts §5.30, p. 470 (1956) (“When liability&#xD;
for defamation is established, the defendant, in addition to such ‘gen­&#xD;
eral’ damages as may be assessed by the jury, is also liable for any&#xD;
special damage which he has sustained”).&#xD;
14                    FAA v. COOPER&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
                            D&#xD;
  We do not claim that the contrary reading of the statute&#xD;
accepted by the Court of Appeals and advanced now by&#xD;
respondent is inconceivable. But because the Privacy Act&#xD;
waives the Federal Government’s sovereign immunity, the&#xD;
question we must answer is whether it is plausible to read&#xD;
the statute, as the Government does, to authorize only&#xD;
damages for economic loss. Nordic Village, 503 U. S., at&#xD;
34, 37. When waiving the Government’s sovereign im­&#xD;
munity, Congress must speak unequivocally. Lane, 518&#xD;
U. S., at 192. Here, we conclude that it did not. As a&#xD;
consequence, we adopt an interpretation of “actual dam­&#xD;
ages” limited to proven pecuniary or economic harm. To&#xD;
do otherwise would expand the scope of Congress’ sover­&#xD;
eign immunity waiver beyond what the statutory text&#xD;
clearly requires.&#xD;
                          III&#xD;
  None of respondent’s contrary arguments suffices to&#xD;
overcome the sovereign immunity canon.&#xD;
                             A&#xD;
   Respondent notes that the term “actual damages” has&#xD;
often been defined broadly in common-law cases, and in&#xD;
our own, to include all compensatory damages. See Brief&#xD;
for Respondent 18–25. For example, in Birdsall v. Coo­&#xD;
lidge, 93 U. S. 64 (1876), a patent infringement case, we&#xD;
observed that “[c]ompensatory damages and actual dam­&#xD;
ages mean the same thing.” Ibid. And in Gertz v. Robert&#xD;
Welch, Inc., 418 U. S. 323 (1974), we wrote that actual&#xD;
injury in the defamation context “is not limited to out-of­&#xD;
pocket loss” and that it customarily includes “impairment&#xD;
of reputation and standing in the community, personal&#xD;
humiliation, and mental anguish and suffering.” Id., at&#xD;
350.&#xD;
   These cases and others cited by respondent stand for the&#xD;
                      Cite as: 566 U. S. ____ (2012)               15&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
unremarkable point that the term “actual damages” can&#xD;
include nonpecuniary loss. But this generic meaning does&#xD;
not establish with the requisite clarity that the Privacy&#xD;
Act, with its distinctive features, authorizes damages for&#xD;
mental and emotional distress. As we already explained,&#xD;
the term “actual damages” takes on different meanings in&#xD;
different contexts.&#xD;
                               B&#xD;
   Respondent’s stronger argument is that the exclusion of&#xD;
“general damages” from the statute simply means that&#xD;
there can be no recovery for presumed damages. Privacy&#xD;
Act victims can still recover for mental and emotional&#xD;
distress, says respondent, so long as it is proved. See Brief&#xD;
for Respondent 54–56.10&#xD;
   This argument is flawed because it suggests that proven&#xD;
mental and emotional distress does not count as general&#xD;
damages. The term “general damages” is not limited to&#xD;
compensation for unproven injuries; it includes compensa­&#xD;
tion for proven injuries as well. See 3 Restatement §621,&#xD;
Comment a (noting that general damages compensate for&#xD;
“harm which . . . is proved, or, in the absence of proof,&#xD;
is assumed to have caused to [the plaintiff’s] reputation”).&#xD;
To be sure, specific proof of emotional harm is not required&#xD;
to recover general damages for dignitary torts. Dobbs&#xD;
§7.3, at 529. But it does not follow that general damages&#xD;
cannot be recovered for emotional harm that is actually&#xD;
proved.&#xD;
   Aside from the fact that general damages need not be&#xD;
proved, what distinguishes those damages, whether&#xD;
proved or not, from the only other category of compensa-&#xD;
tory damages available in the relevant common-law suits is&#xD;
the type of harm. In defamation and privacy cases, “the&#xD;
affront to the plaintiff’s dignity and the emotional harm&#xD;
——————&#xD;
 10 The   dissent advances the same argument. See post, at 9–11.&#xD;
16                    FAA v. COOPER&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
done” are “called general damages, to distinguish them&#xD;
from proof of actual economic harm,” which is called “spe­&#xD;
cial damages.” Id., §3.2, at 139; see also supra, at 10, 12–&#xD;
13, and nn. 6, 7, 9. Therefore, the converse of general&#xD;
damages is special damages, not all proven damages, as&#xD;
respondent would have it. Because Congress removed&#xD;
“general damages” from the Act’s remedial provision, it is&#xD;
reasonable to infer that Congress foreclosed recovery for&#xD;
nonpecuniary harm, even if such harm can be proved, and&#xD;
instead waived the Government’s sovereign immunity only&#xD;
with respect to harm compensable as special damages.&#xD;
                              C&#xD;
  Looking beyond the Privacy Act’s text, respondent&#xD;
points to the use of the term “actual” damages in the&#xD;
remedial provisions of the FHA, 42 U. S. C. §3613(c), and&#xD;
the FCRA, 15 U. S. C. §§1681n, 1681o. As previously&#xD;
mentioned, courts have held that “actual” damages within&#xD;
the meaning of these statutes include compensation for&#xD;
mental and emotional distress. Supra, at 7. Citing the&#xD;
rule of construction that Congress intends the same lan­&#xD;
guage in similar statutes to have the same meaning, see&#xD;
Northcross v. Board of Ed. of Memphis City Schools, 412&#xD;
U. S. 427, 428 (1973) (per curiam), respondent argues that&#xD;
the Privacy Act should also be interpreted as authorizing&#xD;
damages for mental and emotional distress. See Brief for&#xD;
Respondent 25–32.&#xD;
  Assuming for the sake of argument that these lower&#xD;
court decisions are correct, they provide only weak support&#xD;
for respondent’s argument here. Since the term “actual&#xD;
damages” can mean different things in different contexts,&#xD;
statutes other than the Privacy Act provide only limited&#xD;
interpretive aid, and that is especially true here. Neither&#xD;
the FHA nor the FCRA contains text that precisely mir­&#xD;
                     Cite as: 566 U. S. ____ (2012)                   17&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
rors the Privacy Act.11 In neither of those statutes did&#xD;
Congress specifically decline to authorize recovery for&#xD;
general damages as it did in the Privacy Act. Supra, at&#xD;
12–13. And most importantly, none of the lower court&#xD;
cases interpreting the statutes, which respondent has&#xD;
cited, see Brief for Respondent 29–31, involves the sover­&#xD;
eign immunity canon.&#xD;
   Respondent also points to the FTCA, but the FTCA’s&#xD;
general liability provision does not even use the term&#xD;
“actual damages.” It instead provides that the “United&#xD;
States shall be liable” for certain tort claims “in the same&#xD;
manner and to the same extent as a private individual”&#xD;
under relevant state law. 28 U. S. C. §2674, ¶1. For that&#xD;
reason alone, the FTCA’s general liability provision is not&#xD;
a reliable source for interpreting the term “actual damages”&#xD;
in the Privacy Act. Nor does the FTCA’s wrongful­&#xD;
death provision—which authorizes “actual or compensa-&#xD;
tory damages, measured by the pecuniary injuries resulting&#xD;
from such death,” §2674, ¶2—prove that Congress under­&#xD;
stood the term “actual damages” in the Privacy Act to&#xD;
include nonpecuniary mental and emotional harm. To the&#xD;
contrary, it proves that actual damages can be understood&#xD;
to entail only pecuniary harm depending on the context.&#xD;
Because the FTCA, like the FHA and FCRA, does not&#xD;
share the same text or design as the Privacy Act, it is not&#xD;
a fitting analog for construing the Act.&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  11 Compare   42 U. S. C. §3613(c)(1) (stating that “the court may award&#xD;
to the plaintiff actual and punitive damages”); 15 U. S. C. §1681n(a)(1)&#xD;
(authorizing “(A) any actual damages sustained by the consumer as a&#xD;
result of the failure or damages of not less than $100 and not more than&#xD;
$1,000; or (B) . . . actual damages sustained by the consumer as a result&#xD;
of the failure or $1,000, whichever is greater”); §1681o(a)(1) (authoriz­&#xD;
ing “any actual damages sustained by the consumer as a result of the&#xD;
failure”) with 5 U. S. C. §552a(g)(4)(A) (authorizing “actual damages&#xD;
sustained by the individual as a result of the refusal or failure, but in&#xD;
no case shall a person entitled to recovery receive less than the sum of&#xD;
$1,000”).&#xD;
18                          FAA v. COOPER&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
                               D&#xD;
  Finally, respondent argues that excluding damages for&#xD;
mental and emotional harm would lead to absurd results.&#xD;
Persons suffering relatively minor pecuniary loss would&#xD;
be entitled to recover $1,000, while others suffering only&#xD;
severe and debilitating mental or emotional distress would&#xD;
get nothing. See Brief for Respondent 33–35.&#xD;
  Contrary to respondent’s suggestion, however, there is&#xD;
nothing absurd about a scheme that limits the Govern­&#xD;
ment’s Privacy Act liability to harm that can be substanti­&#xD;
ated by proof of tangible economic loss. Respondent in­&#xD;
sists that such a scheme would frustrate the Privacy Act’s&#xD;
remedial purpose, but that ignores the fact that, by delib­&#xD;
erately refusing to authorize general damages, Congress&#xD;
intended to cabin relief, not to maximize it.12&#xD;
——————&#xD;
   12 Despite its rhetoric, the dissent does not dispute most of the steps&#xD;
&#xD;
in our analysis. For example, although the dissent belittles the sover­&#xD;
eign immunity canon, the dissent does not call for its abandonment.&#xD;
See post, at 2–3. Nor does the dissent point out any error in our under­&#xD;
standing of the canon’s meaning. See ibid. The dissent acknowledges&#xD;
that statutes and judicial opinions sometimes use the term “actual&#xD;
damages” to mean pecuniary harm, see post, at 5, and that determining&#xD;
its meaning in a particular statute requires consideration of context,&#xD;
see ibid. In addition, the dissent concedes—as it must in light of our&#xD;
reasoning in Doe v. Chao, 540 U. S. 614 (2004)—that the common law&#xD;
of defamation has relevance in construing the term “actual damages” in&#xD;
the Privacy Act. See post, at 7–9.&#xD;
   The dissent’s argument thus boils down to this: The text and purpose&#xD;
of the Privacy Act make it clear beyond any reasonable dispute that the&#xD;
term “actual damages,” as used in the Act, means compensatory dam­&#xD;
ages for all proven harm and not just damages for pecuniary harm.&#xD;
The dissent reasons that, because the Act seeks to prevent pecuniary&#xD;
and nonpecuniary harm, Congress must have intended to authorize the&#xD;
recovery of money damages from the Federal Government for both&#xD;
types of harm. This inference is plausible, but it surely is not unavoid­&#xD;
able. The Act deters violations of its substantive provisions in other&#xD;
ways—for instance, by permitting recovery for economic injury; by&#xD;
imposing criminal sanctions for some violations, see 5 U. S. C. §552a(i);&#xD;
and possibly by allowing for injunctive relief under the Administrative&#xD;
                     Cite as: 566 U. S. ____ (2012)                    19&#xD;
&#xD;
                          Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
                        *     *    *&#xD;
  In sum, applying traditional rules of construction, we&#xD;
hold that the Privacy Act does not unequivocally authorize&#xD;
an award of damages for mental or emotional distress.&#xD;
Accordingly, the Act does not waive the Federal Govern­&#xD;
ment’s sovereign immunity from liability for such harms.&#xD;
We therefore reverse the judgment of the United States&#xD;
Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit and remand the&#xD;
case for further proceedings consistent with this opinion.&#xD;
&#xD;
                                                      It is so ordered.&#xD;
&#xD;
  JUSTICE KAGAN took no part in the consideration or&#xD;
decision of this case.&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
——————&#xD;
Procedure Act (APA), 5 U. S. C. §§702, 706; see Doe, supra, at 619, n. 1&#xD;
(noting that the absence of equitable relief in suits under&#xD;
§§552a(g)(1)(C) or (D) may be explained by the availability of such relief&#xD;
under the APA).&#xD;
                 Cite as: 566 U. S. ____ (2012)            1&#xD;
&#xD;
                   SOTOMAYOR, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES&#xD;
                         _________________&#xD;
&#xD;
                         No. 10–1024&#xD;
                         _________________&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
   FEDERAL AVIATION ADMINISTRATION, ET AL., &#xD;
&#xD;
      PETITIONERS v. STANMORE CAWTHON &#xD;
&#xD;
                   COOPER &#xD;
&#xD;
 ON WRIT OF CERTIORARI TO THE UNITED STATES COURT OF&#xD;
&#xD;
            APPEALS FOR THE NINTH CIRCUIT&#xD;
&#xD;
                       [March 28, 2012]&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
   JUSTICE SOTOMAYOR, with whom JUSTICE GINSBURG&#xD;
and JUSTICE BREYER join, dissenting.&#xD;
   Congress enacted the Privacy Act of 1974 for the stated&#xD;
purpose of safeguarding individual privacy against Gov-&#xD;
ernment invasion. To that end, the Act provides a civil&#xD;
remedy entitling individuals adversely affected by certain&#xD;
agency misconduct to recover “actual damages” sustained&#xD;
as a result of the unlawful action.&#xD;
   Today the Court holds that “actual damages” is limited&#xD;
to pecuniary loss. Consequently, individuals can no longer&#xD;
recover what our precedents and common sense under-&#xD;
stand to be the primary, and often only, damages sus-&#xD;
tained as a result of an invasion of privacy, namely mental&#xD;
or emotional distress. That result is at odds with the text,&#xD;
structure, and drafting history of the Act. And it cripples&#xD;
the Act’s core purpose of redressing and deterring viola-&#xD;
tions of privacy interests. I respectfully dissent.&#xD;
                              I&#xD;
  The majority concludes that “actual damages” in the&#xD;
civil-remedies provision of the Privacy Act allows recovery&#xD;
for pecuniary loss alone. But it concedes that its interpre-&#xD;
tation is not compelled by the plain text of the statute or&#xD;
otherwise required by any other traditional tool of statu-&#xD;
2                      FAA v. COOPER&#xD;
&#xD;
                   SOTOMAYOR, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
tory interpretation. And it candidly acknowledges that a&#xD;
contrary reading is not “inconceivable.” Ante, at 14. Yet be-&#xD;
cause it considers its reading of “actual damages” to be&#xD;
“plausible,” the majority contends that the canon of sover-&#xD;
eign immunity requires adoption of an interpretation most&#xD;
favorable to the Government. Ibid.&#xD;
   The canon simply cannot bear the weight the majority&#xD;
ascribes it. “The sovereign immunity canon is just that—a&#xD;
canon of construction. It is a tool for interpreting the law,&#xD;
and we have never held that it displaces the other tra-&#xD;
ditional tools of statutory construction.” Richlin Security&#xD;
Service Co. v. Chertoff, 553 U. S. 571, 589 (2008) (opinion&#xD;
of ALITO, J.). Here, traditional tools of statutory construc-&#xD;
tion—the statute’s text, structure, drafting history, and&#xD;
purpose—provide a clear answer: The term “actual dam-&#xD;
ages” permits recovery for all injuries established by&#xD;
competent evidence in the record, whether pecuniary or&#xD;
nonpecuniary, and so encompasses damages for mental&#xD;
and emotional distress. There is no need to seek refuge in&#xD;
a canon of construction, see id., at 589–590 (declining to&#xD;
rely on canon as there is “no ambiguity left for us to con-&#xD;
strue” after application of “traditional tools of statutory&#xD;
interpretation and considerations of stare decisis”), much&#xD;
less one that has been used so haphazardly in the Court’s&#xD;
history, see United States v. Nordic Village, Inc., 503 U. S.&#xD;
30, 42 (1992) (Stevens, J., dissenting) (canon is “nothing&#xD;
but a judge-made rule that is sometimes favored and&#xD;
sometimes disfavored”) (collecting cases).&#xD;
   It bears emphasis that we have said repeatedly that,&#xD;
while “we should not take it upon ourselves to extend&#xD;
the waiver [of sovereign immunity] beyond that which&#xD;
Congress intended,” “[n]either . . . should we assume the&#xD;
authority to narrow the waiver that Congress intended.”&#xD;
United States v. Kubrick, 444 U. S. 111, 117–118 (1979)&#xD;
(emphasis added). See also, e.g., Block v. Neal, 460 U. S.&#xD;
289, 298 (1983) (“The exemption of the sovereign from suit&#xD;
                  Cite as: 566 U. S. ____ (2012)            3&#xD;
&#xD;
                   SOTOMAYOR, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
involves hardship enough where consent has been with-&#xD;
held. We are not to add to its rigor by refinement of con-&#xD;
struction where consent has been announced” (internal&#xD;
quotation marks omitted)). In the Privacy Act, Congress&#xD;
expressly authorized recovery of “actual damages” for&#xD;
certain intentional or willful agency misconduct. The&#xD;
Court should not “as a self-constituted guardian of the&#xD;
Treasury import immunity back into a statute designed to&#xD;
limit it.” Indian Towing Co. v. United States, 350 U. S. 61,&#xD;
69 (1955).&#xD;
                              II&#xD;
&#xD;
                              A&#xD;
&#xD;
   “In a statutory construction case, the beginning point&#xD;
must be the language of the statute, and when a statute&#xD;
speaks with clarity to an issue judicial inquiry into the&#xD;
statute’s meaning, in all but the most extraordinary cir-&#xD;
cumstance, is finished.” Estate of Cowart v. Nicklos Drill-&#xD;
ing Co., 505 U. S. 469, 475 (1992). The language of the&#xD;
civil-remedies provision of the Privacy Act is clear.&#xD;
   At the time Congress drafted the Act, Black’s Law Dic-&#xD;
tionary defined “actual damages” as “[r]eal, substantial&#xD;
and just damages, or the amount awarded to a complain-&#xD;
ant in compensation for his actual and real loss or in-&#xD;
jury” and as “[s]ynonymous with ‘compensatory damages.’ ”&#xD;
Black’s Law Dictionary 467 (rev. 4th ed. 1968) (hereinafter&#xD;
Black’s). The majority claims this is a “general” and “no-&#xD;
tably circular” definition, ante, at 7, but it is unclear why.&#xD;
The definition is plain enough: “Actual damages” compen-&#xD;
sate for actual injury, and thus the term is synonymous&#xD;
with compensatory damages. See Black’s 467 (defining&#xD;
“compensatory damages” as damages that “will compen-&#xD;
sate the injured party for the injury sustained, and noth-&#xD;
ing more; such as will simply make good or replace the&#xD;
4                           FAA v. COOPER&#xD;
&#xD;
                       SOTOMAYOR, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
loss caused by the wrong or injury”).1 There is nothing&#xD;
circular about that definition.2 It is the definition this&#xD;
Court adopted more than a century ago when we recog-&#xD;
nized that “[c]ompensatory damages and actual damages&#xD;
mean the same thing; that is, that the damages shall be&#xD;
the result of the injury alleged and proved, and that the&#xD;
amount awarded shall be precisely commensurate with&#xD;
the injury suffered.” Birdsall v. Coolidge, 93 U. S. 64&#xD;
(1876). It is the definition embraced in current legal&#xD;
dictionaries. See Black’s 445 (9th ed. 2009) (defining&#xD;
“actual damages” as “[a]n amount awarded to a complain-&#xD;
ant to compensate for a proven injury or loss; damages&#xD;
that repay actual losses.—Also termed compensatory&#xD;
damages; tangible damages; real damages” (italics omit-&#xD;
ted)). And it is the definition that accords with the plain&#xD;
and ordinary meaning of the term. See Webster’s Third&#xD;
New International Dictionary 22, 571 (2002) (defining&#xD;
“actual” as “existing in fact or reality” and “damages” as&#xD;
“compensation or satisfaction imposed by law for a wrong&#xD;
or injury caused by a violation of a legal right”). Thus,&#xD;
both as a term of art and in its plain meaning, “actual&#xD;
damages” connotes compensation for proven injuries or&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  1 Black’s Law Dictionary also defined “actual damages” as synony-&#xD;
&#xD;
mous with “general damages.” Black’s 467. While “general damages”&#xD;
has a specialized meaning of presumed damages in libel and slander&#xD;
cases, see n. 4, infra, it more generally can mean damages that “did in&#xD;
fact result from the wrong, directly and proximately.” Black’s 468.&#xD;
  2 The majority declares the definition circular because “defining ‘ac-&#xD;
&#xD;
tual’ damages by reference to ‘actual’ injury is hardly helpful when our&#xD;
task is to determine what Congress meant by ‘actual.’ ” Ante, at 9, n. 4.&#xD;
“Actual injury,” however, is far from an unhelpful reference. This&#xD;
Court already has recognized in the defamation context that “actual&#xD;
injury is not limited to out-of-pocket loss.” Gertz v. Robert Welch, Inc.,&#xD;
418 U. S. 323, 350 (1974). That accords with the definitions of the&#xD;
terms. See Black’s 53, 924 (defining “actual” as “[r]eal; substantial;&#xD;
existing presently in act, having a valid objective existence as opposed&#xD;
to that which is merely theoretical or possible,” and “injury” as “[a]ny&#xD;
wrong or damage done to another”).&#xD;
                      Cite as: 566 U. S. ____ (2012)                     5&#xD;
&#xD;
                       SOTOMAYOR, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
losses. Nothing in the use of that phrase indicates proven&#xD;
injuries need be pecuniary in nature.&#xD;
  The majority discards all this on the asserted ground&#xD;
that “the precise meaning of the term ‘changes with the&#xD;
specific statute in which it is found.’ ” Ante, at 7 (quoting&#xD;
622 F. 3d 1016, 1029 (CA9 2010)). Context, of course, is&#xD;
relevant to statutory interpretation; it may provide clues&#xD;
that Congress did not employ a word or phrase in its&#xD;
ordinary meaning. That well-established interpretive rule&#xD;
cannot, however, render irrelevant—as the majority would&#xD;
have it—the ordinary meaning of “actual damages.”&#xD;
  Moreover, the authority the majority cites for its claim&#xD;
that “actual damages” has no fixed meaning undermines—&#xD;
rather than supports—its holding. Each cited authority&#xD;
involves either a statute in which Congress expressly&#xD;
directed that compensation be measured in strictly eco-&#xD;
nomic terms, or else a statute (e.g., the Copyright Act of&#xD;
1909) in which economic loss is the natural and probable&#xD;
consequence of a violation of the defined legal interest.3&#xD;
Neither factor is present here. Notably absent from the&#xD;
Privacy Act is any provision so much as hinting that “ac-&#xD;
tual damages” should be limited to economic loss. And&#xD;
while “ ‘ “hurt feelings” over the nature of the [copyright]&#xD;
infringement’ ” may “have no place in the actual damages&#xD;
calculus” under the Copyright Act of 1909, ante, at 8 (quot-&#xD;
ing in parenthetical Mackie v. Rieser, 296 F. 3d 909, 917&#xD;
(CA9 2002)), the majority provides no basis for concluding&#xD;
that “hurt feelings” are equally invalid in an Act con-&#xD;
cerned with safeguarding individual privacy. Thus, while&#xD;
context is no doubt relevant, the majority’s cited authority&#xD;
does little to help its cause in the stated context of this&#xD;
statute.&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  3 See 28 U. S. C. §2674; 17 U. S. C. §1009(d)(1); 18 U. S. C. §2318(e)(3)&#xD;
&#xD;
(2006 ed., Supp. IV); 17 U. S. C. §101(b) (1970 ed.); 15 U. S. C. §78bb(a)&#xD;
(2006 ed., Supp. IV).&#xD;
6                      FAA v. COOPER&#xD;
&#xD;
                   SOTOMAYOR, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
                               B&#xD;
   Indeed, the relevant statutory context—the substantive&#xD;
provisions whose breach may trigger suit under the civil-&#xD;
remedies provision—only reinforces the ordinary meaning&#xD;
of “actual damages.”&#xD;
   Congress established substantive duties in the Act that&#xD;
are expressly designed to prevent agency conduct result-&#xD;
ing in intangible harms to the individual. The Act re-&#xD;
quires agencies to “establish appropriate administrative,&#xD;
technical, and physical safeguards” to ensure against&#xD;
security breaches that could result in “substantial harm,&#xD;
embarrassment, inconvenience, or unfairness to any indi-&#xD;
vidual.” 5 U. S. C. §552a(e)(10). It also requires agencies&#xD;
to “maintain all records” used in making a determination&#xD;
about an individual in a manner that is “reasonably neces-&#xD;
sary to assure fairness to the individual in the determina-&#xD;
tion.” §552a(e)(5). Thus an agency violates the terms of&#xD;
the Act if it fails, e.g., to maintain safeguards protecting&#xD;
against “embarrassment”; there is no additional require-&#xD;
ment that the pocketbook be implicated. An agency’s&#xD;
intentional or willful violation of those duties triggers&#xD;
liability for “actual damages” under §552a(g)(4) in the&#xD;
event of an adverse impact. §§552a(g)(1)(C)–(D), (g)(4).&#xD;
   Adopting a reading of “actual damages” that permits&#xD;
recovery for pecuniary loss alone creates a disconnect&#xD;
between the Act’s substantive and remedial provisions. It&#xD;
allows a swath of Government violations to go unreme-&#xD;
died: A federal agency could intentionally or willfully forgo&#xD;
establishing safeguards to protect against embarrassment&#xD;
and no successful private action could be taken against it&#xD;
for the harm Congress identified. Only an interpretation&#xD;
of “actual damages” that permits recovery for nonpecuni-&#xD;
ary harms harmonizes the Act’s substantive and remedial&#xD;
provisions. Robinson v. Shell Oil Co., 519 U. S. 337, 341&#xD;
                     Cite as: 566 U. S. ____ (2012)                     7&#xD;
&#xD;
                       SOTOMAYOR, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
(1997) (statutory interpretation must consider “the&#xD;
broader context of the statute as a whole”).4&#xD;
  The majority draws a different conclusion from the sub-&#xD;
stantive provisions of the Privacy Act. It (correctly) in-&#xD;
fers from them that the Act “serves interests similar to&#xD;
those protected by defamation and privacy torts.” Ante,&#xD;
at 9. It then points to our observation in Doe v. Chao, 540&#xD;
U. S. 614, 625 (2004), that the Act’s civil-remedies provi-&#xD;
sion “parallels” the remedial scheme for the common-law&#xD;
torts of defamation per quod, which permitted recovery&#xD;
of “general damages” (i.e., presumed damages) only if a&#xD;
plaintiff first establishes “special damages” (i.e., monetary&#xD;
loss).5 Ante, at 10. That “parallel,” the majority con-&#xD;
cludes, “suggests the possibility that Congress intended&#xD;
the term ‘actual damages’ in the Act to mean special dam-&#xD;
ages.” Ante, at 11.&#xD;
  The majority reads too much into Doe. At issue in that&#xD;
——————&#xD;
   4 It bears noting that the Privacy Act does not authorize injunctive&#xD;
&#xD;
relief when a suit is maintained under 5 U. S. C. §§552a(g)(1)(C) and&#xD;
(D). Rather, injunctive relief is available under the Act only for a&#xD;
limited category of suits: suits to amend a record and suits for access to&#xD;
a record. See §§552a(g)(2), (g)(3). Thus an individual who, like peti-&#xD;
tioner, brings suit under subparagraph (g)(1)(C) or (D) for an inten-&#xD;
tional or willful violation of the Act will be without a remedy under&#xD;
the majority’s reading of “actual damages.”&#xD;
   5 As the majority notes, “general damages” at common law refers to&#xD;
&#xD;
damages “presumed” to accrue from the violation of the legally pro-&#xD;
tected right. No proof of actual injury was required. See D. Dobbs,&#xD;
Law of Remedies §7.2, p. 513 (1973) (hereinafter Dobbs); Doe, 540 U. S.,&#xD;
at 621. “Special damages,” in contrast, “meant monetary loss.” Dobbs §7.2,&#xD;
at 512; Doe, 540 U. S., at 625. Common-law defamation actions falling&#xD;
within the rubric of defamation per se allowed successful plaintiffs to&#xD;
recover “general damages.” See Dobbs §7.2, at 513; Doe, 540 U. S., at&#xD;
621. This stood in contrast to actions sounding in defamation per quod,&#xD;
which permitted recovery only if the plaintiff established “special&#xD;
damages.” See Dobbs, §7.2 at 512; Doe, 540 U. S., at 625. Even in&#xD;
defamation per quod cases, a plaintiff could recover nonpecuniary&#xD;
injuries upon establishing some pecuniary loss. See Dobbs §7.2, at 521;&#xD;
Doe, 540 U. S., at 625. See also ante, at 10.&#xD;
8                           FAA v. COOPER&#xD;
&#xD;
                       SOTOMAYOR, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
case was the question whether the Act’s civil-suit provi-&#xD;
sion authorized recovery of a guaranteed minimum award&#xD;
of $1,000 absent proof of some “actual damages.” The&#xD;
Court answered in the negative, and in the course of doing&#xD;
so replied to petitioner’s argument that there was “some-&#xD;
thing peculiar in offering some guaranteed damages . . .&#xD;
only to those plaintiffs who can demonstrate actual dam-&#xD;
ages.” 540 U. S., at 625. Although the Court cited the&#xD;
Act’s parallels to defamation per quod actions in noting&#xD;
that nothing was “peculiar” about the Act’s remedial&#xD;
scheme, Doe did not take the further step of deciding that&#xD;
“actual damages” means economic loss alone. Indeed, it&#xD;
expressly reserved that question. Id., at 627, n. 12.&#xD;
  The majority, moreover, is wrong to conclude that the&#xD;
Act’s parallels with defamation per quod actions suggest&#xD;
Congress intended “actual damages” to mean “special&#xD;
damages.” Quite the opposite. The fact that Congress&#xD;
“would probably have known about” defamation per quod&#xD;
actions, id., at 625, makes it all the more significant that&#xD;
Congress did not write “special damages” in the civil-&#xD;
remedies provision. This Court is typically not in the&#xD;
business of substituting words we think Congress in-&#xD;
tended to use for words Congress in fact used. Yet that is&#xD;
precisely what the majority does when it rewrites “actual&#xD;
damages” to mean “special damages.”6 In sum, the statu-&#xD;
tory context, and in particular the Act’s substantive provi-&#xD;
sions, confirms the ordinary meaning of “actual damages.”&#xD;
Although the Act shares parallels with common-law defa-&#xD;
mation torts, such analogies do not warrant a reading of&#xD;
&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  6 The majority cites a collection of lower court opinions that have used&#xD;
&#xD;
“actual damages” in place of “special damages” to note that Congress&#xD;
would not have been alone in using the former term to refer to the&#xD;
latter. Ante, at 11–12. But that a handful of lower courts on occasion&#xD;
have been imprecise in their terminology provides no basis to assume&#xD;
the Legislature has been equally careless in the text of a statute.&#xD;
                     Cite as: 566 U. S. ____ (2012)                     9&#xD;
&#xD;
                       SOTOMAYOR, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
the phrase that is at odds with the statute’s plain text.7&#xD;
                             C&#xD;
   An uncodified provision of the Act, tied to the Act’s&#xD;
drafting history, also reinforces the ordinary meaning of&#xD;
“actual damages.” As the majority notes, prior to reconcil-&#xD;
iation, the Senate and House bills contained civil-remedies&#xD;
provisions that were different in a critical respect: The&#xD;
Senate bill allowed for the recovery of “actual and general&#xD;
damages,” whereas the House bill allowed for the recovery&#xD;
of “actual damages” alone.8 In the reconciliation process,&#xD;
the provision for “general damages” was dropped and an&#xD;
uncodified section of the Act was amended to require the&#xD;
newly established Privacy Protection Study Commission to&#xD;
consider, among its other jobs, “whether the Federal Gov-&#xD;
ernment should be liable for general damages incurred by&#xD;
an individual as the result of a willful or intentional vio-&#xD;
lation of the provisions of sections 552a(g)(1)(C) or (D).”&#xD;
§5(c)(2)(B)(iii), 88 Stat. 1907; see also Doe, 540 U. S.,&#xD;
at 622.&#xD;
   As the Court explained in Doe, “[t]he deletion of ‘general&#xD;
damages’ from the bill is fairly seen . . . as a deliberate&#xD;
elimination of any possibility of imputing harm and&#xD;
awarding presumed damages.” Id., at 623; see also id., at&#xD;
——————&#xD;
   7 There is yet another flaw in the majority’s reasoning. At common&#xD;
&#xD;
law a plaintiff who successfully established “special damages” in an&#xD;
action for defamation per quod could proceed to recover damages for&#xD;
emotional and mental distress. See ante, at 10; n. 5, supra. If “Con-&#xD;
gress intended the term ‘actual damages’ in the Act to mean special&#xD;
damages,” ante, at 11, then an individual who successfully establishes&#xD;
some pecuniary loss from a violation of the Act—presumably as trivial&#xD;
as the cost of a bottle of Tylenol—should be permitted to recover for&#xD;
emotional and mental distress. The majority, of course, does not accept&#xD;
that result, and its piecemeal embrace of the common law undermines&#xD;
its assertion that Congress intended “special damages” in place of&#xD;
“actual damages.”&#xD;
   8 See S. 3418, 93d Cong., 2d Sess., §303(c)(1) (1974); H. R. 16373, 93d&#xD;
&#xD;
Cong., 2d Sess., §3 (1974).&#xD;
10                      FAA v. COOPER&#xD;
&#xD;
                    SOTOMAYOR, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
622, n. 5 (“Congress explicitly rejected the proposal to&#xD;
make presumed damages available for Privacy Act viola-&#xD;
tions”). The elimination of presumed damages from the&#xD;
bill can only reasonably imply that what Congress left&#xD;
behind—“actual damages”—comprised damages that are&#xD;
not presumed, i.e., damages proven by competent evidence&#xD;
in the record. See Gertz v. Robert Welch, Inc., 418 U. S.&#xD;
323, 349–350 (1974) (distinguishing in defamation context&#xD;
between presumed damages and damages for actual inju-&#xD;
ries sustained by competent evidence in the record, which&#xD;
include “impairment of reputation and standing in the&#xD;
community, personal humiliation, and mental anguish&#xD;
and suffering”); Carey v. Piphus, 435 U. S. 247, 262–264&#xD;
(1978) (distinguishing between presumed damages and&#xD;
proven damages for mental and emotional distress).&#xD;
   Rather than view the deletion of general damages (pre-&#xD;
sumed damages) as leaving the converse (proven dam-&#xD;
ages), the majority supposes that the deletion leaves only a&#xD;
subset of proven damages—those of an economic nature,&#xD;
i.e., “special damages.” Once again, however, the major-&#xD;
ity’s insistence that “Congress intended ‘actual damages’ in&#xD;
the Privacy Act to mean special damages for proven pecu-&#xD;
niary loss,” ante, at 13, finds no basis in the statutory text,&#xD;
see supra, at 8. And its response to the conclusion that&#xD;
Congress retained recovery for proven damages when it&#xD;
eliminated presumed damages is singularly unsatisfying.&#xD;
The majority declares such a conclusion “flawed” because&#xD;
“general damages” “includes compensation for proven&#xD;
injuries as well,” so that “what distinguishes [general]&#xD;
damages, whether proved or not, from the only other&#xD;
category of compensatory damages available in the rele-&#xD;
vant common-law suits is the type of harm” the term&#xD;
encompasses—which the majority takes to be emotional&#xD;
harm alone. Ante, at 15–16. That assertion is defective on&#xD;
two scores. First, a plaintiff ’s ability to present proof of&#xD;
injury in a defamation per se action (and to recover for&#xD;
                     Cite as: 566 U. S. ____ (2012)                   11&#xD;
&#xD;
                       SOTOMAYOR, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
such proven injury) does not alter the definition of “gen-&#xD;
eral damages,” which we already explained in Doe means&#xD;
“presumed damages.” 540 U. S., at 621; see also id., at&#xD;
623; n. 5, supra. Second, “general damages” is not limited&#xD;
to a “type” of harm. The majority’s contrary assertion that&#xD;
the term permits recovery only for emotional “types” of&#xD;
harm overlooks the fact that “general damages are partly&#xD;
based on the belief that the plaintiff will suffer unprovable&#xD;
pecuniary losses.” Dobbs §7.2, at 514 (emphasis added). It&#xD;
thus was established at common law that in a defamation&#xD;
per se action, “the plaintiff is usually free to prove what-&#xD;
ever actual pecuniary loss he can,” and “the jury may be&#xD;
permitted to view the actual pecuniary loss proven as the&#xD;
tip of the iceberg, assume that there is still more un-&#xD;
proven, and award damage accordingly.” Ibid.&#xD;
   At its core, the majority opinion relies on the following&#xD;
syllogism: The common law employed two terms of art in&#xD;
defamation actions. Because Congress excluded recovery&#xD;
for “general damages,” it must have meant to retain recov-&#xD;
ery only for “special damages.” That syllogism, of course,&#xD;
ignores that there is another category of damages. It is&#xD;
the very category Congress used in the text of the Privacy&#xD;
Act: “Actual damages.” However much Congress may&#xD;
have drawn “parallels,” ante, at 10, between the Act and&#xD;
the common-law tort of defamation, the fact remains that&#xD;
Congress expressly choose not to use the words “special&#xD;
damages.”9&#xD;
                            D&#xD;
  I turn finally to the statute’s purpose, for “[a]s in all&#xD;
cases of statutory interpretation, our task is to interpret&#xD;
——————&#xD;
  9 The majority cites the conclusions of the Privacy Protection Study&#xD;
&#xD;
Commission in support of its interpretation of “actual damages.” The&#xD;
majority rightfully does not claim this piece of postenactment, extratex-&#xD;
tual material is due any deference; nor do I find its unelaborated&#xD;
conclusions persuasive.&#xD;
12                     FAA v. COOPER&#xD;
&#xD;
                   SOTOMAYOR, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
the words of th[e] statut[e] in light of the purposes Con-&#xD;
gress sought to serve.” Chapman v. Houston Welfare&#xD;
Rights Organization, 441 U. S. 600, 608 (1979); see also&#xD;
Dolan v. Postal Service, 546 U. S. 481, 486 (2006) (“Inter-&#xD;
pretation of a word or phrase depends upon reading the&#xD;
whole statutory text, considering the purpose and context&#xD;
of the statute, and consulting any precedents or authori-&#xD;
ties that inform the analysis”). The purposes of the Priv-&#xD;
acy Act could not be more explicit, and they are consistent&#xD;
with interpreting “actual damages” according to its ordi-&#xD;
nary meaning.&#xD;
   “The historical context of the Act is important to an&#xD;
understanding of its remedial purposes. In 1974, Con-&#xD;
gress was concerned with curbing the illegal surveillance&#xD;
and investigation of individuals by federal agencies that&#xD;
had been exposed during the Watergate scandal.” Dept.&#xD;
of Justice, Office of Privacy and Civil Liberties, Overview of&#xD;
the Privacy Act 4 (2010). In particular, Congress recog-&#xD;
nized that “the increasing use of computers and sophisti-&#xD;
cated information technology . . . has greatly magnified&#xD;
the harm to individual privacy that can occur from any&#xD;
collection, maintenance, use, or dissemination of personal&#xD;
information.” §2(a), 88 Stat. 1896. Identifying the right to&#xD;
privacy as “a personal and fundamental right,” Congress&#xD;
found it “necessary and proper” to enact the Privacy Act&#xD;
“in order to protect the privacy of individuals identified in&#xD;
information systems maintained by Federal agencies.”&#xD;
Ibid.&#xD;
   Congress explained that the “purpose of this Act is to&#xD;
provide certain safeguards for an individual against an&#xD;
invasion of personal privacy by requiring Federal agen-&#xD;
cies, except as otherwise provided by law, to,” inter alia,&#xD;
“be subject to civil suit for any damages which occur as a&#xD;
result of willful or intentional action which violates any&#xD;
individual’s rights under this Act.” §2(b)(6), ibid. (empha-&#xD;
sis added). That statement is an explicit reference to suits&#xD;
                 Cite as: 566 U. S. ____ (2012)           13&#xD;
&#xD;
                   SOTOMAYOR, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
brought under §552a(g)(4); no other provision speaks to a&#xD;
civil suit based on “willful or intentional” agency miscon-&#xD;
duct. It signals unmistakably congressional recognition&#xD;
that the civil-remedies provision is integral to realizing&#xD;
the Act’s purposes.&#xD;
  Reading “actual damages” to permit recovery for any&#xD;
injury established by competent evidence in the record—&#xD;
pecuniary or not—best effectuates the statute’s basic&#xD;
purpose. Although some privacy invasions no doubt result&#xD;
in economic loss, we have recognized time and again that&#xD;
the primary form of injuries is nonpecuniary, and includes&#xD;
mental distress and personal humiliation. See Time, Inc.&#xD;
v. Hill, 385 U. S. 374, 385, n. 9 (1967) (“In the ‘right of&#xD;
privacy’ cases the primary damage is the mental dis-&#xD;
tress”); see also Gertz, 418 U. S., at 350 (“[A]ctual injury”&#xD;
in defamatory falsehood cases “is not limited to out-of-&#xD;
pocket loss. Indeed, the more customary types of actual&#xD;
harm inflicted by defamatory falsehood include impair-&#xD;
ment of reputation and standing in the community, per-&#xD;
sonal humiliation, and mental anguish and suffering”).&#xD;
Accord, 2 Dobbs §7.1.(1), at 259 (2d ed. 1993) (privacy is a&#xD;
dignitary interest, and “in a great many of the cases” in&#xD;
which the interest is invaded “the only harm is the affront&#xD;
to the plaintiff ’s dignity as a human being, the damage to&#xD;
his self-image, and the resulting mental distress”). That&#xD;
accords with common sense.&#xD;
  In interpreting the civil-remedies provision, we must not&#xD;
forget Congress enacted the Privacy Act to protect pri-&#xD;
vacy. The majority’s reading of “actual damages” renders&#xD;
the remedial provision impotent in the face of concededly&#xD;
unlawful agency action whenever the injury is solely&#xD;
nonpecuniary. That result is patently at odds with Con-&#xD;
gress’ stated purpose. The majority, however, does not&#xD;
grapple with the ramifications of its opinion. It acknowl-&#xD;
edges the suggestion that its holding leads to absurd&#xD;
results as it allows individuals suffering relatively minor&#xD;
14                     FAA v. COOPER&#xD;
&#xD;
                   SOTOMAYOR, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
pecuniary losses to recover $1,000 while others suffering&#xD;
severe mental anguish to recover nothing. But it con-&#xD;
cludes that “there is nothing absurd about a scheme that&#xD;
limits the Government’s Privacy Act liability to harm that&#xD;
can be substantiated by proof of tangible economic loss.”&#xD;
Ante, at 18. Perhaps; it is certainly within Congress’&#xD;
prerogative to enact the statute the majority envisions,&#xD;
namely one that seeks to safeguard against invasions of&#xD;
privacy without remedying the primary harm that results&#xD;
from invasions of privacy. The problem for the majority is&#xD;
that one looks in vain for any indication in the text of the&#xD;
statute before us that Congress intended such a result.&#xD;
Nowhere in the Privacy Act does Congress so much as hint&#xD;
that it views a $5 hit to the pocketbook as more worthy of&#xD;
remedy than debilitating mental distress, and the major-&#xD;
ity’s contrary assumption discounts the gravity of emo-&#xD;
tional harm caused by an invasion of the personal integ-&#xD;
rity that privacy protects.&#xD;
                        *    *     *&#xD;
  After today, no matter how debilitating and substantial&#xD;
the resulting mental anguish, an individual harmed by&#xD;
a federal agency’s intentional or willful violation of the&#xD;
Privacy Act will be left without a remedy unless he or she&#xD;
is able to prove pecuniary harm. That is not the result&#xD;
Congress intended when it enacted an Act with the ex-&#xD;
press purpose of safeguarding individual privacy against&#xD;
Government invasion. And it is not a result remotely&#xD;
suggested by anything in the text, structure, or history of&#xD;
the Act. For those reasons, I respectfully dissent.&#xD;
&lt;/pre&gt;</opinion>