<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><opinion id="799992" path="/scotus/56NY/bell-v-thompson/" sha1="cd280b755494e37449b1cf4f7b2eb3370b996fa3" court="Supreme Court of the United States" download_URL="http://www.supremecourt.gov/opinions/opinions.aspx" time_retrieved="2012-05-17 03:19:28+00:00" date_filed="2005-06-27" precedential_status="Published" local_path="pdf/2005/06/27/04-514.pdf" docket_number="04-514" federal_cite_one="545 U.S. 794" case_name="Bell v. Thompson" nature_of_suit="" source="manual input" blocked="False" date_blocked="None" extracted_by_ocr="False" cited_by="172305,400,1086867,1086381,1086188,931123">&lt;pre class="inline"&gt;(Slip Opinion)              OCTOBER TERM, 2004                                       1&#xD;
&#xD;
                                       Syllabus&#xD;
&#xD;
         NOTE: Where it is feasible, a syllabus (headnote) will be released, as is&#xD;
       being done in connection with this case, at the time the opinion is issued.&#xD;
       The syllabus constitutes no part of the opinion of the Court but has been&#xD;
       prepared by the Reporter of Decisions for the convenience of the reader.&#xD;
       See United States v. Detroit Timber &amp; Lumber Co., 200 U. S. 321, 337.&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES&#xD;
&#xD;
                                       Syllabus&#xD;
&#xD;
                  BELL, WARDEN v. THOMPSON&#xD;
&#xD;
CERTIORARI TO THE UNITED STATES COURT OF APPEALS FOR&#xD;
                  THE SIXTH CIRCUIT&#xD;
&#xD;
       No. 04–514.      Argued April 26, 2005—Decided June 27, 2005&#xD;
After respondent Thompson was convicted of murder and sentenced to&#xD;
  death, Tennessee state courts denied postconviction relief on his&#xD;
  claim that his trial counsel had been ineffective for failing to ade-&#xD;
  quately investigate his mental health. His federal habeas attorneys&#xD;
  subsequently retained psychologist Dr. Sultan, whose report and&#xD;
  deposition contended that Thompson suffered from serious mental&#xD;
  illness at the time of his offense. The District Court dismissed the&#xD;
  petition, but apparently Thompson’s habeas counsel had failed to in-&#xD;
  clude Sultan’s deposition and report in the record. Upholding the&#xD;
  dismissal, the Sixth Circuit, inter alia, found no ineffective assistance&#xD;
  and did not discuss Sultan’s report and deposition in detail. That&#xD;
  court later denied rehearing, but stayed issuance of its mandate&#xD;
  pending disposition of Thompson’s certiorari petition. After this&#xD;
  Court denied certiorari on December 1, 2003, the Sixth Circuit stayed&#xD;
  its mandate again, pending disposition of a petition for rehearing,&#xD;
  which this Court denied on January 20, 2004. A copy of that order&#xD;
  was filed with the Sixth Circuit on January 23, but the court did not&#xD;
  issue its mandate. The State set Thompson’s execution date, and&#xD;
  state and federal proceedings began on his competency to be exe-&#xD;
  cuted. Competency proceedings were pending in the Federal District&#xD;
  Court on June 23, 2004, when the Sixth Circuit issued an amended&#xD;
  opinion in the federal habeas case, vacating the District Court’s ha-&#xD;
  beas judgment and remanding the case for an evidentiary hearing on&#xD;
  the ineffective-assistance claim. The Sixth Circuit supplemented the&#xD;
  record on appeal with Sultan’s deposition and explained that its au-&#xD;
  thority to issue an amended opinion five months after this Court de-&#xD;
  nied rehearing was based on its inherent power to reconsider an opin-&#xD;
  ion before issuance of the mandate.&#xD;
2                        BELL v. THOMPSON&#xD;
&#xD;
                                Syllabus&#xD;
&#xD;
Held: Assuming that Federal Rule of Appellate Procedure 41 authorizes&#xD;
 a stay of a mandate following a denial of certiorari and that a court&#xD;
 may stay the mandate without entering an order, the Sixth Circuit’s&#xD;
 decision to do so here was an abuse of discretion. Pp. 6–19.&#xD;
    (a) This Court need not decide the scope of the court of appeals’&#xD;
 Rule 41 authority to withhold a mandate in order to resolve this case.&#xD;
 Pp. 6–9.&#xD;
    (b) Prominent among the reasons warranting the result here is&#xD;
 that the Sixth Circuit did not release its amended opinion for more&#xD;
 than five months after this Court denied rehearing. The consequence&#xD;
 of delay for the State’s criminal justice system was compounded by&#xD;
 the Sixth Circuit’s failure to issue an order or otherwise give notice to&#xD;
 the parties that it was reconsidering its earlier opinion. The express&#xD;
 terms of the Sixth Circuit’s stay state that the mandate would be&#xD;
 stayed until this Court acted on the rehearing petition. Thus, once&#xD;
 rehearing was denied, the stay dissolved by operation of law. Ten-&#xD;
 nessee, relying on the Sixth Circuit’s earlier orders and this Court’s&#xD;
 certiorari and rehearing denials could assume that the mandate&#xD;
 would issue, especially since Thompson sought no additional stay and&#xD;
 the Sixth Circuit gave no indication that it might be revisting its ear-&#xD;
 lier decision. The latter point is important, for it is an open question&#xD;
 whether a court may exercise its Rule 41(b) authority to extend the&#xD;
 time to issue a mandate through mere inaction. Without a formal&#xD;
 docket entry neither the parties nor this Court had, or have, any way&#xD;
 to know whether the Sixth Circuit had stayed the mandate or simply&#xD;
 made a clerical mistake. That court could have spared the parties&#xD;
 and state judicial system considerable time and resources had it noti-&#xD;
 fied them that it was reviewing its decision. The scheduling of&#xD;
 Thompson’s execution and the resulting competency proceedings&#xD;
 were steps taken in reliance on the assumption that the federal ha-&#xD;
 beas case was final. That assumption was all the more reasonable&#xD;
 because the delay in issuing the mandate took place after this Court&#xD;
 had denied certiorari, which usually signals the end of litigation. See&#xD;
 Fed. Rule App. Proc. 41(d)(2)(D). The fact that the Sixth Circuit had&#xD;
 the opportunity at the rehearing stage to consider the same argu-&#xD;
 ments it eventually adopted in its amended opinion is yet another&#xD;
 factor supporting the determination here. A review of the Sultan&#xD;
 deposition also reinforces this conclusion. While the evidence would&#xD;
 have been relevant to the District Court’s analysis, it is not of such a&#xD;
 character as to warrant the Sixth Circuit’s extraordinary departure&#xD;
 from standard procedures. Finally, by withholding its mandate for&#xD;
 months—based on evidence supporting only an arguable constitu-&#xD;
 tional claim—while the State prepared to carry out Thompson’s sen-&#xD;
 tence, the Sixth Circuit did not accord the appropriate level of respect&#xD;
                     Cite as: 545 U. S. ____ (2005)                  3&#xD;
&#xD;
                               Syllabus&#xD;
&#xD;
  to the State’s judgment that Thompson’s crimes merit the ultimate&#xD;
  punishment. See Calderon v. Thompson, 523 U. S. 538, 554–557.&#xD;
  Pp. 9–19.&#xD;
373 F. 3d 688, reversed.&#xD;
&#xD;
   KENNEDY, J., delivered the opinion of the Court, in which REHNQUIST,&#xD;
C. J., and O’CONNOR, SCALIA, and THOMAS, JJ., joined. BREYER, J., filed&#xD;
a dissenting opinion, in which STEVENS, SOUTER, and GINSBURG, JJ.,&#xD;
joined.&#xD;
                        Cite as: 545 U. S. ____ (2005)                              1&#xD;
&#xD;
                             Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
     NOTICE: This opinion is subject to formal revision before publication in the&#xD;
     preliminary print of the United States Reports. Readers are requested to&#xD;
     notify the Reporter of Decisions, Supreme Court of the United States, Wash-&#xD;
     ington, D. C. 20543, of any typographical or other formal errors, in order&#xD;
     that corrections may be made before the preliminary print goes to press.&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES&#xD;
                                   _________________&#xD;
&#xD;
                                   No. 04–514&#xD;
                                   _________________&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
  RICKY BELL, WARDEN, PETITIONER v. GREGORY&#xD;
                 THOMPSON&#xD;
 ON WRIT OF CERTIORARI TO THE UNITED STATES COURT OF&#xD;
            APPEALS FOR THE SIXTH CIRCUIT&#xD;
                                 [June 27, 2005]&#xD;
&#xD;
  JUSTICE KENNEDY delivered the opinion of the Court.&#xD;
  This case requires us to consider whether, after we had&#xD;
denied certiorari and a petition for rehearing, the Court of&#xD;
Appeals had the power to withhold its mandate for more&#xD;
than five months without entering a formal order. We&#xD;
hold that, even assuming a court may withhold its man-&#xD;
date after the denial of certiorari in some cases, the Court&#xD;
of Appeals’ decision to do so here was an abuse of&#xD;
discretion.&#xD;
                              I&#xD;
   In 1985, Gregory Thompson and Joanna McNamara&#xD;
abducted Brenda Blanton Lane from a store parking lot in&#xD;
Shelbyville, Tennessee. After forcing Lane to drive them&#xD;
to a remote location, Thompson stabbed her to death.&#xD;
Thompson offered no evidence during the guilt phase of&#xD;
trial and was convicted by a jury of first-degree murder.&#xD;
   Thompson’s defense attorneys concentrated their efforts&#xD;
on persuading the sentencing jury that Thompson’s posi-&#xD;
tive qualities and capacity to adjust to prison life provided&#xD;
good reasons for not imposing the death penalty. Before&#xD;
trial, Thompson’s counsel had explored the issue of his&#xD;
2                    BELL v. THOMPSON&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
mental condition. The trial judge referred Thompson to a&#xD;
state-run mental health facility for a 30-day evaluation.&#xD;
The resulting report indicated that Thompson was compe-&#xD;
tent at the time of the offense and at the time of the ex-&#xD;
amination. The defense team retained their own expert,&#xD;
Dr. George Copple, a clinical psychologist. At sentencing&#xD;
Copple testified that Thompson was remorseful and still&#xD;
had the ability to work and contribute while in prison.&#xD;
Thompson presented the character testimony of a number&#xD;
of witnesses, including former high school teachers, his&#xD;
grandparents, and two siblings. Arlene Cajulao, Thomp-&#xD;
son’s girlfriend while he was stationed with the Navy in&#xD;
Hawaii, also testified on his behalf. She claimed that&#xD;
Thompson’s behavior became erratic after he suffered&#xD;
head injuries during an attack by three of his fellow ser-&#xD;
vicemen. In rebuttal the State called Dr. Glenn Watson, a&#xD;
clinical psychologist who led the pretrial evaluation of&#xD;
Thompson’s competence. Watson testified that his exami-&#xD;
nation of Thompson revealed no significant mental illness.&#xD;
   The jury sentenced Thompson to death. His conviction&#xD;
and sentence were affirmed on direct review. State v.&#xD;
Thompson, 768 S. W. 2d 239 (Tenn. 1989), cert. denied,&#xD;
497 U. S. 1031 (1990).&#xD;
   In his state postconviction petition, Thompson claimed&#xD;
his trial counsel had been ineffective for failing to conduct&#xD;
an adequate investigation into his mental health. Thomp-&#xD;
son argued that his earlier head injuries had diminished&#xD;
his mental capacity and that evidence of his condition&#xD;
should have been presented as mitigating evidence during&#xD;
the penalty phase of trial. Under Tennessee law, mental&#xD;
illness that impairs a defendant’s capacity to appreciate the&#xD;
wrongfulness of his conduct or to conform his conduct to the&#xD;
requirements of the law is a mitigating factor in capital&#xD;
sentencing. Tenn. Code Ann. §39–2–203(j)(8) (1982) (re-&#xD;
pealed); §39–13–204(j)(8) (Lexis 2003). The postconviction&#xD;
court denied relief following an evidentiary hearing, and&#xD;
                 Cite as: 545 U. S. ____ (2005)           3&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
the Tennessee Court of Criminal Appeals affirmed.&#xD;
Thompson v. State, 958 S. W. 2d 156 (1997). The Tennes-&#xD;
see Supreme Court denied discretionary review.&#xD;
   Thompson renewed his ineffective-assistance-of-counsel&#xD;
claim on federal habeas. Thompson’s attorneys retained a&#xD;
psychologist, Dr. Faye Sultan, to assist with the proceed-&#xD;
ings. At this point, 13 years had passed since Thompson’s&#xD;
conviction. Sultan examined and interviewed Thompson&#xD;
three times, questioned his family members, and conducted&#xD;
an extensive review of his legal, military, medical, and&#xD;
prison records, App. 12, before diagnosing him as suffering&#xD;
from schizoaffective disorder, bipolar type, id., at 20. She&#xD;
contended that Thompson’s symptoms indicated he was&#xD;
“suffering serious mental illness at the time of the 1985&#xD;
offense for which he has been convicted and sentenced.&#xD;
This mental illness would have substantially impaired Mr.&#xD;
Thompson’s ability to conform his conduct to the require-&#xD;
ments of the law.” Ibid. Sultan prepared an expert report&#xD;
on Thompson’s behalf and was also deposed by the State.&#xD;
   In February 2000, the United States District Court for&#xD;
the Eastern District of Tennessee granted the State’s&#xD;
motion for summary judgment and dismissed the habeas&#xD;
petition. The court held that Thompson failed to show&#xD;
that the state court’s resolution of his claim rested on an&#xD;
unreasonable application of Supreme Court precedent or&#xD;
on an unreasonable determination of the facts in light of&#xD;
the evidence presented in state court. See 28 U. S. C.&#xD;
§2254(d). The District Court also stated that Thompson&#xD;
had not presented “any significant probative evidence that&#xD;
[he] was suffering from a significant mental disease that&#xD;
should have been presented to the jury during the pun-&#xD;
ishment phase as mitigation.” No. 4:98–CV006 (ED Tenn.,&#xD;
Feb. 17, 2000), App. to Pet. for Cert. 270. Sultan’s deposi-&#xD;
tion and report, however, had apparently not been in-&#xD;
cluded in the District Court record.&#xD;
   While Thompson’s appeal to the Court of Appeals for the&#xD;
4                    BELL v. THOMPSON&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
Sixth Circuit was pending, he filed a motion in the District&#xD;
Court under Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 60(b) request-&#xD;
ing that the court supplement the record with Sultan’s&#xD;
expert report and deposition. Thompson’s habeas counsel&#xD;
at the time explained that the failure to include the Sultan&#xD;
evidence in the summary judgment record was an over-&#xD;
sight. Thompson also asked the Court of Appeals to hold&#xD;
his case in abeyance pending a ruling from the District&#xD;
Court and attached the Sultan evidence in support of his&#xD;
motion.&#xD;
   The District Court denied the Rule 60(b) motion as&#xD;
untimely, and the Court of Appeals denied Thompson’s&#xD;
motion to hold his appeal in abeyance. On January 9,&#xD;
2003, a divided panel of the Court of Appeals affirmed the&#xD;
District Court’s denial of habeas relief. 315 F. 3d 566.&#xD;
The lead opinion, authored by Judge Suhrheinrich, rea-&#xD;
soned that there was no ineffective assistance of counsel&#xD;
because Thompson’s attorneys were aware of his head&#xD;
injuries and made appropriate inquiries into his mental&#xD;
fitness. Id., at 589–592. In particular, Thompson’s attor-&#xD;
neys had requested that the trial court order a competency&#xD;
evaluation. A team of experts at the Middle Tennessee&#xD;
Mental Health Institute, a state-run facility, found “no&#xD;
mental illness, mental defect, or insanity.” Id., at 589. Dr.&#xD;
George Copple, the clinical psychologist retained by&#xD;
Thompson’s attorneys, also “found no evidence of mental&#xD;
illness.” Ibid. Judge Suhrheinrich emphasized that none&#xD;
of the experts retained by Thompson since trial had of-&#xD;
fered an opinion on his mental condition at the time of the&#xD;
crime. Id., at 589–592. The lead opinion contained a&#xD;
passing reference to Thompson’s unsuccessful Rule 60(b)&#xD;
motion, but did not discuss the Sultan deposition or expert&#xD;
report in any detail. Id., at 583, n. 13. Judge Moore con-&#xD;
curred in the result based on Thompson’s failure to pre-&#xD;
sent “evidence that his counsel knew or should have&#xD;
known either that Thompson was mentally ill or that his&#xD;
                 Cite as: 545 U. S. ____ (2005)           5&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
mental condition was deteriorating at the time of his trial&#xD;
or at the time of his crime.” Id., at 595.&#xD;
   Thompson filed a petition for rehearing. The petition&#xD;
placed substantial emphasis on the Sultan evidence, quot-&#xD;
ing from both her deposition and expert report. The Court&#xD;
of Appeals denied the petition for rehearing and stayed&#xD;
the issuance of its mandate pending the disposition of&#xD;
Thompson’s petition for certiorari.&#xD;
   This Court denied certiorari on December 1, 2003. 540&#xD;
U. S. 1051. The following day, Thompson filed a motion in&#xD;
the Court of Appeals seeking to extend the stay of man-&#xD;
date pending disposition of his petition for rehearing in&#xD;
this Court. The Court of Appeals granted the motion and&#xD;
“ordered that the mandate be stayed to allow appellant&#xD;
time to file a petition for rehearing from the denial of the&#xD;
writ of certiorari, and thereafter until the Supreme Court&#xD;
disposes of the case.” App. to Pet. for Cert. 348. On Janu-&#xD;
ary 20, 2004, this Court denied Thompson’s petition for&#xD;
rehearing. 540 U. S. 1158. A copy of the order was filed&#xD;
with the Court of Appeals on January 23, 2004. The Court&#xD;
of Appeals, however, did not issue its mandate.&#xD;
   The State, under the apparent assumption that the&#xD;
federal habeas corpus proceedings had terminated, filed a&#xD;
motion before the Tennessee Supreme Court requesting&#xD;
that an execution date be set. The court scheduled&#xD;
Thompson’s execution for August 19, 2004.&#xD;
   From February to June 2004, there were proceedings in&#xD;
both state and federal courts related to Thompson’s pre-&#xD;
sent competency to be executed under Ford v. Wainwright,&#xD;
477 U. S. 399 (1986). The state courts, after considering&#xD;
Sultan’s testimony (which was based in part on followup&#xD;
observations after her initial 1998 examination) as well as&#xD;
that of other experts, found Thompson competent to be&#xD;
executed. Thompson v. State, 134 S. W. 3d 168 (Tenn.&#xD;
2004). Thompson’s Ford claim was still pending before the&#xD;
Federal District Court when on June 23, 2004, some seven&#xD;
6                    BELL v. THOMPSON&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
months after this Court denied certiorari, the Court of&#xD;
Appeals for the Sixth Circuit issued an amended opinion&#xD;
in Thompson’s initial federal habeas case. 373 F. 3d 688.&#xD;
The new decision vacated the District Court’s judgment&#xD;
denying habeas relief and remanded the case for an evi-&#xD;
dentiary hearing on Thompson’s ineffective-assistance-of-&#xD;
counsel claim. Id., at 691–692. The Court of Appeals&#xD;
relied on its equitable powers to supplement the record on&#xD;
appeal with Dr. Sultan’s 1999 deposition after finding that&#xD;
it was “apparently negligently omitted” and “probative of&#xD;
Thompson’s mental state at the time of the crime.” Id., at&#xD;
691. The court also explained its authority to issue an&#xD;
amended opinion five months after this Court denied a&#xD;
petition for rehearing: “[W]e rely on our inherent power to&#xD;
reconsider our opinion prior to the issuance of the man-&#xD;
date, which has not yet issued in this case.” Id., at 691–&#xD;
692. Judge Suhrheinrich authored a lengthy separate&#xD;
opinion concurring in part and dissenting in part, which&#xD;
explained that his chambers initiated the sua sponte&#xD;
reconsideration of the case. He agreed with the majority&#xD;
about the probative value of the Sultan deposition, refer-&#xD;
ring to the evidence as “critical.” Id., at 733. Unlike the&#xD;
majority, however, Judge Suhrheinrich would have relied&#xD;
upon fraud on the court to justify the decision to expand&#xD;
the record and issue an amended opinion. Id., at 725–726,&#xD;
729–742. He found “implausible” the explanation offered&#xD;
by Thompson’s habeas counsel for his failure to include&#xD;
the Sultan deposition in the District Court record, id., at&#xD;
742, and speculated that counsel “planned to unveil Dr.&#xD;
Sultan’s opinion on the eve of Thompson’s execution,” id.,&#xD;
at 738, n. 21.&#xD;
   We granted certiorari. 543 U. S. ___ (2005).&#xD;
                              II&#xD;
  At issue in this case is the scope of the Court of Appeals’&#xD;
authority to withhold the mandate pursuant to Federal&#xD;
                Cite as: 545 U. S. ____ (2005)             7&#xD;
&#xD;
                    Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
Rule of Appellate Procedure 41.        As relevant, the Rule&#xD;
provides:&#xD;
     “(b) When Issued. The court’s mandate must issue&#xD;
   7 calendar days after the time to file a petition for re-&#xD;
   hearing expires, or 7 calendar days after entry of an&#xD;
   order denying a timely petition for panel rehearing,&#xD;
   petition for rehearing en banc, or motion for stay of&#xD;
   mandate, whichever is later. The court may shorten&#xD;
   or extend the time.&#xD;
     “(c) Effective Date. The mandate is effective when&#xD;
   issued.&#xD;
     “(d) Staying the Mandate.&#xD;
     “(1) On Petition for Rehearing or Motion. The&#xD;
   timely filing of a petition for panel rehearing, petition&#xD;
   for rehearing en banc, or motion for stay of mandate,&#xD;
   stays the mandate until disposition of the petition or&#xD;
   motion, unless the court orders otherwise.&#xD;
     “(2) Pending Petition for Certiorari.&#xD;
     “(A) A party may move to stay the mandate pending&#xD;
   the filing of a petition for a writ of certiorari in the&#xD;
   Supreme Court. The motion must be served on all&#xD;
   parties and must show that the certiorari petition&#xD;
   would present a substantial question and that there is&#xD;
   good cause for a stay.&#xD;
     “(B) The stay must not exceed 90 days, unless the&#xD;
   period is extended for good cause or unless the party&#xD;
   who obtained the stay files a petition for the writ and&#xD;
   so notifies the circuit clerk in writing within the pe-&#xD;
   riod of the stay. In that case, the stay continues until&#xD;
   the Supreme Court’s final disposition.&#xD;
        .           .           .          .              .&#xD;
     “(D) The court of appeals must issue the mandate&#xD;
   immediately when a copy of a Supreme Court order&#xD;
   denying the petition for writ of certiorari is filed.”&#xD;
 Tennessee argues that the Court of Appeals was re-&#xD;
8                    BELL v. THOMPSON&#xD;
&#xD;
                      Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
quired to issue the mandate following this Court’s denial&#xD;
of Thompson’s petition for certiorari. The State’s position&#xD;
rests on Rule 41(d)(2)(D), which states that “[t]he court of&#xD;
appeals must issue the mandate immediately when a copy&#xD;
of a Supreme Court order denying the petition for writ of&#xD;
certiorari is filed.” This provision, the State points out,&#xD;
admits of no exceptions, so the mandate should have&#xD;
issued on the date that a copy of this Court’s order deny-&#xD;
ing certiorari was filed with the Court of Appeals, i.e.,&#xD;
December 8, 2003.&#xD;
   The State further contends that because the mandate&#xD;
should have issued in December 2003, the Court of Ap-&#xD;
peals’ amended opinion was in essence a recall of the&#xD;
mandate. If this view is correct, the Court of Appeals’&#xD;
decision to revisit its earlier opinion must satisfy the&#xD;
standard established by Calderon v. Thompson, 523 U. S.&#xD;
538 (1998). Calderon held that “where a federal court of&#xD;
appeals sua sponte recalls its mandate to revisit the merits&#xD;
of an earlier decision denying habeas corpus relief to a state&#xD;
prisoner, the court abuses its discretion unless it acts to&#xD;
avoid a miscarriage of justice as defined by our habeas&#xD;
corpus jurisprudence.” Id., at 558. See also Schlup v. Delo,&#xD;
513 U. S. 298 (1995); Sawyer v. Whitley, 505 U. S. 333&#xD;
(1992).&#xD;
   Thompson counters by arguing that Rule 41(d)(2)(D) is&#xD;
determinative only when the court of appeals enters a stay&#xD;
of the mandate to allow the Supreme Court to dispose of a&#xD;
petition for certiorari. The provision, Thompson says, does&#xD;
not affect the court of appeals’ broad discretion to enter a&#xD;
stay for other reasons. He relies on Rule 41(b), which&#xD;
provides the court of appeals may “shorten or extend the&#xD;
time” in which to issue the mandate. Because the author-&#xD;
ity vested by Rule 41(b) is not limited to the period before&#xD;
a petition for certiorari is denied, he argues that the Court&#xD;
of Appeals had the authority to stay its mandate following&#xD;
this Court’s denial of certiorari and rehearing. Although&#xD;
                 Cite as: 545 U. S. ____ (2005)            9&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
the Court of Appeals failed to issue an order staying the&#xD;
mandate after we denied rehearing, Thompson asserts&#xD;
that the court exercised its Rule 41(b) powers by simply&#xD;
failing to issue it.&#xD;
  To resolve this case, we need not adopt either party’s&#xD;
interpretation of Rule 41.      Instead, we hold that—&#xD;
assuming, arguendo, both that the Rule authorizes a stay&#xD;
of the mandate following the denial of certiorari and also&#xD;
that a court may stay the mandate without entering an&#xD;
order—here the Court of Appeals abused its discretion in&#xD;
doing so.&#xD;
                             III&#xD;
   We find an abuse of discretion for the following reasons.&#xD;
   Prominent among our concerns is the length of time&#xD;
between this Court’s denial of certiorari and the Court of&#xD;
Appeals’ issuance of its amended opinion. We denied&#xD;
Thompson’s petition for certiorari in December 2003 and&#xD;
his petition for rehearing one month later. From this last&#xD;
denial, however, the Court of Appeals delayed issuing its&#xD;
mandate for over five months, releasing its amended&#xD;
opinion in June.&#xD;
   The consequence of delay for the State’s criminal justice&#xD;
system was compounded by the Court of Appeals’ failure&#xD;
to issue an order or otherwise give notice to the parties&#xD;
that the court was reconsidering its earlier opinion. The&#xD;
Court of Appeals had issued two earlier orders staying its&#xD;
mandate. The first order stayed the mandate pending&#xD;
disposition of Thompson’s petition for certiorari. The&#xD;
second order extended the stay to allow Thompson time to&#xD;
file a petition for rehearing with this Court and “thereaf-&#xD;
ter until the Supreme Court disposes of the case.” So by&#xD;
the express terms of the second order the mandate was not&#xD;
to be stayed after this Court acted; and when we denied&#xD;
rehearing on January 20, 2004, the Court of Appeals’&#xD;
second stay dissolved by operation of law. Tennessee,&#xD;
10                   BELL v. THOMPSON&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
acting in reliance on the Court of Appeals’ earlier orders&#xD;
and our denial of certiorari and rehearing, could assume&#xD;
that the mandate would—indeed must—issue. While it&#xD;
might have been prudent for the State to verify that the&#xD;
mandate had issued, it is understandable that it pro-&#xD;
ceeded to schedule an execution date. Thompson, after all,&#xD;
had not sought an additional stay of the mandate, and the&#xD;
Court of Appeals had given no indication that it might be&#xD;
revisiting its earlier decision.&#xD;
   This latter point is important. It is an open question&#xD;
whether a court may exercise its Rule 41(b) authority to&#xD;
extend the time for the mandate to issue through mere&#xD;
inaction. Even assuming, however, that a court could&#xD;
effect a stay for a short period of time by withholding the&#xD;
mandate, a delay of five months is different in kind.&#xD;
“Basic to the operation of the judicial system is the princi-&#xD;
ple that a court speaks through its judgments and orders.”&#xD;
Murdaugh Volkswagen, Inc. v. First National Bank of&#xD;
South Carolina, 741 F. 2d 41, 44 (CA4 1984). Without a&#xD;
formal docket entry neither the parties nor this Court had,&#xD;
or have, any way to know whether the court had stayed&#xD;
the mandate or simply made a clerical mistake. Cf. Bal-&#xD;
lard v. Commissioner, 544 U. S. ___, ___ (2005) (slip op., at&#xD;
17). The dissent claims “the failure to notify the parties&#xD;
was likely due to a simple clerical error” on the part of the&#xD;
Clerk’s office. Post, at 12–13 (opinion of BREYER, J.). The&#xD;
record lends no support to this speculation. The dissent&#xD;
also fails to explain why it is willing to apply a “presump-&#xD;
tion of regularity” to the panel’s actions but not to the&#xD;
Clerk’s. Ibid.&#xD;
   The Court of Appeals could have spared the parties and&#xD;
the state judicial system considerable time and resources&#xD;
if it had notified them that it was reviewing its original&#xD;
panel decision. After we denied Thompson’s petition for&#xD;
rehearing, Tennessee scheduled his execution date. This,&#xD;
in turn, led to various proceedings in state and federal&#xD;
                 Cite as: 545 U. S. ____ (2005)           11&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
court to determine Thompson’s present competency to be&#xD;
executed. See, e.g., Thompson v. State, 134 S. W. 3d 168&#xD;
(Tenn. 2004). All of these steps were taken in reliance on&#xD;
the mistaken impression that Thompson’s first federal&#xD;
habeas case was final. The State had begun to “invok[e]&#xD;
its entire legal and moral authority in support of executing&#xD;
its judgment.” Calderon v. Thompson, 523 U. S., at 556–&#xD;
557.&#xD;
   The parties’ assumption that Thompson’s habeas pro-&#xD;
ceedings were complete was all the more reasonable be-&#xD;
cause the Court of Appeals’ delay in issuing its mandate&#xD;
took place after we had denied certiorari. As a practical&#xD;
matter, a decision by this Court denying discretionary&#xD;
review usually signals the end of litigation. While Rule&#xD;
41(b) may authorize a court to stay the mandate after&#xD;
certiorari is denied, the circumstances where such a stay&#xD;
would be warranted are rare. See, e.g., First Gibraltar&#xD;
Bank, FSB v. Morales, 42 F. 3d 895 (CA5 1995); Alphin v.&#xD;
Henson, 552 F. 2d 1033 (CA4 1977). In the typical case,&#xD;
where the stay of mandate is entered solely to allow this&#xD;
Court time to consider a petition for certiorari, Rule&#xD;
41(d)(2)(D) provides the default: “The court of appeals&#xD;
must issue the mandate immediately when a copy of a&#xD;
Supreme Court order denying the petition for writ of&#xD;
certiorari is filed.”&#xD;
   By providing a mechanism for correcting errors in the&#xD;
courts of appeals before Supreme Court review is re-&#xD;
quested, the Federal Rules of Appellate Procedure ensure&#xD;
that litigation following the denial of certiorari will be&#xD;
infrequent. See Fed. Rule App. Proc. 40(a) (“Unless the&#xD;
time is shortened or extended by order or local rule, a&#xD;
petition for panel rehearing may be filed within 14 days&#xD;
after entry of judgment”). See also Fed. Rules App. Proc.&#xD;
35 (rehearing en banc), 40 (panel rehearing).&#xD;
   Indeed, in this case Thompson’s petition for rehearing&#xD;
and suggestion for rehearing en banc pressed the same&#xD;
12                   BELL v. THOMPSON&#xD;
&#xD;
                      Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
arguments that eventually were adopted by the Court of&#xD;
Appeals in its amended opinion. The Sultan evidence,&#xD;
first presented to the Court of Appeals as an attachment&#xD;
to Thompson’s motion to hold his appeal in abeyance, was&#xD;
quoted extensively in the petition for rehearing to the&#xD;
Court of Appeals. Pet. for Rehearing and Suggestion for&#xD;
Rehearing En Banc in No. 2:00–5516 (CA6), pp. 12–20,&#xD;
28–31. After the request for rehearing was denied, the&#xD;
State could have assumed with good reason that the Court&#xD;
of Appeals was not impressed by Thompson’s arguments&#xD;
based on the Sultan evidence. The court’s opportunity to&#xD;
consider these arguments at the rehearing stage is yet&#xD;
another factor supporting our determination that the&#xD;
decision to withhold the mandate was in error. Cf.&#xD;
Calderon v. Thompson, supra, at 551–553 (questioning&#xD;
whether a “mishandled law clerk transition” and the “failure&#xD;
of another judge to notice the action proposed by the original&#xD;
panel” would justify recalling the mandate in a nonhabeas&#xD;
case).&#xD;
   The dissent’s explanation of how the Sultan evidence&#xD;
was overlooked is inaccurate in several respects. For&#xD;
example, the statements that the “Sultan documents were&#xD;
not in the initial record on appeal,” post, at 9, and that&#xD;
“the panel previously had not seen these documents”&#xD;
before the rehearing stage, id., at 9, convey the wrong&#xD;
impression. Although the Sultan evidence was not part of&#xD;
the District Court’s summary judgment record, the docu-&#xD;
ments were included in the certified record on appeal as&#xD;
attachments to Thompson’s Rule 60(b) motion. Record&#xD;
133; Docket Entry 4/5/02 in No. 98–CV–6 (ED Tenn.);&#xD;
Docket Entry 4/10/02 in No. 00–5516 (CA6). The dissent&#xD;
also argues the petition for rehearing did not adequately&#xD;
bring the Sultan evidence to the attention of the Court of&#xD;
Appeals. Post, at 9–10, 13–14. This is simply untrue. The&#xD;
original panel opinion, which did not discuss the Sultan&#xD;
evidence in any detail, emphasized that Thompson had&#xD;
                 Cite as: 545 U. S. ____ (2005)          13&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
failed to produce any evidence that he was mentally ill at&#xD;
the time of his offense. 315 F. 3d, at 590; id., at 595–596&#xD;
(Moore, J., concurring). The petition for rehearing attacked&#xD;
this conclusion in no uncertain terms and placed the Sultan&#xD;
evidence front and center. Here, for example, is an excerpt&#xD;
from the petition’s table of contents:&#xD;
       “II. THE CONCLUSION THAT THERE IS NO&#xD;
    EVIDENCE PRESENTED IN THE RECORD OF&#xD;
    THOMPSON’S MENTAL ILLESS AT THE TIME OF&#xD;
    THE CRIME IS WRONG&#xD;
       “A. Thompson Has Set Forth Above The Record&#xD;
    Facts Demonstrating His Mental Illness At The Time&#xD;
    of The Crime&#xD;
       “B. The Majority Overlooks The Facts And Expert&#xD;
    Opinion Set Forth In Dr. Sultan’s Report and Deposi-&#xD;
    tion.” Pet. for Rehearing and Suggestion for Rehear-&#xD;
    ing En Banc in No. 2:00–5516 (CA6), p. ii.&#xD;
See also id., at 1 (mentioning the Sultan evidence in the&#xD;
second paragraph of the statement in support of panel&#xD;
rehearing). The rehearing petition did not explain why&#xD;
Sultan’s deposition and expert report had been omitted&#xD;
from the summary judgment record but that is beside the&#xD;
point. The petition acknowledged that the Sultan evi-&#xD;
dence was first presented to the District Court as an at-&#xD;
tachment to the Rule 60(b) motion, id., at 29, and gave the&#xD;
Sultan evidence a prominent and explicit mention in the&#xD;
table of contents. It is difficult to see how Thompson’s&#xD;
counsel could have been clearer in telling the Court of&#xD;
Appeals that it was wrong. The dissent’s treatment of this&#xD;
issue assumes that judges forget even the basic details of a&#xD;
capital case only one month after issuing a 38-page opin-&#xD;
ion and that judges cannot be relied upon to read past the&#xD;
first page of a petition for rehearing. The problem is that&#xD;
the dissent cannot have it both ways: If the Sultan evi-&#xD;
dence is as crucial as the dissent claims, it would not&#xD;
14                  BELL v. THOMPSON&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
easily have been overlooked by the Court of Appeals at the&#xD;
rehearing stage.&#xD;
   Our review of the Sultan deposition reinforces our con-&#xD;
clusion that the Court of Appeals abused its discretion by&#xD;
withholding the mandate. Had the Sultan deposition and&#xD;
report been fully considered in the federal habeas proceed-&#xD;
ings, it no doubt would have been relevant to the District&#xD;
Court’s analysis. Based on the Sultan deposition Thomp-&#xD;
son could have argued he suffered from mental illness at&#xD;
the time of his crime that would have been a mitigating&#xD;
factor under Tennessee law and that his trial attorneys&#xD;
were constitutionally ineffective for failing to conduct an&#xD;
adequate investigation into his mental health.&#xD;
   Relevant though the Sultan evidence may be, however,&#xD;
it is not of such a character as to warrant the Court of&#xD;
Appeals’ extraordinary departure from standard appellate&#xD;
procedures. There are ample grounds to conclude the&#xD;
evidence was unlikely to have altered the District Court’s&#xD;
resolution of Thompson’s ineffective-assistance-of-counsel&#xD;
claim. Sultan examined Thompson for the first time on&#xD;
August 20, 1998, App. 37, some 13 years after Thompson’s&#xD;
crime and conviction. She relied on the deterioration in&#xD;
Thompson’s present mental health—something that obvi-&#xD;
ously was not observable at the time of trial—as evidence&#xD;
of his condition in 1985. (Indeed, there was a marked&#xD;
decline in his condition during the 6-month period be-&#xD;
tween Sultan’s first two visits. Id., at 51–58.) Sultan’s&#xD;
findings regarding Thompson’s condition in 1985 are&#xD;
contradicted by the testimony of two experts who exam-&#xD;
ined him at the time of trial, Dr. Watson and Dr. Copple.&#xD;
Watson performed a battery of tests at the Middle Tennes-&#xD;
see Mental Health Institute, where Thompson was re-&#xD;
ferred by the trial court for an examination, and concluded&#xD;
that Thompson “ ‘[did] not appear to be suffering from any&#xD;
complicated mental disorder which would impair his&#xD;
capacity to appreciate the wrongfulness of the alleged&#xD;
                 Cite as: 545 U. S. ____ (2005)           15&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
offenses, or which would impair his capacity to conform&#xD;
his conduct to the requirements of the law.’ ” 19 Tr. 164.&#xD;
Indeed, Watson presented substantial evidence supporting&#xD;
his conclusion that Thompson was malingering for mental&#xD;
illness. Id., at 151–152; 20 id., at 153–160. For example,&#xD;
Thompson claimed he could not read despite a B average&#xD;
in high school and one year’s college credit. 19 id., at 137;&#xD;
20 id., at 151. Thompson’s test scores also indicated that&#xD;
he was attempting to fake schizophrenia. 20 id., at 153–&#xD;
154. Copple, the psychologist retained by Thompson’s&#xD;
defense team, agreed with Watson that Thompson was not&#xD;
suffering from mental illness. 19 id., at 58. Had the&#xD;
Sultan deposition been included in the District Court&#xD;
record, Thompson still would have faced an uphill battle to&#xD;
obtaining federal habeas relief. He would have had to&#xD;
argue that his trial attorneys should have continued to&#xD;
investigate his mental health even after both Watson and&#xD;
Copple had opined that there was nothing to uncover.&#xD;
   Sultan’s testimony does not negate Thompson’s respon-&#xD;
sibility for committing the underlying offense, but it does&#xD;
bear upon an argument that Thompson’s attorneys could&#xD;
have presented at sentencing. Sultan’s ultimate conclu-&#xD;
sion—that Thompson’s mental illness substantially im-&#xD;
paired his ability to conform his conduct to the require-&#xD;
ments of the law—is couched in the language of a&#xD;
mitigating factor under Tennessee law. Tenn. Code Ann.&#xD;
§39–2–203(j)(8) (1982). See also §39–13–204(j)(8) (Lexis&#xD;
2003). Thompson’s trial attorneys, however, chose not to&#xD;
pursue a mitigation strategy based on mental illness,&#xD;
stressing instead character evidence from family and&#xD;
friends and expert testimony that he had the capacity to&#xD;
adjust to prison. Thompson v. State, 958 S. W. 2d, at 164–&#xD;
165. This strategic calculation, while ultimately unsuc-&#xD;
cessful, was based on a reasonable investigation into&#xD;
Thompson’s background. Sultan relied on three witnesses&#xD;
in preparing her report: Thompson’s grandmother, sister,&#xD;
16                  BELL v. THOMPSON&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
and ex-girlfriend. These witnesses not only were inter-&#xD;
viewed by the defense attorneys; they testified at sentenc-&#xD;
ing. Consultation with these witnesses, when combined&#xD;
with the opinions of Watson and Copple, provided an&#xD;
adequate basis for Thompson’s attorneys to conclude that&#xD;
focusing on Thompson’s mental health was not the best&#xD;
strategy. As the Tennessee Court of Criminal Appeals&#xD;
noted, “Because two experts did not detect brain damage,&#xD;
counsel cannot be faulted for discarding a strategy that&#xD;
could not be supported by a medical opinion.” Id., at 165.&#xD;
   Without a single citation to the record, the dissent sug-&#xD;
gests that Thompson’s attorneys failed to conduct ade-&#xD;
quate interviews of the defense witnesses on whom Sultan&#xD;
relied in her report. Post, at 14–15. Most of the informa-&#xD;
tion on Thompson’s childhood was provided to Sultan by&#xD;
Nora Jean Wharton, Thompson’s older sister. App. 16–18.&#xD;
Setting aside the fact that Thompson did not argue in&#xD;
state court that his counsel’s interview of Wharton was&#xD;
inadequate, Thompson v. State, 958 S. W. 2d, at 160–169,&#xD;
Thompson’s attorneys cannot be faulted for failing to elicit&#xD;
from her any details on Thompson’s difficult home life.&#xD;
After all, Wharton testified at trial that Thompson’s child-&#xD;
hood was “poor,” but “very happy.” 18 Tr. 3. The dissent&#xD;
also implies that the experts who examined Thompson&#xD;
lacked information necessary to reach an accurate as-&#xD;
sessment. The record refutes this assertion. In conduct-&#xD;
ing his examination, Watson had access to Thompson’s&#xD;
social history and military records. 19 id., at 149; 20 id.,&#xD;
at 186 (Exh. 102, pp. 11, 27–28). Watson was also aware&#xD;
of the prior head injuries as well as Thompson’s claim that&#xD;
he heard voices. 19 id., at 152; 20 id., at 154–155. Never-&#xD;
theless, Watson, whose evaluation was contemporaneous&#xD;
with the trial, found no evidence that Thompson was&#xD;
mentally ill at the time of the crime. Watson’s report was&#xD;
unequivocal on this point:&#xD;
                  Cite as: 545 U. S. ____ (2005)           17&#xD;
&#xD;
                      Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
       “ ‘Mr. Thompson’s speech and communication were&#xD;
    coherent, rational, organized, relevant, and devoid of&#xD;
    circumstantiality, tangentiality, looseness of associa-&#xD;
    tions, paranoid ideation, ideas of reference, delusions,&#xD;
    and other indicators of a thought disorder. His affect&#xD;
    was appropriate to his thought content, and he exhib-&#xD;
    ited no flight of ideas, manic, depressed, or bizarre&#xD;
    behaviors, and his speech was not pressured nor&#xD;
    rapid. He exhibited none of the signs of an affective&#xD;
    illness. His judgment and insight are rather poor.&#xD;
    Psychological testing revealed him to be functioning&#xD;
    in the average range intellectually, to exhibit no signs&#xD;
    of organicity or brain damage on the Bender-Gestalt&#xD;
    Test and the Bender Interference Procedure. Person-&#xD;
    ality profiles revealed no evidence of a psychosis, but&#xD;
    indicated malingering in the mental illness direction.&#xD;
    (For example, the schizophrenic score was at T 120,&#xD;
    while clinical observations revealed no evidence of a&#xD;
    thought disorder.) Mr. Thompson’s memory for recent&#xD;
    and remote events appeared unimpaired.’ ” 20 id., at&#xD;
    159–160.&#xD;
   Sultan’s testimony provides some support for the argu-&#xD;
ment that the strategy of emphasizing Thompson’s posi-&#xD;
tive attributes was a mistake in light of Thompson’s dete-&#xD;
riorated condition 13 years after the trial. This evidence,&#xD;
however, would not come close to satisfying the miscar-&#xD;
riage of justice standard under Calderon had the Court of&#xD;
Appeals recalled the mandate. Neither, in our view, did&#xD;
this evidence justify the Court of Appeals’ decision to&#xD;
withhold the mandate without notice to the parties, which&#xD;
in turn led the State to proceed for five months on the&#xD;
mistaken assumption that the federal habeas proceedings&#xD;
had terminated. The dissent suggests that failing to take&#xD;
account of the Sultan evidence would result in a “miscar-&#xD;
riage of justice,” post, at 1–2, 16, but the dissent uses that&#xD;
18                   BELL v. THOMPSON&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
phrase in a way that is inconsistent with our precedents.&#xD;
In Sawyer v. Whitley, 505 U. S., at 545–547, this Court held&#xD;
that additional mitigating evidence could not meet the&#xD;
miscarriage of justice standard. Only evidence that affects&#xD;
a defendant’s eligibility for the death penalty—which the&#xD;
Sultan evidence is not—can support a miscarriage of&#xD;
justice claim in the capital sentencing context. Id., at 547;&#xD;
Calderon, 523 U. S., at 559–560.&#xD;
   One last consideration informs our review of the Court&#xD;
of Appeals’ actions. In Calderon, we held that federalism&#xD;
concerns, arising from the unique character of federal&#xD;
habeas review of state-court judgments, and the policies&#xD;
embodied in the Antiterrorism and Effective Death Pen-&#xD;
alty Act of 1996 required an additional presumption&#xD;
against recalling the mandate. This case also arises from&#xD;
federal habeas corpus review of a state conviction. While&#xD;
the State’s reliance interest is not as strong in a case&#xD;
where, unlike Calderon, the mandate has not issued, the&#xD;
finality and comity concerns that animated Calderon are&#xD;
implicated here. Here a dedicated judge discovered what&#xD;
he believed to have been an error, and we are respectful of&#xD;
the Court of Appeals’ willingness to correct a decision that&#xD;
it perceived to have been mistaken. A court’s discretion&#xD;
under Rule 41 must be exercised, however, in a way that&#xD;
is consistent with the “ ‘State’s interest in the finality of&#xD;
convictions that have survived direct review within the&#xD;
state court system.’ ” Id., at 555 (quoting Brecht v. Abra-&#xD;
hamson, 507 U. S. 619, 635 (1993)). Tennessee expended&#xD;
considerable time and resources in seeking to enforce a&#xD;
capital sentence rendered 20 years ago, a sentence that&#xD;
reflects the judgment of the citizens of Tennessee that&#xD;
Thompson’s crimes merit the ultimate punishment. By&#xD;
withholding the mandate for months—based on evidence&#xD;
that supports only an arguable constitutional claim—while&#xD;
the State prepared to carry out Thompson’s sentence, the&#xD;
Court of Appeals did not accord the appropriate level of&#xD;
                 Cite as: 545 U. S. ____ (2005)           19&#xD;
&#xD;
                     Opinion of the Court&#xD;
&#xD;
respect to that judgment. See Calderon v. Thompson, su-&#xD;
pra, at 554–557.&#xD;
   The Court of Appeals may have been influenced by&#xD;
Sultan’s unsettling account of Thompson’s condition dur-&#xD;
ing one of her visits. She described Thompson as being in&#xD;
“terrible psychological condition,” “physically filthy,” and&#xD;
“highly agitated.” App. 51. This testimony raised ques-&#xD;
tions about Thompson’s deteriorating mental health and&#xD;
perhaps his competence to be executed, but these concerns&#xD;
were properly addressed in separate proceedings. Based&#xD;
on the most recent state-court decision, which rejected the&#xD;
argument that Thompson is not competent to be executed,&#xD;
it appears that his condition has improved. Thompson v.&#xD;
State, 134 S. W. 3d, at 184–185. Proceedings on this issue&#xD;
were underway in the District Court when the Court of&#xD;
Appeals issued its second opinion. If those proceedings&#xD;
resume, the District Court will have an opportunity to&#xD;
address these matters again and in light of the current&#xD;
evidence.&#xD;
   Taken together these considerations convince us that&#xD;
the Court of Appeals abused any discretion Rule 41 ar-&#xD;
guably granted it to stay its mandate, without entering a&#xD;
formal order, after this Court had denied certiorari. The&#xD;
judgment of the Court of Appeals for Sixth Circuit is re-&#xD;
versed.&#xD;
                                            It is so ordered.&#xD;
                 Cite as: 545 U. S. ____ (2005)           1&#xD;
&#xD;
                    BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED STATES&#xD;
                         _________________&#xD;
&#xD;
                          No. 04–514&#xD;
                         _________________&#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
  RICKY BELL, WARDEN, PETITIONER v. GREGORY&#xD;
                 THOMPSON&#xD;
 ON WRIT OF CERTIORARI TO THE UNITED STATES COURT OF&#xD;
            APPEALS FOR THE SIXTH CIRCUIT&#xD;
                        [June 27, 2005]&#xD;
&#xD;
   JUSTICE BREYER, with whom JUSTICE STEVENS, JUSTICE&#xD;
SOUTER, and JUSTICE GINSBURG join, dissenting.&#xD;
   This capital case arises out of unusual circumstances—&#xD;
circumstances of a kind that I have not previously experi-&#xD;
enced in the 25 years I have served on the federal bench.&#xD;
After an appellate court writes and releases an opinion,&#xD;
but before it issues its mandate, the writing judge,&#xD;
through happenstance, comes across a document that (he&#xD;
reasonably believes) shows not only that the court’s initial&#xD;
decision is wrong but that the decision will lead to a seri-&#xD;
ous miscarriage of justice. What is the judge to do?&#xD;
   What the judge did here was to spend time—hundreds&#xD;
of hours (while a petition for certiorari was pending before&#xD;
this Court and during the five months following our denial&#xD;
of the petition for rehearing)—reviewing the contents of&#xD;
the vast record with its many affidavits, reports, tran-&#xD;
scripts, and other documents accumulated in the course of&#xD;
numerous state and federal proceedings during the pre-&#xD;
ceding 20 years. The judge ultimately concluded that his&#xD;
initial instinct about the document was correct. The&#xD;
document was critically important. It could affect the&#xD;
outcome of what is, and has always been, the major issue&#xD;
in the case. To consider the case without reference to it&#xD;
could mean a miscarriage of justice.&#xD;
   The judge consequently wrote a lengthy opinion (almost&#xD;
2                    BELL v. THOMPSON&#xD;
&#xD;
                     BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
30,000 words) explaining what had happened. The other&#xD;
members of the panel did not agree with everything in&#xD;
that opinion, but they did agree that their initial decision&#xD;
must be vacated.&#xD;
   The Court commendably describes what occurred as&#xD;
follows: A “dedicated judge discovered what he believed to&#xD;
have been an error, and we are respectful of the Court of&#xD;
Appeals’ willingness to correct a decision that it perceived&#xD;
to have been mistaken.” Ante, at 18. The Court, however,&#xD;
does not decide this case in a manner consistent with that&#xD;
observation. A somewhat more comprehensive account of&#xD;
the nature of the “error”—of the matter at stake, of the&#xD;
importance of the document, of the mystery of its late&#xD;
appearance, of the potential for a miscarriage of justice—&#xD;
should help make apparent the difficult circumstance the&#xD;
panel believed it faced. It will also explain why there was&#xD;
no “abuse” of discretion in the panel’s effort to “correct a&#xD;
decision that it perceived to have been mistaken.”&#xD;
                              I&#xD;
  Judge Suhrheinrich, the panel member who investi-&#xD;
gated the record, is an experienced federal judge, serving&#xD;
since 1984 as a federal trial court judge and since 1990 as&#xD;
a federal appellate judge. He wrote a lengthy account of&#xD;
the circumstances present here. To understand this case,&#xD;
one must read that full account and then compare it with&#xD;
the Court’s truncated version. I provide a rough summary&#xD;
of the matter based upon my own reading of his opinion.&#xD;
373 F. 3d 688, 692–742 (CA6 2004).&#xD;
                              A&#xD;
  The panel’s initial decision, issued on January 9, 2003,&#xD;
focused upon an issue often raised when federal habeas&#xD;
courts review state proceedings in a capital case, namely,&#xD;
the effectiveness of counsel at the original trial. 315 F. 3d&#xD;
566, 587–594 (CA6 2003). See Strickland v. Washington,&#xD;
                 Cite as: 545 U. S. ____ (2005)           3&#xD;
&#xD;
                    BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
466 U. S. 668 (1984). In this instance, the federal ineffec-&#xD;
tive-assistance claim was that state trial counsel had not&#xD;
sufficiently investigated the background of the defendant,&#xD;
Gregory Thompson. Thompson claimed that an adequate&#xD;
investigation would have shown, to the satisfaction of&#xD;
testifying experts, that he suffered from episodes of&#xD;
schizophrenia at the time of the crime. The schizophre-&#xD;
nia—though episodic—would have proved a mitigating&#xD;
circumstance at the penalty phase. 373 F. 3d, at 697–698,&#xD;
and n. 4.&#xD;
   Thompson’s trial took place in a Tennessee state court,&#xD;
where he was found guilty of murder and sentenced to&#xD;
death. His state-appointed counsel put on no defense at&#xD;
trial. At sentencing, however, counsel sought to show that&#xD;
Thompson was schizophrenic. State forensic psychologists&#xD;
examined Thompson and concluded that Thompson,&#xD;
probably “malingering,” did not show genuine and signifi-&#xD;
cant symptoms of schizophrenia at that time and was not&#xD;
mentally ill. A clinical psychologist hired by Thompson’s&#xD;
counsel examined Thompson for eight hours and reached&#xD;
approximately the same conclusion: he said that Thomp-&#xD;
son was not then mentally ill. Id., at 692, 694–695.&#xD;
   Thompson raised the issue of his mental condition in&#xD;
state postconviction proceedings, which he initiated in&#xD;
1990. His expert witness, Dr. Gillian Blair, testified (with&#xD;
much supportive material) that Thompson was by that&#xD;
time clearly displaying serious schizophrenic symptoms—&#xD;
voice illusions, attempts at physical self-mutilation, and&#xD;
the like. Indeed, the State conceded that he was under a&#xD;
regime of major antipsychotic medication. But Dr. Blair&#xD;
said that she could not determine whether Thompson had&#xD;
been similarly afflicted (i.e., suffering from episodes of&#xD;
schizophrenia) at the time of the crime without a thorough&#xD;
background investigation—funds for which the state court&#xD;
declined to make available. The state court then ruled in&#xD;
the State’s favor. Id., at 694–695.&#xD;
4                   BELL v. THOMPSON&#xD;
&#xD;
                    BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
   Thompson filed a habeas petition in Federal District&#xD;
Court about eight months after the state court’s denial of&#xD;
postconviction relief became final. As I said above, see&#xD;
supra, at 3, he claimed ineffective assistance of counsel.&#xD;
The Federal District Court appointed counsel, an assistant&#xD;
federal public defender. Counsel then obtained the ser-&#xD;
vices of two experts, Dr. Barry Crown and Dr. Faye Sul-&#xD;
tan. Both examined Thompson, and the latter, Dr. Sultan,&#xD;
conducted the more thorough background investigation&#xD;
that Dr. Blair had earlier sought. The State, after depos-&#xD;
ing Dr. Sultan, moved for summary judgment. 373 F. 3d,&#xD;
at 696, 700–704, 711.&#xD;
   The District Court granted that motion on the ground&#xD;
that “Thompson has not provided this Court with anything&#xD;
other than factually unsupported allegations that he was&#xD;
incompetent at the time he committed the crime,” nor “has&#xD;
Thompson provided this Court with any significant proba-&#xD;
tive evidence that [he] was suffering from a significant&#xD;
mental disease that should have been presented to the&#xD;
jury during the punishment phase as mitigation evidence.”&#xD;
Id., at 712–713 (quoting District Court’s memorandum&#xD;
opinion (emphasis and internal quotation marks omitted)).&#xD;
   Thompson (now with a new public defender as counsel)&#xD;
appealed the District Court’s grant of summary judgment&#xD;
in the State’s favor. (A little over a year later, while the&#xD;
appeal was still pending, Thompson’s new counsel, appar-&#xD;
ently having discovered that Dr. Sultan’s deposition and&#xD;
report had not been included in the record before the&#xD;
District Court, filed a motion in that court for relief from&#xD;
judgment under Federal Rule of Civil Procedure 60(b),&#xD;
seeking to supplement the record with those documents.&#xD;
Counsel also filed a motion in the appellate court, with the&#xD;
Sultan deposition attached, requesting that the appeal be&#xD;
held in abeyance while the District Court considered the&#xD;
Rule 60(b) motion.      Both motions were denied, and&#xD;
Thompson’s counsel did not take an appeal from the Dis-&#xD;
                  Cite as: 545 U. S. ____ (2005)            5&#xD;
&#xD;
                     BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
trict Court’s denial of the Rule 60(b) motion.) 373 F. 3d, at&#xD;
714–715, and n. 10, 724–725.&#xD;
    The Court of Appeals reviewed the District Court’s&#xD;
grant of summary judgment. In doing so, the appellate&#xD;
panel examined the record before that court. It noted that&#xD;
Thompson’s federal habeas counsel had hired two experts&#xD;
(Crown and Sultan), and had told the court (in an offer of&#xD;
proof) that they would provide evidence that Thompson&#xD;
suffered from mental illness at the time of the crime. But&#xD;
the appellate panel found that neither expert had done so.&#xD;
Indeed, said the panel, Thompson had “never submitted to&#xD;
any court any proof that he suffered from severe mental&#xD;
illness at the time of the crime.” 315 F. 3d, at 590 (em-&#xD;
phasis altered). Though Thompson’s several attorneys&#xD;
had made the same allegation for many years in several&#xD;
different courts (said the panel), “at each opportunity,&#xD;
counsel fail[ed] to secure an answer to the critical issue of&#xD;
whether Thompson was mentally ill at the time of the&#xD;
crime.” Ibid. That fact, concluded the panel (over a dis-&#xD;
sent), was fatal to Thompson’s basic ineffective-assistance-&#xD;
of-counsel claim. Obviously “trial counsel cannot be&#xD;
deemed ineffective for failing to discover something that&#xD;
does not appear to exist.” Ibid.; see also id., at 595 (Moore,&#xD;
J., concurring in result) (“Thompson has presented no&#xD;
evidence that his [trial] counsel knew or should have&#xD;
known either that Thompson was mentally ill or that his&#xD;
mental condition was deteriorating at the time of his trial&#xD;
or at the time of his crime”). The dissenting judge thought&#xD;
Thompson had made out an ineffective-assistance claim by&#xD;
showing that his trial counsel had relied on an inadequate&#xD;
expert, that is, an expert without the necessary qualifica-&#xD;
tions to counter the State’s experts’ conclusions. Id., at&#xD;
599–605 (opinion of Clay, J.).&#xD;
   The appeals court issued its opinion on January 9, 2003.&#xD;
Thompson’s appointed federal appeals counsel filed a&#xD;
rehearing petition, which the court denied on March 10,&#xD;
6                   BELL v. THOMPSON&#xD;
&#xD;
                    BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
2003. See App. to Pet. for Cert. 346 (Order in No. 00–5516&#xD;
(CA6)). Thompson’s counsel then sought Supreme Court&#xD;
review. This Court denied review (and rehearing) about&#xD;
one year later. 540 U. S. 1051 (2003) (denying certiorari);&#xD;
540 U. S. 1158 (2004) (denying rehearing).&#xD;
                               B&#xD;
  The Court of Appeals, following ordinary appellate-court&#xD;
practice, withheld issuance of its mandate while the case&#xD;
was under review here, namely during calendar year 2003.&#xD;
During that time and in the months that followed, some-&#xD;
thing unusual happened. Judge Suhrheinrich realized&#xD;
that the panel, in reaching its decision, seemed to have&#xD;
overlooked documents provided by Dr. Sultan that likely&#xD;
were relevant. In September 2003, the appellate court&#xD;
called for the entire certified record. Upon reviewing that&#xD;
record, Judge Suhrheinrich found Dr. Sultan’s deposition&#xD;
and accompanying report. 373 F. 3d, at 692–693; App. to&#xD;
Pet. for Cert. 347–348; see also Appendix, infra.&#xD;
  The Sultan documents filled the evidentiary gap that&#xD;
underlay the District Court’s and the appellate panel’s&#xD;
determinations. These documents made clear that Dr.&#xD;
Sultan had investigated Thompson’s background in depth&#xD;
and that in her (well-supported) opinion, Thompson had&#xD;
suffered from serious episodic bouts of schizophrenia at&#xD;
the time the crime was committed. Clearly the documents&#xD;
contained evidence supporting Thompson’s claim regard-&#xD;
ing his mental state at the time of the offense. Why had&#xD;
the District Court denied the existence of any such evi-&#xD;
dence? Why had Judge Suhrheinrich, and the other mem-&#xD;
bers of the panel (and the State, which took Dr. Sultan’s&#xD;
deposition) done the same?&#xD;
  Judge Suhrheinrich then drafted an opinion that sought&#xD;
to answer three questions:&#xD;
  Question One: Do these documents actually provide&#xD;
strong evidence that Thompson was schizophrenic (and&#xD;
                 Cite as: 545 U. S. ____ (2005)           7&#xD;
&#xD;
                    BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
seriously so) at the time of the crime?&#xD;
   Question Two: If so, given the many previous opportuni-&#xD;
ties that Thompson has had to raise the issue of his men-&#xD;
tal health, to what extent would these documents be likely&#xD;
to matter in respect to the legal question raised in Thomp-&#xD;
son’s federal proceedings, i.e., would they likely lead a&#xD;
federal habeas court to hold that Thompson’s trial counsel&#xD;
was ineffective for failing to undertake a background&#xD;
investigation akin to that performed by Dr. Sultan?&#xD;
   Question Three: How did these documents previously&#xD;
escape our attention?&#xD;
                              1&#xD;
   The panel answered the first question—regarding the&#xD;
importance of the documents—unanimously. Sultan’s&#xD;
report and deposition were critically important. As Judge&#xD;
Suhrheinrich’s opinion explains, these documents detail&#xD;
Thompson’s horrendous childhood, his family history of&#xD;
mental illness, his self-destructive schizophrenic behavior&#xD;
(including auditory hallucinations) as a child, his mood&#xD;
swings and bizarre behavior as a young adult, and a wors-&#xD;
ening of that behavior after a serious beating to his head&#xD;
that he suffered while in the Navy. For example, Dr.&#xD;
Sultan’s examination of Thompson and her interviews&#xD;
with Thompson’s family members and others revealed that&#xD;
as a child Thompson would repeatedly bang his head&#xD;
against the wall to “knock the Devil out” after his grand-&#xD;
mother yelled at him, “You have the Devil in you.” 373&#xD;
F. 3d, at 716 (internal quotation marks omitted). These&#xD;
documents explain how Thompson, as a young adult,&#xD;
would talk to himself and scream and cry for no apparent&#xD;
reason. They suggest that he had bouts of paranoia.&#xD;
   The documents provide strong support for the conclu-&#xD;
sion that Thompson suffered from episodes of schizophre-&#xD;
nia at the time of the offense. And they thereby offer&#xD;
significant support for the conclusion that, had earlier&#xD;
8                   BELL v. THOMPSON&#xD;
&#xD;
                    BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
testifying experts had this information, they could have&#xD;
countered the State’s experts’ conclusion that Thompson&#xD;
was malingering at the time of trial. Thus, the Sultan&#xD;
materials seriously undermined the foundation of the&#xD;
State’s position in respect to Thompson’s mental condition.&#xD;
  The Sultan materials also revealed that trial counsel&#xD;
failed to discover other mitigating evidence of importance.&#xD;
Interviews with family members revealed repeated inci-&#xD;
dents of violence in the family, including an episode in&#xD;
which, as a young boy, Thompson witnessed his father&#xD;
brutally beat and rape his mother. His grandmother, with&#xD;
whom Thompson and his siblings lived after their mother&#xD;
died, subjected them to abuse and neglect. She would&#xD;
forget to feed the children, leaving them to steal money&#xD;
from under her bed to buy food. These and other circum-&#xD;
stances are detailed in sections of the Sultan report and&#xD;
deposition reproduced in the Appendix, infra.&#xD;
                              2&#xD;
   The panel also responded unanimously and affirma-&#xD;
tively to the second question: Would federal-court access to&#xD;
the Sultan documents likely have made a significant&#xD;
difference in respect to the federal legal question at issue&#xD;
in Thompson’s habeas petition, namely, the failure of&#xD;
Thompson’s trial counsel to investigate his background?&#xD;
Trial counsel had had important indications that some-&#xD;
thing was wrong. Indeed, counsel himself had sought an&#xD;
evaluation of Thompson’s mental condition. He also was&#xD;
aware of Thompson’s violent behavior in the military, and&#xD;
knew that Thompson had said he had had auditory hallu-&#xD;
cinations all his life. He was aware, too, of the changes in&#xD;
Thompson’s behavior. Should counsel not then have&#xD;
investigated further?&#xD;
   The Sultan documents make clear that, had he done so,&#xD;
he would have had a strong answer to the State’s experts.&#xD;
Thus the documents were relevant to the outcome of the&#xD;
                 Cite as: 545 U. S. ____ (2005)            9&#xD;
&#xD;
                     BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
federal habeas proceedings. The Federal District Court&#xD;
based its grant of summary judgment on the premise that&#xD;
there was no evidence supporting Thompson’s claim. The&#xD;
documents showed that precisely such evidence was then&#xD;
available.&#xD;
                                3&#xD;
   The panel (while disagreeing about how to allocate&#xD;
blame) agreed in part about the answer to the third ques-&#xD;
tion: how these documents previously had escaped the&#xD;
panel’s attention. The judges agreed that the Sultan&#xD;
documents were not in the initial record on appeal. The&#xD;
panel’s original opinion, while mentioning both Dr. Sultan&#xD;
and Dr. Crown, assumed that neither expert had ad-&#xD;
dressed Thompson’s mental condition at the time of the&#xD;
crime. 315 F. 3d, at 583, n. 13 (“Sultan’s affidavit does not&#xD;
discuss Thompson’s mental state at the time of the offense”&#xD;
(emphasis added)); ibid. (explaining that Thompson filed a&#xD;
Rule 60(b) motion to supplement the record with Dr.&#xD;
Sultan’s report, but not mentioning that the report ad-&#xD;
dressed Thompson’s mental condition at the time of the&#xD;
offense); see also supra, at 5.&#xD;
   How had the panel overlooked the copies of the Sultan&#xD;
deposition attached to (1) the rehearing petition and (2)&#xD;
the (Rule 60(b)-related) motion to hold the appeal in abey-&#xD;
ance? As for the rehearing petition, the reason could well&#xD;
lie in the petition’s (incorrect) suggestion that the panel&#xD;
had already considered the appended document as part of&#xD;
the original record. See Pet. for Rehearing and Suggestion&#xD;
for Rehearing En Banc in No. 2:00–5516 (CA6), p. 1 (“A&#xD;
majority of this panel overlooked other proof in the record,&#xD;
including but not limited to, the expert opinion of Dr. Faye&#xD;
E. Sultan”); see also id., at 28–32. While the petition&#xD;
explains the importance of the documents, it does not&#xD;
explain the circumstances, namely, that the panel previ-&#xD;
ously had not seen these documents. Instead, it gives the&#xD;
10                  BELL v. THOMPSON&#xD;
&#xD;
                    BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
impression that counsel was simply reemphasizing a&#xD;
matter the panel had already considered. To that extent,&#xD;
the petition reduced the likelihood that the panel would&#xD;
make the connection it later made and fatally weakened&#xD;
its argument for re-hearing.&#xD;
   As for the motion to hold the appeal in abeyance, the&#xD;
panel’s failure to recognize the significance of the ap-&#xD;
pended Sultan materials is also understandable. The&#xD;
motion gives the impression that the appellate court&#xD;
would have been able to handle any problem arising from&#xD;
the exclusion of these materials in an appeal taken from&#xD;
the District Court’s Rule 60(b) decision. The appellate&#xD;
court, however, never had any such opportunity because&#xD;
counsel did not appeal the District Court’s denial of the&#xD;
Rule 60(b) motion.&#xD;
                               C&#xD;
  Once the panel understood the significance of the Sultan&#xD;
report, it had to decide what to do. An appellate court&#xD;
exists to correct legal errors made in the trial court. What&#xD;
legal error had the District Court committed? The appeal&#xD;
concerned its grant of summary judgment in the State’s&#xD;
favor. The District Court made that decision on the basis&#xD;
of the record before it, and that record apparently lacked&#xD;
the relevant documents. How then could an appeals court&#xD;
say that the District Court was wrong to grant the sum-&#xD;
mary judgment motion?&#xD;
  The panel answered this question by not holding that&#xD;
the District Court had erred. Finding that the Sultan&#xD;
documents had been “apparently negligently omitted”&#xD;
from the record, it exercised its equitable powers to sup-&#xD;
plement the record with the deposition. 373 F. 3d, at 691.&#xD;
It also found that, since the State itself had helped to&#xD;
create that document (because the State had taken Sul-&#xD;
tan’s deposition), the District Court’s reconsideration of&#xD;
the matter would not unfairly prejudice the State. And it&#xD;
                  Cite as: 545 U. S. ____ (2005)           11&#xD;
&#xD;
                     BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
noted that this case is a death case. Then, relying on its&#xD;
“inherent power to reconsider” an opinion “prior to the&#xD;
issuance of the mandate,” the court issued a new opinion,&#xD;
vacating the District Court’s grant of summary judgment&#xD;
to the State and remanding the case to the District Court&#xD;
for further proceedings on the matter. Ibid.&#xD;
                             II&#xD;
    The question before us is not whether we, as judges,&#xD;
would have come to the same conclusions as did the panel&#xD;
of the Court of Appeals. It is whether the three members&#xD;
of the appellate panel abused their discretion in reconsid-&#xD;
ering the matter and, after agreeing unanimously that&#xD;
they would have reached a different result had they con-&#xD;
sidered the overlooked evidence, vacating the District&#xD;
Court’s judgment and remanding the case.&#xD;
   The Court concludes that the panel’s reconsideration of&#xD;
the matter and decision to vacate the District Court’s&#xD;
judgment amounted to an “abuse of discretion.” Ante, at 1.&#xD;
It therefore reverses the panel’s unanimous interlocutory&#xD;
judgment remanding a capital case to the District Court&#xD;
for an evidentiary hearing. The Court lists five reasons&#xD;
why the Court of Appeals “abused its discretion.” None of&#xD;
these reasons, whether taken separately or considered&#xD;
together, stands up to examination.&#xD;
   Reason One. During the 5-month period after this Court&#xD;
denied rehearing of Thompson’s certiorari petition, during&#xD;
which time the Court of Appeals was reconsidering the&#xD;
matter, it gave “no indication that it might be revisiting its&#xD;
earlier decision.” Had it “notified” the parties, the court&#xD;
“could have spared the parties and the state judicial system&#xD;
considerable time and resources.” Ante, at 10.&#xD;
   If this consideration favors the Court’s conclusion, it&#xD;
does so to a very modest degree. For one thing, the Fed-&#xD;
eral Rules themselves neither set an unchangeable dead-&#xD;
line for issuance of a mandate nor require notice when the&#xD;
12                  BELL v. THOMPSON&#xD;
&#xD;
                    BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
court enlarges the time for issuance. Compare Fed. Rule&#xD;
App. Proc. 41(b) (2005) (“The court may shorten or extend&#xD;
the time”), with Rule 41(b) (1968) (mandate “shall” issue&#xD;
“unless the time is shortened or extended by order” (em-&#xD;
phasis added)). The Advisory Committee Notes to Rule 41&#xD;
expressly contemplate that the parties will themselves&#xD;
check the docket to determine whether the mandate has&#xD;
issued. See Advisory Committee’s 1998 Note on subd. (c)&#xD;
of Rule 41 (“[T]he parties can easily calculate the antici-&#xD;
pated date of issuance and verify issuance of the man-&#xD;
date[;] the entry of the order on the docket alerts the&#xD;
parties to that fact”). And Sixth Circuit Rules require the&#xD;
Circuit Clerk to provide all parties with copies of the&#xD;
mandate. See Internal Operating Procedure 41(a) (CA6&#xD;
2005) (“Copies of the mandate are distributed to all parties&#xD;
and the district court clerk’s office”). Thus, the State’s&#xD;
attorneys knew, or certainly should have known, that the&#xD;
mandate had not issued, and, as experienced practitioners,&#xD;
they also knew, or certainly should have known, that a&#xD;
proceeding is not technically over until the court has&#xD;
issued its mandate. And if concerned by the delay (and&#xD;
some delay in such matters is not uncommon), they could&#xD;
have asked the Circuit Clerk why the mandate had not&#xD;
issued. If necessary, they could have filed a motion seek-&#xD;
ing that information or seeking the mandate’s immediate&#xD;
issuance.&#xD;
  For another thing, since notification is a clerical duty,&#xD;
the panel may have thought the parties had been notified.&#xD;
One of the judges on the panel could well have instructed&#xD;
the Circuit Clerk not to issue the mandate, and then&#xD;
simply have assumed that the Clerk would notify the&#xD;
parties of that fact (though the Clerk, perhaps inadver-&#xD;
tently, did not do so). Why would the court want to hide&#xD;
what it was doing from the parties? Once we apply a&#xD;
presumption of regularity to the panel’s actions, we must&#xD;
assume that the failure to notify the parties was likely due&#xD;
                  Cite as: 545 U. S. ____ (2005)           13&#xD;
&#xD;
                     BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
to a simple clerical error.&#xD;
   Further, the prejudice to the State that troubles the&#xD;
Court was likely small or nonexistent. The need to reset&#xD;
an execution date is not uncommon, and the state court’s&#xD;
execution order explicitly foresaw that possibility. See 373&#xD;
F. 3d, at 692 (Tennessee Supreme Court order set Thomp-&#xD;
son’s execution date for August 19, 2004, “unless other-&#xD;
wise ordered by this Court or other appropriate authority”&#xD;
(internal quotation marks omitted)). Moreover, the State&#xD;
has not even argued—despite ample opportunity to do&#xD;
so—that the further proceedings ordered by the panel&#xD;
would actually have required it to set a new date.&#xD;
   Finally, the State did not, by way of a petition for re-&#xD;
hearing, make any of its “failure to notify” arguments to&#xD;
the Court of Appeals. Although the law does not require&#xD;
the State to seek rehearing, such a petition would have&#xD;
permitted the panel to explain why the State was not&#xD;
notified and possibly to explore the matter of prejudice.&#xD;
There is no reason to reward the State for not filing a&#xD;
petition by assuming prejudice where none appears to&#xD;
exist.&#xD;
   Given the State’s likely knowledge that the mandate&#xD;
had not issued, the existence of avenues for resolving any&#xD;
uncertainty, and the small likelihood of prejudice, the lack&#xD;
of notice does not significantly advance the Court’s “abuse&#xD;
of discretion” finding. Indeed, if the Court believes that&#xD;
the Court of Appeals could have issued a revised opinion&#xD;
correcting its earlier judgment if only it had given notice to&#xD;
the parties, the sanction it now imposes—outright rever-&#xD;
sal—is far out of proportion to the crime.&#xD;
   Reason Two. The court’s “opportunity to consider” the&#xD;
Sultan evidence “at the rehearing stage is yet another&#xD;
factor supporting” the abuse-of-discretion “determination.”&#xD;
Ante, at 12. I agree that it is unfortunate that, upon&#xD;
review of the rehearing petition, the panel failed to make&#xD;
the connection that would have allowed it, at that time, to&#xD;
14                   BELL v. THOMPSON&#xD;
&#xD;
                     BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
reach the same conclusion it reached later. Still, the&#xD;
petition wrongly implied that the Sultan documents were&#xD;
part of the original appeal. Because it did not request&#xD;
rehearing on the ground that the documents were not in&#xD;
the record, it did not offer a genuine “opportunity to con-&#xD;
sider” the Sultan evidence.&#xD;
   Under these circumstances, I cannot agree that the&#xD;
court’s opportunity to consider these documents at the&#xD;
rehearing stage should militate in favor of finding an&#xD;
abuse of discretion. To the contrary, I believe we should&#xD;
encourage, rather than discourage, an appellate panel,&#xD;
when it learns that it has made a serious mistake, to take&#xD;
advantage of an opportunity to correct it, rather than to&#xD;
ignore the problem.&#xD;
   Reason Three. The “Sultan evidence . . . is not of such a&#xD;
character as to warrant [a] . . . departure from standard&#xD;
appellate procedures” because “the evidence was unlikely to&#xD;
have altered the District Court’s resolution of Thompson’s&#xD;
ineffective-assistance-of-counsel claim.” Ante, at 14. That&#xD;
is to say, given the expert testimony in the trial court, the&#xD;
Sultan evidence is unlikely meaningfully to have strength-&#xD;
ened Thompson’s claim before the Federal District Court.&#xD;
Ante, at 14–15.&#xD;
   This conclusion is wrong. The Court argues the follow-&#xD;
ing: (1) Dr. Sultan’s conclusion rests in significant part&#xD;
upon interviews with three witnesses, Thompson’s grand-&#xD;
mother and sister (with whom Dr. Sultan spoke directly)&#xD;
and his girlfriend (whose interview with a defense investi-&#xD;
gator Dr. Sultan reviewed); (2) since all three of these&#xD;
witnesses testified at sentencing, Thompson’s counsel&#xD;
must have consulted them at the time; and (3)&#xD;
“[c]onsultation with these witnesses, when combined with&#xD;
the opinions of [the State’s expert] and [Thompson’s ex-&#xD;
pert], provided an adequate basis for Thompson’s attor-&#xD;
neys to conclude that focusing on Thompson’s mental&#xD;
health was not the best strategy.” Ante, at 16. The Court&#xD;
                 Cite as: 545 U. S. ____ (2005)          15&#xD;
&#xD;
                    BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
then says that trial counsel’s “strategy” may have been “a&#xD;
mistake,” ante, at 17, but apparently not enough of a&#xD;
mistake to amount to inadequate assistance of counsel.&#xD;
   But how do the Court’s conclusions follow from the&#xD;
premises? Dr. Sultan’s interview of the three witnesses&#xD;
apparently turned up new information, indeed, crucial&#xD;
information. Why does that fact not tend show that trial&#xD;
counsel’s own “consultation” with those witnesses was&#xD;
inadequate? Or, if trial counsel was aware of the informa-&#xD;
tion, why does that not tend to show that trial counsel&#xD;
hired an expert who was not qualified to assess Thomp-&#xD;
son’s mental condition, or that counsel failed adequately to&#xD;
convey the critical information to that expert? This Court&#xD;
in Wiggins v. Smith, 539 U. S. 510, 523–525 (2003), found&#xD;
trial counsel inadequate for failing to conduct a reasonable&#xD;
investigation, given notice that such an investigation&#xD;
would likely turn up important mitigating evidence. See&#xD;
also Rompilla v. Beard, ante, p. ___. Why is the same not&#xD;
true here, where Thompson’s trial counsel was fully aware&#xD;
of the need for a background investigation, and then either&#xD;
did not ask the right questions, or did not hire the right&#xD;
expert, or did not convey the right information to that&#xD;
expert? At the least, is there not a good argument to this&#xD;
effect—an argument that the Sultan documents signifi-&#xD;
cantly strengthened? All three judges on the panel&#xD;
thought so: They concluded that they would have reached&#xD;
a different result on Thompson’s ineffective-assistance-of-&#xD;
counsel claim had they been aware of the Sultan docu-&#xD;
ments. The Court does not satisfactorily explain its basis&#xD;
for second-guessing the panel on this point.&#xD;
   Reason Four. The Sultan evidence does “not come close&#xD;
to satisfying the miscarriage of justice standard under&#xD;
Calderon.” Ante, at 17 (referring to Calderon v. Thomp-&#xD;
son, 523 U. S. 538 (1998)). As the Court apparently&#xD;
agrees, see ante, at 8–9, Calderon does not apply here.&#xD;
And the panel’s basic conclusion—that consideration of&#xD;
16                   BELL v. THOMPSON&#xD;
&#xD;
                     BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
Thompson’s ineffective-assistance-of-counsel claim with-&#xD;
out the benefit of the Sultan evidence would constitute a&#xD;
grave miscarriage of justice—survives any plausible stan-&#xD;
dard of review. I can find nothing in the Court’s opinion&#xD;
that explains why the panel’s conclusion is wrong.&#xD;
   Reason Five. The Court of Appeals “did not accord the&#xD;
appropriate level of respect” to the State’s “judgment.”&#xD;
Ante, at 19. If by “judgment” the Court means to refer to&#xD;
the state court’s original judgment of conviction, this&#xD;
reason simply repeats Reason Four. The panel carefully&#xD;
examined the entire record and determined that there is a&#xD;
significant likelihood the Sultan evidence would demon-&#xD;
strate a violation of the Federal Constitution.&#xD;
   If the Court means to refer to the state court’s judgment&#xD;
not to set aside the conviction in state postconviction&#xD;
proceedings, the Court is clearly wrong. The state court&#xD;
on collateral review refused to authorize funds for a back-&#xD;
ground investigation, one for which Thompson’s expert&#xD;
then showed a strong need, and which Thompson’s expert&#xD;
now shows could well have demonstrated a significantly&#xD;
mitigating mental condition. How is it disrespectful of the&#xD;
State for a federal habeas court to identify a constitutional&#xD;
error that occurred in state-court proceedings in a capital&#xD;
case, by taking account of a key piece of evidence, mistak-&#xD;
enly omitted from the record?&#xD;
   If the Court means to refer to the State’s decision to&#xD;
proceed with the execution, I cannot possibly agree. The&#xD;
Court could not mean that any exercise by a federal court&#xD;
to correct an inadvertent, and important, evidentiary error&#xD;
is “disrespectful” of a State’s effort to proceed to execution.&#xD;
But if it does not mean “any” exercise at all, then how can&#xD;
it say the present exercise is disrespectful? The present&#xD;
exercise embodies as thorough an examination of the&#xD;
record and as significant a piece of evidence as one is&#xD;
likely to find. The process—the detail and care with which&#xD;
the Court of Appeals combed the record—does not show&#xD;
                 Cite as: 545 U. S. ____ (2005)           17&#xD;
&#xD;
                     BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
“disrespect.” It shows the contrary.&#xD;
  The upshot is that the Court’s five reasons are uncon-&#xD;
vincing. The Court simply states those reasons as conclu-&#xD;
sions. It fails to show how, or why, the unanimous panel&#xD;
erred in reaching diametrically opposite conclusions, all&#xD;
supported with detailed evidence set forth in Judge Suhr-&#xD;
heinrich’s opinion. It does not satisfactorily explain the&#xD;
evidentiary basis for its own conclusions. And, in the&#xD;
process, it loses sight of the question before us: again, not&#xD;
whether we, as judges, would have reached the same&#xD;
conclusion that the three judges on the panel reached, but&#xD;
rather whether they, having unanimously agreed that&#xD;
their earlier decision was wrong, abused their discretion in&#xD;
setting it right.&#xD;
                             III&#xD;
  Ultimately this case presents three kinds of question.&#xD;
The first is a narrow legal question. Has the Court of&#xD;
Appeals abused its discretion? For the reasons I have set&#xD;
forth, the answer to that question, legally speaking, must&#xD;
be “no.”&#xD;
  The second is an epistemological question. How, in&#xD;
respect to matters involving the legal impact of the Sultan&#xD;
report and deposition, can the Court replace the panel’s&#xD;
judgment with its own? Judge Suhrheinrich’s opinion&#xD;
demonstrates why any assessment of that legal impact&#xD;
must grow out of thorough knowledge of the record. He&#xD;
spent hundreds of hours with its numerous documents in&#xD;
order to make that assessment. Those of his conclusions&#xD;
that were shared by the other members of the panel are&#xD;
logical, rest upon record-based facts, and are nowhere&#xD;
refuted (in respect to those facts) by anything before us or&#xD;
by anything in the Court’s opinion. How can the Court&#xD;
know that the panel is wrong?&#xD;
  The third question is about basic jurisprudence. A legal&#xD;
system is based on rules; it also seeks justice in the indi-&#xD;
18                   BELL v. THOMPSON&#xD;
&#xD;
                     BREYER, J., dissenting&#xD;
&#xD;
vidual case. Sometimes these ends conflict. To take ac-&#xD;
count of such conflict, the system often grants judges a&#xD;
degree of discretion, thereby providing oil for the rule-&#xD;
based gears. When we tell the Court of Appeals that it&#xD;
cannot exercise its discretion to correct the serious error it&#xD;
discovered here, we tell courts they are not to act to cure&#xD;
serious injustice in similar cases. The consequence is to&#xD;
divorce the rule-based result from the just result. The&#xD;
American judicial system has long sought to avoid that&#xD;
divorce. Today’s decision takes an unfortunate step in the&#xD;
wrong direction.&#xD;
                 Cite as: 545 U. S. ____ (2005)         19&#xD;
&#xD;
               Appendix to opinion of BREYER, J.&#xD;
&#xD;
       APPENDIX TO OPINION OF BREYER, J.&#xD;
&#xD;
    Excerpts from the Gregory Thompson Psychological&#xD;
    Report prepared by Dr. Faye E. Sultan at the River-&#xD;
    bend Maximum Security Institution (RMSI) (July 22,&#xD;
    1999), App. 11–20.&#xD;
&#xD;
“REFERRAL QUESTIONS:&#xD;
&#xD;
“Mr. Gregory Thompson was referred for psychological&#xD;
evaluation in July, 1998 by attorney Mr. Stephen M.&#xD;
Kissinger of the Federal Defender Services of Eastern&#xD;
Tennessee Incorporated. Mr. Thompson was convicted of&#xD;
murder in 1985. This evaluation was requested to address&#xD;
the following questions:&#xD;
    “1. Mr. Thompson’s current psychological status[.]&#xD;
    “2. Mr. Thompson’s likely psychological status and&#xD;
    mental state before and surrounding the time of the&#xD;
    1985 offense.&#xD;
    “3. Social, environmental, psychological, and economic&#xD;
    factors in the life of Mr. Thompson which might have&#xD;
    be[en] considered to be mitigating in nature at the&#xD;
    time of his trial.&#xD;
“PROCEDURE:&#xD;
“Psychological evaluation of Mr. Thompson was initiated&#xD;
on August 20, 1998. This first evaluation session extended&#xD;
over a period of approximately four hours and consisted of&#xD;
clinical interview and the administration of the Minnesota&#xD;
Multiphasic Personality Inventory–2 (MMPI–2). Some&#xD;
review of prior psychological evaluation records was con-&#xD;
ducted to establish what formal psychological and neuro-&#xD;
psychological testing had been administered to Mr.&#xD;
Thompson. Levels of current intellectual and neuropsy-&#xD;
chological functioning had been recently assessed by neu-&#xD;
ropsychologist, Barry Crown, Ph.D., so no attempt was&#xD;
20                  BELL v. THOMPSON&#xD;
&#xD;
               Appendix to opinion of BREYER, J.&#xD;
&#xD;
made to replicate this type of assessment.&#xD;
“Following the 8–20–98 initial evaluation session, a very&#xD;
extensive review of legal, military, medical, prison and&#xD;
psychiatric/psychological records was initiated. A list of&#xD;
the documents examined is attached to this report.&#xD;
      .          .            .            .          .&#xD;
“. . . Two further interviews were conducted with Mr.&#xD;
Thompson for [the] limited purpose [of determining&#xD;
Thompson’s competence to participate in habeas proceed-&#xD;
ings], on 2–2–99 and 4–7–99, totaling approximately six&#xD;
hours of additional observation. Voluminous Tennessee&#xD;
Department of Corrections mental health, medical, and&#xD;
administrative records were reviewed at this time as well.&#xD;
      .          .            .            .          .&#xD;
“[T]he extensive record review conducted, the ten hours of&#xD;
clinical observations made of Mr. Thompson during the&#xD;
preceding eleven months, the interviews conducted with&#xD;
collateral informants, and the recent and past psychologi-&#xD;
cal testing which had been administered provide enough&#xD;
data to make it possible to render professional opinions&#xD;
about Mr. Thompson’s mental state at and around the&#xD;
time of the 1985 offense.&#xD;
“CLINICAL OBSERVATIONS:&#xD;
“Mr. Gregory Thompson was cooperative with the assess-&#xD;
ment procedure. He answered all questions posed to him&#xD;
and appeared to be alert, watchful and interested in the&#xD;
interview process. His speech was sometimes tangential&#xD;
and rambling. Although motor behavior appeared con-&#xD;
trolled there was a manic quality to his verbalizations.&#xD;
Mr. Thompson was oriented as to person, place and time,&#xD;
but he repeatedly expressed his firm belief that he had&#xD;
written each and every song which played on the radio.&#xD;
“Mr. Thompson displayed symptoms of psychosis during&#xD;
the two subsequent meetings. The details of these ses-&#xD;
sions will not be reviewed here.&#xD;
                 Cite as: 545 U. S. ____ (2005)           21&#xD;
&#xD;
                Appendix to opinion of BREYER, J.&#xD;
&#xD;
“FORMAL PSYCHOLOGICAL TESTING:&#xD;
“The Minnesota Multiphasic Personality lnventory–2&#xD;
(MMPI–2) was administered to Mr. Thompson on 8–20–&#xD;
98. It had been determined in other examination settings&#xD;
that Mr. Thompson’s level of reading competence exceeded&#xD;
the necessary level of 8th grade ability required for proper&#xD;
administration of this test.&#xD;
“The MMPI–2 profile produced by Mr. Thompson is con-&#xD;
sidered valid and appropriate for interpretation. Indi-&#xD;
viduals producing similar profiles are described as experi-&#xD;
encing significant psychological difficulties and chronic&#xD;
psychological maladjustment. Such individuals are con-&#xD;
sidered to be highly suspicious of others, often displaying&#xD;
paranoid features. There is indication in this profile of the&#xD;
presence of a thought disorder and the inability to manage&#xD;
emotions. The world is perceived as a threatening and&#xD;
dangerous place and fears are viewed as externally gener-&#xD;
ated and reality-based rather than as a product of an&#xD;
internally generated state. The behavior of such individu-&#xD;
als is often described as hostile, aggressive, and rebellious&#xD;
against authority. Poor impulse control, lack of trust in&#xD;
others, and low frustration tolerance may result in such&#xD;
individuals displaying rage in interpersonal relationships.&#xD;
“Individuals producing this testing profile are also de-&#xD;
scribed as experiencing depressed mood. There is the&#xD;
strong possibility that such individuals have contemplated&#xD;
suicide and report preoccupation with feeling guilty and&#xD;
unworthy. Testing items were endorsed which suggest&#xD;
memory and concentration problems, and an inability to&#xD;
make decisions.&#xD;
“RELEVANT PSYCHOLOGICAL/PSYCHIATRIC DATA&#xD;
CONTAINED IN RECORDS:&#xD;
&#xD;
“The[re] is substantial documentation throughout the&#xD;
&#xD;
Tennessee Department of Corrections records that Mr.&#xD;
&#xD;
Greg Thompson has suffered from significant mental&#xD;
&#xD;
22                   BELL v. THOMPSON&#xD;
&#xD;
                Appendix to opinion of BREYER, J.&#xD;
&#xD;
illness since at least the time of . . . his incarceration in&#xD;
1985. He has been treated almost continuously with some&#xD;
combination of major tranquilizer and/or anti-depressant&#xD;
and/or anti-anxiety medications. He has received a vari-&#xD;
ety of diagnostic labels including Psychosis, Psychosis Not&#xD;
Otherwise Specified, Paranoid Schizophrenia, Mania,&#xD;
Mixed Substance Abuse, Schizophrenia, BiPolar Affective&#xD;
Disorder, Schizoaffective Disorder, Malingering, and Adult&#xD;
Antisocial Behavior. This is clearly indicative of the Ten-&#xD;
nessee DOC mental health staff’s view that Mr. Thompson&#xD;
has experienced major mental illness throughout at least&#xD;
most of his period of incarceration. Further, there is&#xD;
extensive documentation contained in these records of&#xD;
many episodes of bizarre aggressive and/or self-destructive&#xD;
behavior.&#xD;
“INTERVIEWS WITH COLLATERAL WITNESSES:&#xD;
“Five individuals were interviewed (either by telephone or&#xD;
face-to-face) who provided significant supplemental infor-&#xD;
mation about the life circumstances and past/present&#xD;
psychological functioning of Mr. Gregory Thompson.&#xD;
“Ms. Maybelle Lamar&#xD;
“Ms. Lamar is Mr. Thompson’s maternal grandmother.&#xD;
She was interviewed by telephone on July 21, 1999. Ms.&#xD;
Lamar assumed total responsibility for the care and rear-&#xD;
ing of Mr. Thompson and his two older siblings after his&#xD;
mother was killed when Mr. Thompson was approximately&#xD;
five years old. Mr. Thompson remained in her home until&#xD;
he entered the military as a young adult.&#xD;
“Ms. Lamar recalls the period following her daughter’s&#xD;
fatal automobile accident as one of tremendous strain and&#xD;
disruption for her. She was unable to describe the reac-&#xD;
tion of the three young children to their mother’s death&#xD;
because she ‘took to my bed’ for approximately five or six&#xD;
weeks following the accident. Ms. Lamar was unable to&#xD;
                 Cite as: 545 U. S. ____ (2005)          23&#xD;
&#xD;
               Appendix to opinion of BREYER, J.&#xD;
&#xD;
attend to these children in any way at that time. She did&#xD;
not recall how they obtained food or clothing, or whether&#xD;
they were in any distress. Ms. Lamar reported that she&#xD;
was drinking alcohol quite heavily during this period and&#xD;
that she left her bed to resume household activities only&#xD;
because the children contracted a serious medical illness.&#xD;
“Ms. Lamar described Mr. Thompson as displaying signifi-&#xD;
cantly ‘different’ behavior when he returned to visit her&#xD;
following his discharge from the U. S. Navy. ‘Greg didn’t&#xD;
act the same’. Unlike the ‘eager to please’, passive, some-&#xD;
times funny, gentle boy who she had reared, Mr. Thomp-&#xD;
son was ‘angry’, ‘sometimes sad’. ‘I don’t think he wanted&#xD;
me to know what was going on with him. He mostly just&#xD;
stayed away from me.’ Ms. Lamar reported that she no-&#xD;
ticed Mr. Thompson sometimes ‘staring off into space’ or&#xD;
‘talking to himself ’. She would ask him about these be-&#xD;
haviors. ‘He’d deny it. He acted like he didn’t know what&#xD;
I was talking about.’ Ms. Lamar recalls being quite con-&#xD;
cerned about her grandson’s mental state during this time.&#xD;
She did not recall ever being asked these questions at any&#xD;
time before or during Mr. Thompson’s trial.&#xD;
“Ms. Nora Jean Hall Wharton&#xD;
“Nora Jean Wharton is Mr. Thompson’s older sister. A&#xD;
lengthy telephone interview was conducted with her on&#xD;
July 21, 1999. She grew up in the same home as Mr.&#xD;
Thompson and had continuous contact with him through-&#xD;
out his childhood. Mr. Thompson lived briefly in the home&#xD;
of his sister following his discharge from the military.&#xD;
“Ms. Wharton described Mr. Greg Thompson as a highly&#xD;
sensitive, passive, timid, emotionally vulnerable child.&#xD;
She described a childhood of great hardship. According to&#xD;
her report, their grandmother, Ms. Maybelle Lamar[,] was&#xD;
verbally abusive, neglectful of the children’s basic daily&#xD;
needs, highly critical, and unable to care properly for the&#xD;
children. Ms. Wharton described many instances of such&#xD;
24                   BELL v. THOMPSON&#xD;
&#xD;
                Appendix to opinion of BREYER, J.&#xD;
&#xD;
abuse and neglect. She described the period following&#xD;
their mother’s death as particularly chaotic and neglectful,&#xD;
recalling that often there was no food in the home and&#xD;
that the children would take money from under their&#xD;
grandmother’s mattress to go and buy food. In the period&#xD;
following their mother’s death, Ms. Wharton reported that&#xD;
her grandmother was continuously drunk and unable to&#xD;
care for her grandchildren. According to Ms. Wharton,&#xD;
Greg Thompson frequently witnessed his sister Nora being&#xD;
beaten by their grandmother.&#xD;
“Ms. Wharton further recalled that she and her younger&#xD;
brother had witnessed the brutal beating and rape of their&#xD;
mother by their biological father. She recalls Greg stand-&#xD;
ing in the scene screaming and sobbing uncontrollably.&#xD;
“Ms. Wharton reported that Greg would frequently cry at&#xD;
school during the early school years, and, as a result, was&#xD;
often the victim of intense mockery from his classmates.&#xD;
Because Ms. Wharton was in the same classroom as her&#xD;
brother she observed these behaviors and often intervened&#xD;
on her brother’s behalf. She described Mr. Thompson’s&#xD;
response to this abuse as quite passive.&#xD;
“Of particular significance is Ms. Wharton’s recollections&#xD;
about Mr. Thompson repeatedly banging his head against&#xD;
the wall of their home on many occasions during their&#xD;
early childhood. This behavior frequently followed their&#xD;
grandmother yelling at Greg ‘You have the Devil in you.’&#xD;
Mr. Thompson would tell his sister that he was attempt-&#xD;
ing to ‘knock the Devil out’ of his head in this way. Ms.&#xD;
Wharton recalls believing that this behavior was quite&#xD;
odd.&#xD;
“Following his discharge from military service, Ms. Whar-&#xD;
ton described Mr. Thompson’s behavior as significantly&#xD;
different than his prior conduct and attitude. She re-&#xD;
ported several episodes of bizarre behavior which included&#xD;
a sudden intense emotional reaction without obvious&#xD;
external provocation. Mr. Thompson would become ex-&#xD;
                 Cite as: 545 U. S. ____ (2005)           25&#xD;
&#xD;
                Appendix to opinion of BREYER, J.&#xD;
&#xD;
tremely angry, would cry and scream for a len[g]thy period&#xD;
of time, would appear as if he might or actually become&#xD;
quite physically violent or aggressive, and then would&#xD;
suddenly retreat. Ms. Thompson reported this behavior&#xD;
and her concerns about it to her grandmother. Ms. Lamar&#xD;
suggested that Ms. Wharton take her brother to the psy-&#xD;
chiatric unit of the local hospital for treatment. Ms.&#xD;
Wharton did not attempt to get any treatment for Mr.&#xD;
Thompson and reports feeling quite guilty about this.&#xD;
“Nora Jean Wharton described her own struggles with&#xD;
mental illness throughout the past fifteen years. She has&#xD;
received counseling to assist her in coping with the effects&#xD;
of her abusive childhood and she has been treated with a&#xD;
combination of a major tranquilizer (Stellazine) and anti-&#xD;
depressant medications. She reported that her younger&#xD;
half-sister Kim has also suffered from significant mental&#xD;
illness.&#xD;
“CUSTODY OFFICERS AT RMSI&#xD;
“Following the second interview conducted with Mr.&#xD;
Thompson on 2–2–99, I informally interviewed two cus-&#xD;
tody officers who escorted Mr. Thompson back to his cell.&#xD;
These officers have not as yet been identified by name.&#xD;
Both reported that they were aware that Mr. Thompson&#xD;
was quite mentally ill and that they were concerned about&#xD;
him. They further reported that they believed it would be&#xD;
in his best interest to be housed in a prison facility better&#xD;
equipped to deal with individuals experiencing severe&#xD;
mental illness.&#xD;
“MICHAEL CHAVIS&#xD;
“Federal Defender Services of Eastern Tennessee investi-&#xD;
gator, Mr. Michael Chavis, was interviewed about his July&#xD;
29 through August 2, 1998 interview with Ms. Arlene&#xD;
Cajulao in Honolulu, Hawaii. Ms. Cajulao and Mr.&#xD;
Thompson had an intimate relationship and lived together&#xD;
26                  BELL v. THOMPSON&#xD;
&#xD;
               Appendix to opinion of BREYER, J.&#xD;
&#xD;
for approximately four years, from 1980 to 1984.&#xD;
“Mr. Chavis reported that Ms. Cajulao described Mr.&#xD;
Thompson as displaying increasingly bizarre behavior&#xD;
during the latter part of their relationship. Similar to&#xD;
descriptions proved by Ms. Nora Wharton, Ms. Cajulao&#xD;
reported several episodes of ‘paranoid’ and aggressive&#xD;
behavior which had no apparent external antecedent. She&#xD;
reported that Mr. Thompson sometimes thought that&#xD;
people were ‘after’ him. He would close all the curtains in&#xD;
the house because he did not want the person who was&#xD;
‘looking’ for him to see him through the curtains. She&#xD;
remembers being quite concerned about Mr. Thompson’s&#xD;
mental state.&#xD;
“SUMMARY AND CONCLUSIONS:&#xD;
“Mr. Gregory Thompson has experienced symptoms of&#xD;
major mental illness throughout his adult life. Indeed,&#xD;
there is information available which suggests that Mr.&#xD;
Thompson was displaying significant signs of mental&#xD;
illness from the time he was a small child. Self-injurious&#xD;
behavior is reported as early as six years old. There is&#xD;
extensive documentation contained within the records&#xD;
reviewed for this evaluation that Mr. Thompson has ex-&#xD;
perienced a thought disorder and/or an affective disorder&#xD;
of some type for many years.&#xD;
“It is my opinion that Mr. Gregory Thompson is most&#xD;
appropriately diagnosed, according to the Diagnostic and&#xD;
Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, Fourth Edition, as&#xD;
having Schizoaffective Disorder, Bipolar Type. As is&#xD;
typical of this illness, symptoms became apparent in early&#xD;
adulthood. Mr. Thompson was suffering serious mental&#xD;
illness at the time of the 1985 offense for which he has&#xD;
been convicted and sentenced. This mental illness would&#xD;
have substantially impaired Mr. Thompson’s ability to&#xD;
conform his conduct to the requirements of the law.&#xD;
“Further, Mr. Thompson was the victim of severe child-&#xD;
                 Cite as: 545 U. S. ____ (2005)          27&#xD;
&#xD;
                Appendix to opinion of BREYER, J.&#xD;
&#xD;
hood emotional abuse and physical neglect. His family&#xD;
background is best described as highly neglectful and &#xD;
&#xD;
economically deprived. Mr. Thompson repeatedly wit&#xD;
        -&#xD;
nessed episodes of violence during his childhood in which &#xD;
&#xD;
one family member assaulted or brutalized another. &#xD;
&#xD;
There are significant aspects of Mr. Thompson’s social&#xD;
&#xD;
history that have been recognized as mitigating in other &#xD;
&#xD;
capital cases &#xD;
&#xD;
“It is important to note that all of the information related &#xD;
&#xD;
to Mr. Thompson’s early mental illness and social history &#xD;
&#xD;
was available at the time of his 1985 trial. &#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
“[signed]&#xD;
&#xD;
“Faye E. Sultan, Ph.D.” &#xD;
&#xD;
&#xD;
                         *     *      *&#xD;
&#xD;
    Excerpts from the Deposition of Dr. Faye E. Sultan&#xD;
    (July 22, 1999), Id., at 71–73, 76–80.&#xD;
   “Q. What indicates to you or what indicia are there for&#xD;
you that suggest Mr. Thompson was displaying significant&#xD;
signs of mental illness from the time he was a small child?&#xD;
How do you arrive at that conclusion?&#xD;
   “A. .            .            .           .            .&#xD;
   “By the time of the first grade, Mr. Thompson, when he&#xD;
was being yelled at by his grandmother, she was report-&#xD;
edly verbally abusive in the following fashion: She would&#xD;
yell at him you have the devil in you, boy. [His sister, Ms.&#xD;
Wharton] would then observe Mr. Thompson standing or&#xD;
sitting beside a wall repeatedly banging his head into the&#xD;
wall. She, in her role as protector of him, would ask him&#xD;
what was going on, and he would tell her he was trying to&#xD;
knock the devil out of his head. She recalls at the time,&#xD;
although she was quite young herself, being worried about&#xD;
his behavior and thinking of it as very odd.&#xD;
28                   BELL v. THOMPSON&#xD;
&#xD;
                Appendix to opinion of BREYER, J.&#xD;
&#xD;
     .            .           .             .           .&#xD;
   “Q. Sort of a self-punishment or a self-exorcism type&#xD;
thing?&#xD;
   “A. A self-injurious behavior is what we would call it I&#xD;
think. Mr. Thompson, when he was Greg, in the first and&#xD;
second and third grade had rather frequent hysterical&#xD;
crying episodes in classrooms that Ms. Wharton recalls&#xD;
also as very unusual in the context of his schoolroom&#xD;
situation. She describes him as being the subject of tor-&#xD;
ment on the part of the students because he behaved in an&#xD;
odd fashion. Sometimes he would simply begin to cry and&#xD;
wail and scream and apparently made a sound like a fire&#xD;
engine when he was sobbing and developed the nickname&#xD;
Fire Engine. That’s reported in the trial transcript. She&#xD;
told me much more detail about actually the extent of&#xD;
those kind[s] of emotional outbursts.&#xD;
   “At home it was rather common for Mr. Thompson to&#xD;
begin to cry and scream during times when Ms. Wharton&#xD;
herself was being beaten by their grandmother. Ms.&#xD;
Wharton was the victim of physical abuse on the part of&#xD;
the grandmother. Mr. Thompson observed much of this&#xD;
since they were together virtually all of the time, and Nora&#xD;
Wharton was not really permitted much interaction out-&#xD;
side of their home.&#xD;
     .            .           .             .           .&#xD;
   “Q. Your diagnosis for Mr. Thompson is schizoaffective&#xD;
disorder, comma, bipolar type. What leads you to that&#xD;
diagnosis from what you’ve reviewed and your testing&#xD;
results?&#xD;
   “A. What leads me to the diagnosis is that there is a&#xD;
long history, perhaps at this point almost a 20-year his-&#xD;
tory, of simultaneous thought disorder on the part of Mr.&#xD;
Thompson documented throughout all the records, and&#xD;
affective disorder, emotional disorder, being unable to&#xD;
regulate his emotions, sometimes falling into the pits of&#xD;
despair and becoming suicidal, sometimes becoming&#xD;
                 Cite as: 545 U. S. ____ (2005)           29&#xD;
&#xD;
                Appendix to opinion of BREYER, J.&#xD;
&#xD;
highly agitated and manic and having too much energy,&#xD;
too much exuberance, and grandiose thinking.             The&#xD;
thought disorder is manifested in persecutory ideas, delu-&#xD;
sions of grandeur—lots of different kinds of delusions&#xD;
actually—auditory hallucinations that he sometimes&#xD;
admits to, sometimes suspected by the doctors who are&#xD;
doing the examination.&#xD;
   “The psychological testing early on in Mr. Thompson’s&#xD;
incarceration confirm[s] the presence of a psychotic proc-&#xD;
ess. There was an MMPI administered to him by a prison&#xD;
psychologist in 1990 that is described as valid and indica-&#xD;
tive of psychotic process, and throughout the prison record&#xD;
he receives a variety of diagnoses that take into account&#xD;
both thought disorder and affective illness.&#xD;
   “The very best diagnosis to describe all of the complex of&#xD;
symptoms that I just talked to you about is schizoaffective&#xD;
disorder, bipolar type.&#xD;
   “Q. You note in your report Mr. Thompson was ob-&#xD;
served having a significant change in behavior after he&#xD;
was discharged from the Navy. What significance do you&#xD;
attach to that fact?&#xD;
   “A. Well. . . [p]rior to his entry into the military Mr.&#xD;
Thompson is described almost uniformly . . . as passive, as&#xD;
compliant, as eager to please, as gentle, as timid, as eager&#xD;
to run from attacks.&#xD;
   “At some point . . . he began to notice that people were&#xD;
trying to hurt him all the time, that officers and other&#xD;
people of his rank and slightly above his rank attempted&#xD;
to provoke him, that they sometimes physically assaulted&#xD;
him, that he thought he was being followed a lot, and that&#xD;
he sometimes struck out in what he thought was defense&#xD;
and then later found out from other people who he knew&#xD;
and trusted that there wasn’t anything to defend against&#xD;
or that there might not have been anything to defend&#xD;
against.&#xD;
   “Q. This is what he related to you during your interview&#xD;
30                  BELL v. THOMPSON&#xD;
&#xD;
               Appendix to opinion of BREYER, J.&#xD;
&#xD;
last August?&#xD;
  “A. Right. The people who saw him after the military&#xD;
each were struck by how very different he seemed. That&#xD;
was the word that kept being used, ‘different.’ Sometimes&#xD;
the people I was speaking to were not able to describe&#xD;
what different meant, but, for example, the grandmother&#xD;
said that he was different as in not right, that he wasn’t&#xD;
himself. Ms. Wharton tells me that the grandmother was&#xD;
very well aware that he was in deep psychological distress,&#xD;
and, in fact, the grandmother suggested that he be taken&#xD;
to the psychiatric unit at Grady Hospital in Atlanta, I&#xD;
believe, for treatment. The grandmother observed him&#xD;
staring off into space for long periods of time. She ob-&#xD;
served him mumbling to himself. When she asked him&#xD;
what he was doing, he told her he had no idea what she&#xD;
was talking about. She said that was very different from&#xD;
the boy who left her to go into service.&#xD;
  “The sister has even a better glimpse of him than that,&#xD;
because he actually went to live with her for a while, and&#xD;
she said he was bizarre. She described him as paranoid.&#xD;
She said that he would explode for no reason at all, that&#xD;
she was afraid of him for the very first time in her life,&#xD;
that they had always been terribly close, the sort of close&#xD;
where if there was only one piece of bread to eat they&#xD;
would share it, that they always looked out for one an-&#xD;
other, and that suddenly he was behaving in ways that&#xD;
she simply could not identify. She described three very&#xD;
serious episodes of aggression and emotional upset that&#xD;
she said are what led her to approach her grandmother&#xD;
about what to do for treatment for him.&#xD;
    .            .            .          .            .&#xD;
  “Q. You state that the schizoaffective disorder, bipolar&#xD;
type, would substantially impair Mr. Thompson’s ability to&#xD;
conform his conduct to the requirements of the law. How&#xD;
so?&#xD;
  “A. There are points in time when Mr. Thompson is out&#xD;
                  Cite as: 545 U. S. ____ (2005)           31&#xD;
&#xD;
                Appendix to opinion of BREYER, J.&#xD;
&#xD;
of contact with reality. He is responding to situations that&#xD;
simply don’t exist or that he perceives in extremely exag-&#xD;
gerated or different form. A person is not able to conform&#xD;
one’s conduct to the law if you are frankly delusional or&#xD;
hallucinating in some way. Mr. Thompson over the years&#xD;
has had both of those symptoms.&#xD;
   “Q. So it’s this delusional aspect of this disorder that is&#xD;
the main factor that would keep him from having the&#xD;
ability to conform his conduct to the requirements of law,&#xD;
if I understand you correctly?&#xD;
   “A. Is it the main factor? Let me say that I think it’s at&#xD;
least as potent a factor if not more as the other aspect of&#xD;
his mental illness, which is that he has emotional disregu-&#xD;
lation.&#xD;
   “Q. Meaning?&#xD;
   “A. Meaning Mr. Thompson often is not in control of his&#xD;
emotions. He has episodes of rage, of aggression, that he&#xD;
doesn’t understand or relate to very well. He’s told about&#xD;
them later. Sometimes he remembers them, sometimes he&#xD;
doesn’t. He is often embarrassed about his behavior af-&#xD;
terwards, but there are points at which I believe he’s not&#xD;
in control of what he’s doing.&#xD;
   “Q. When you say ‘he’s not in control of what he’s do-&#xD;
ing,’ are you saying that it’s impulsive behavior?&#xD;
   “A. If I am emotionally disregulated, if I’m over-aroused&#xD;
and overreactive and I operate out of a faulty belief sys-&#xD;
tem, so that not only do I have the impulse to do things&#xD;
that I ordinarily wouldn’t, but I also think things are&#xD;
going on that aren’t, I have a combination in which yes, I&#xD;
suppose you could call it impulse, but you also have to&#xD;
take the notion into account that it might be an impulse to&#xD;
do something that doesn’t make any sense.&#xD;
   “Q. Does this disorder prevent Mr. Thompson from&#xD;
planning his activities?&#xD;
   “A. Sometimes, yes, it does.&#xD;
   “Q. And so the inability to plan, would that be a factor&#xD;
32                  BELL v. THOMPSON&#xD;
&#xD;
               Appendix to opinion of BREYER, J.&#xD;
&#xD;
that would prevent him from conforming his conduct to&#xD;
the requirements of the law?&#xD;
  “A. If that were in operation at some time. In the his-&#xD;
tory of the Department of Corrections’ mental health&#xD;
records, when he’s properly medicated I don’t think that’s&#xD;
true about him.&#xD;
  “Q. Is it your professional opinion, then, that when he is&#xD;
medicated he has the ability to plan, but when he is not&#xD;
medicated he does not always have the ability to plan?&#xD;
  “A. Those two things are true. It’s also true that if he’s&#xD;
inadequately medicated or improperly medicated he&#xD;
doesn’t have the ability to plan anything. I don’t know&#xD;
whether he has impulses. I think he’s all impulse, so to&#xD;
have impulses implies that there’s a part of you that’s not&#xD;
impulsive. For example, when Mr. Chavis and I saw him&#xD;
during my second interview with him, he could not have&#xD;
planned anything at all, not beyond the nanosecond in&#xD;
which he was experiencing the world. But he was receiv-&#xD;
ing psychotropic medications at the time, so that’s why I&#xD;
have to put that qualifier in there.”&#xD;
&lt;/pre&gt;</opinion>