<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><opinion id="1695921" path="/scotus/9G92/skidmore-v-pittsburg-c-st-lr-co/" sha1="6f887d9aa7064cdb276bf3bd85d2616e50dd0f85" court="Supreme Court of the United States" time_retrieved="2013-10-30 07:08:56.309357+00:00" date_filed="1884-10-27" precedential_status="Published" local_path="" federal_cite_one="112 U.S. 33" case_name="Skidmore v. Pittsburg, C. &amp; St. LR Co." judges="Waite" nature_of_suit="" source="lawbox" blocked="False" date_blocked="None" extracted_by_ocr="False">&lt;div&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;b&gt;112 U.S. 33 (1884)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h1&gt;SKIDMORE &amp;amp; Others&lt;br&gt;
v.&lt;br&gt;
PITTSBURG, CINCINNATI &amp;amp; ST. LOUIS RAILWAY COMPANY.&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Supreme Court of United States.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;Submitted October 17, 1884.&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;Decided October 27, 1884.&lt;/center&gt;
IN ERROR TO THE CIRCUIT COURT OF THE UNITED STATES FOR THE NORTHERN DISTRICT OF ILLINOIS.
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="star-pagination"&gt;*34&lt;/span&gt; &lt;i&gt;Mr. George Willard&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Mr. George Driggs&lt;/i&gt; for plaintiffs in error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No counsel appeared for defendant in error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="star-pagination"&gt;*36&lt;/span&gt; MR. CHIEF JUSTICE WAITE delivered the opinion of the court. He stated the facts in the foregoing language and continued:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The judgment below was clearly right. The Columbus, Chicago &amp;amp; Indiana Central Company was, in equity, the owner of the property when the lease was made and when the Pittsburg, Cincinnati &amp;amp; St. Louis Company went into possession under it. The deed executed in February, 1872, pursuant to the contract of purchase, converted the equitable title of the Columbus, Chicago &amp;amp; Indiana Central Company into a legal title, which at once, by operation of law, inured to the benefit of the Pittsburg, Cincinnati &amp;amp; St. Louis Company under its lease. All the rights of William B. Skidmore, as against the property, accrued long after those of the Pittsburg, Cincinnati &amp;amp; St. Louis Company and are subject to the title of that company. Such being the case, it is entirely unnecessary to inquire whether the Skidmores acquired a valid title to the property as against the Columbus, Chicago &amp;amp; Indiana Central Company. The Pittsburg, Cincinnati &amp;amp; St. Louis Company is entitled to the possession, whether that title be good or bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;The judgment is affirmed.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</opinion>