<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><opinion id="87837" path="/scotus/s7r/the-gray-jacket/" sha1="e3062ca876bc04fde997d16d1adb2f3450071796" court="Supreme Court of the United States" time_retrieved="2010-04-28 16:01:25+00:00" date_filed="1867-04-15" precedential_status="Published" local_path="" federal_cite_one="72 U.S. 370" scotus_early_cite="5 Wall. 370" case_name="The Gray Jacket" nature_of_suit="" source="lawbox merged with resource.org" blocked="False" date_blocked="None" extracted_by_ocr="False">&lt;div&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span class="citation no-link"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;72&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;370&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; (____)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span class="citation no-link"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;Wall.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;370&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h1&gt;THE GRAY JACKET&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Supreme Court of United States.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="star-pagination"&gt;*371&lt;/span&gt; The CHIEF JUSTICE delivered the opinion of the court on this point:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The court has considered the question whether counsel shall be heard in this cause on behalf of the Treasury Department, and has instructed me to say that in causes where the United States is a party, and is represented by the Attorney-General or the Assistant Attorney-General, or special counsel employed by the Attorney-General, no counsel can be heard in opposition on behalf of any other of the departments of the government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the present case, however, the argument has doubtless proceeded under the impression at the bar that counsel would be heard on behalf of the Treasury Department, and the court is desirous of all the light that can be derived from the fullest discussion. The counsel for the Treasury Department may be heard, therefore, if he sees fit, on behalf of the claimant, and two hours will be allowed for the argument, without prejudice to the time which remains to the counsel who opened the cause, for reply to the Attorney-General and the counsel for the captors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</opinion>