<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><opinion id="88073" path="/scotus/sbv/nailor-v-williams/" sha1="41d5b64ee926d7e1d1bba1d7ffdc340e802ebd54" court="Supreme Court of the United States" time_retrieved="2010-04-28 16:01:30+00:00" date_filed="1869-11-18" precedential_status="Published" local_path="" federal_cite_one="75 U.S. 107" scotus_early_cite="8 Wall. 107" case_name="Nailor v. Williams" judges="Miller" nature_of_suit="" source="lawbox merged with resource.org" blocked="False" date_blocked="None" extracted_by_ocr="False" cited_by="316088,101681">&lt;div&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span class="citation no-link"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;75&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;107&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; (____)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span class="citation no-link"&gt;&lt;span class="volume"&gt;8&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="reporter"&gt;Wall.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="page"&gt;107&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;h1&gt;NAILOR&lt;br&gt;
v.&lt;br&gt;
WILLIAMS.&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Supreme Court of United States.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="star-pagination"&gt;*108&lt;/span&gt; Messrs. Brent and Phillips, for the plaintiff in error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Bradley, contra.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="star-pagination"&gt;*109&lt;/span&gt; Mr. Justice MILLER delivered the opinion of the court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a question is asked of a witness on the stand, the answer to which is pertinent and legal testimony, and the court refuses to permit the witness to answer, this is error which a revising court will correct, because the injury to the party consists in the refusal of the court to permit the answer to be given, and he can do nothing more to prove the wrong done him than to show that he asked a legal question, the answer to which, by the action of the court, was denied him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But where a question is asked which is illegal only because it may elicit improper testimony, and the court permits it to be answered against the objection of the other party, the injury done the party is by the answer, and notwithstanding the erroneous ruling of the court, if the witness knows nothing of the matter to which he is interrogated, or if his answer is favorable to the objecting party, it works him no injury. If it does, he can show it by making the answer a part of the bill of exceptions, and unless he does this there is no error of which a revising court can take notice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this reason, and also because there is nothing in the bill of exceptions which enables us to say that the questions themselves exceeded the reasonable license which a court, in its discretion, may allow in cross-examination, we are of opinion that no error is shown by these bills of exception.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As they constitute the only matters alleged against the judgment of the court below, it is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AFFIRMED.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</opinion>