<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<opinion>
   <metadata>
      <case_name>Watts v. United States</case_name>
      <id>107904</id>
      <date_filed>1969-04-21</date_filed>
      <judges>Per Curiam</judges>
      <nature_of_suit/>
      <citation>
         <volume>394</volume>
         <reporter>U.S.</reporter>
         <page>705</page>
         <lexis_cite/>
      </citation>
      <federal_cite_one>394 U.S. 705</federal_cite_one>
      <cited_by>
         <case>2485906</case>
         <case>2471882</case>
         <case>2465594</case>
         <case>2367075</case>
         <case>2355073</case>
         <case>2341603</case>
         <case>2335474</case>
         <case>2305962</case>
         <case>2278940</case>
         <case>2276742</case>
         <case>2171748</case>
         <case>2151477</case>
         <case>2145424</case>
         <case>2143196</case>
         <case>2077617</case>
         <case>1996194</case>
         <case>1819095</case>
         <case>1711987</case>
         <case>1612341</case>
         <case>1611761</case>
         <case>1611644</case>
         <case>1599683</case>
         <case>1599081</case>
         <case>1542311</case>
         <case>1533806</case>
         <case>1519008</case>
         <case>1489964</case>
         <case>1467193</case>
         <case>1462169</case>
         <case>1459347</case>
         <case>1452401</case>
         <case>1442799</case>
         <case>1435629</case>
         <case>1434532</case>
         <case>1433861</case>
         <case>1426989</case>
         <case>1402683</case>
         <case>1383204</case>
         <case>1304595</case>
         <case>1302746</case>
         <case>1249273</case>
         <case>1234691</case>
         <case>1228180</case>
         <case>1225990</case>
         <case>1208483</case>
         <case>1208061</case>
         <case>1196196</case>
         <case>1195859</case>
         <case>1156738</case>
         <case>1122506</case>
         <case>1115665</case>
         <case>1093249</case>
         <case>901475</case>
         <case>900894</case>
         <case>845584</case>
         <case>842997</case>
         <case>358121</case>
         <case>328045</case>
         <case>1065477</case>
         <case>1065473</case>
         <case>1065187</case>
         <case>1063095</case>
         <case>1059424</case>
         <case>1041305</case>
         <case>1038357</case>
         <case>1037258</case>
         <case>1030505</case>
         <case>1027243</case>
         <case>1024451</case>
         <case>993029</case>
         <case>987265</case>
         <case>904120</case>
         <case>880587</case>
         <case>879179</case>
         <case>875382</case>
         <case>867453</case>
         <case>865398</case>
         <case>857640</case>
         <case>857100</case>
         <case>844258</case>
         <case>813181</case>
         <case>807790</case>
         <case>807716</case>
         <case>807412</case>
         <case>803268</case>
         <case>793933</case>
         <case>792038</case>
         <case>791592</case>
         <case>790629</case>
         <case>790311</case>
         <case>789967</case>
         <case>789818</case>
         <case>788171</case>
         <case>787608</case>
         <case>785747</case>
         <case>784960</case>
         <case>783269</case>
         <case>779594</case>
         <case>779397</case>
         <case>779282</case>
         <case>778045</case>
         <case>777725</case>
         <case>776461</case>
         <case>774758</case>
         <case>773469</case>
         <case>772636</case>
         <case>770308</case>
         <case>768755</case>
         <case>765858</case>
         <case>761276</case>
         <case>760367</case>
         <case>760240</case>
         <case>755620</case>
         <case>753544</case>
         <case>747616</case>
         <case>741766</case>
         <case>739286</case>
         <case>733382</case>
         <case>723735</case>
         <case>722482</case>
         <case>712968</case>
         <case>691051</case>
         <case>689137</case>
         <case>687390</case>
         <case>683501</case>
         <case>681631</case>
         <case>681316</case>
         <case>681155</case>
         <case>675762</case>
         <case>673194</case>
         <case>668598</case>
         <case>662471</case>
         <case>661459</case>
         <case>656069</case>
         <case>655992</case>
         <case>654625</case>
         <case>654620</case>
         <case>625913</case>
         <case>623947</case>
         <case>621667</case>
         <case>621623</case>
         <case>617778</case>
         <case>614270</case>
         <case>613104</case>
         <case>612849</case>
         <case>608123</case>
         <case>590330</case>
         <case>578246</case>
         <case>577160</case>
         <case>573893</case>
         <case>573121</case>
         <case>571467</case>
         <case>569827</case>
         <case>562684</case>
         <case>557824</case>
         <case>557708</case>
         <case>553940</case>
         <case>548945</case>
         <case>544673</case>
         <case>542010</case>
         <case>541812</case>
         <case>536229</case>
         <case>536177</case>
         <case>528530</case>
         <case>518921</case>
         <case>516519</case>
         <case>505870</case>
         <case>505850</case>
         <case>498504</case>
         <case>492919</case>
         <case>485272</case>
         <case>484914</case>
         <case>483891</case>
         <case>480220</case>
         <case>463377</case>
         <case>462751</case>
         <case>458574</case>
         <case>457082</case>
         <case>443935</case>
         <case>443045</case>
         <case>442849</case>
         <case>440485</case>
         <case>437122</case>
         <case>426305</case>
         <case>426273</case>
         <case>419146</case>
         <case>415591</case>
         <case>411281</case>
         <case>400089</case>
         <case>399958</case>
         <case>399372</case>
         <case>368200</case>
         <case>362265</case>
         <case>360362</case>
         <case>352425</case>
         <case>335138</case>
         <case>330199</case>
         <case>327113</case>
         <case>324792</case>
         <case>318522</case>
         <case>315447</case>
         <case>313564</case>
         <case>304430</case>
         <case>304381</case>
         <case>303587</case>
         <case>302624</case>
         <case>300530</case>
         <case>299122</case>
         <case>295291</case>
         <case>294765</case>
         <case>291934</case>
         <case>290817</case>
         <case>290627</case>
         <case>288469</case>
         <case>288073</case>
         <case>287470</case>
         <case>287452</case>
         <case>286720</case>
         <case>286181</case>
         <case>222198</case>
         <case>221261</case>
         <case>218709</case>
         <case>203199</case>
         <case>197526</case>
         <case>197264</case>
         <case>172598</case>
         <case>171216</case>
         <case>165582</case>
         <case>160828</case>
         <case>157548</case>
         <case>157333</case>
         <case>127908</case>
         <case>112774</case>
         <case>111946</case>
         <case>110798</case>
         <case>109284</case>
         <case>68210</case>
         <case>65183</case>
         <case>53962</case>
         <case>39245</case>
         <case>37076</case>
         <case>25528</case>
         <case>21907</case>
         <case>6998</case>
         <case>1368</case>
         <case>540</case>
         <case>385</case>
      </cited_by>
      <precedential_status>Published</precedential_status>
      <download_url/>
      <source>lawbox merged with resource.org</source>
   </metadata>
   <body><div>
      <span class="citation no-link">
         <span class="volume">394</span>
         <span class="reporter">U.S.</span>
         <span class="page">705</span>
      </span> (1969) WATTS v. UNITED STATES. No. 1107, Misc. <p>Supreme Court of United States.</p>
      Decided April 21, 1969. ON PETITION FOR WRIT OF CERTIORARI TO THE UNITED STATES COURT OF
      APPEALS FOR THE DISTRICT OF COLUMBIA CIRCUIT. <p>Joseph Forer for petitioner.</p>
      <p>Solicitor General Griswold for the United States.</p>
      <p>Ralph J. Temple, Melvin L. Wulf, and Lawrence Speiser for the American Civil Liberties
         Union et al. as amici curiae.</p>
      <p>PER CURIAM.</p>
      <p>After a jury trial in the United States District Court for the District of Columbia,
         petitioner was convicted of violating a 1917 statute which prohibits any person from
         "knowingly and willfully . . . [making] any threat to take the life of or to inflict bodily
         harm upon the President of the United States . . . ."<span class="sup">[*]</span> The
         incident <span class="star-pagination">*706</span> which led to petitioner's arrest
         occurred on August 27, 1966, during a public rally on the Washington Monument grounds. The
         crowd present broke up into small discussion groups and petitioner joined a gathering
         scheduled to discuss police brutality. Most of those in the group were quite young, either
         in their teens or early twenties. Petitioner, who himself was 18 years old, entered into
         the discussion after one member of the group suggested that the young people present should
         get more education before expressing their views. According to an investigator for the Army
         Counter Intelligence Corps who was present, petitioner responded: "They always holler at us
         to get an education. And now I have already received my draft classification as 1-A and I
         have got to report for my physical this Monday coming. I am not going. If they ever make me
         carry a rifle the first man I want to get in my sights is L. B. J." "They are not going to
         make me kill my black brothers." On the basis of this statement, the jury found that
         petitioner had committed a felony by knowingly and willfully threatening the President. The
         United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit affirmed by a
         two-to-one vote. 131 U. S. App. D. C. 125, 402 F. 2d 676 (1968). We reverse.</p>
      <p>At the close of the Government's case, petitioner's trial counsel moved for a judgment of
         acquittal. He contended that there was "absolutely no evidence on the basis of which the
         jury would be entitled to find that [petitioner] made a threat against the life of the
         President." <span class="star-pagination">*707</span> He stressed the fact that
         petitioner's statement was made during a political debate, that it was expressly made
         conditional upon an event&#x97;induction into the Armed Forces&#x97;which petitioner vowed
         would never occur, and that both petitioner and the crowd laughed after the statement was
         made. He concluded, "Now actually what happened here in all this was a kind of very crude
         offensive method of stating a political opposition to the President. What he was saying, he
         says, I don't want to shoot black people because I don't consider them my enemy, and if
         they put a rifle in my hand it is the people that put the rifle in my hand, as symbolized
         by the President, who are my real enemy." We hold that the trial judge erred in denying
         this motion.</p>
      <p>Certainly the statute under which petitioner was convicted is constitutional on its face.
         The Nation undoubtedly has a valid, even an overwhelming, interest in protecting the safety
         of its Chief Executive and in allowing him to perform his duties without interference from
         threats of physical violence. See H. R. Rep. No. 652, 64th Cong., 1st Sess. (1916).
         Nevertheless, a statute such as this one, which makes criminal a form of pure speech, must
         be interpreted with the commands of the First Amendment clearly in mind. What is a threat
         must be distinguished from what is constitutionally protected speech.</p>
      <p>The judges in the Court of Appeals differed over whether or not the "willfullness"
         requirement of the statute implied that a defendant must have intended to carry out his
         "threat." Some early cases found the willfullness requirement met if the speaker
         voluntarily uttered the charged words with "an apparent determination to carry them into
         execution." Ragansky v. United States, <span class="citation no-link">
            <span class="volume">253</span>
            <span class="reporter">F.</span>
            <span class="page">643</span>
         </span>, 645 (C. A. 7th Cir. 1918) (emphasis supplied); cf. Pierce v. United States, 365 F.
         2d 292 (C. A. <span class="star-pagination">*708</span> 10th Cir. 1966). The majority below
         seemed to agree. Perhaps this interpretation is correct, although we have grave doubts
         about it. See the dissenting opinion below, 131 U. S. App. D. C., at 135-142, 402 F. 2d, at
         686-693 (Wright, J.). But whatever the "willfullness" requirement implies, the statute
         initially requires the Government to prove a true "threat." We do not believe that the kind
         of political hyperbole indulged in by petitioner fits within that statutory term. For we
         must interpret the language Congress chose "against the background of a profound national
         commitment to the principle that debate on public issues should be uninhibited, robust, and
         wide-open, and that it may well include vehement, caustic, and sometimes unpleasantly sharp
         attacks on government and public officials." New York Times Co. v. Sullivan, 376 U. S. 254,
         270 (1964). The language of the political arena, like the language used in labor disputes,
         see Linn v. United Plant Guard Workers of America, 383 U. S. 53, 58 (1966), is often
         vituperative, abusive, and inexact. We agree with petitioner that his only offense here was
         "a kind of very crude offensive method of stating a political opposition to the President."
         Taken in context, and regarding the expressly conditional nature of the statement and the
         reaction of the listeners, we do not see how it could be interpreted otherwise.</p>
      <p>The motion for leave to proceed in forma pauperis and the petition for a writ of certiorari
         are granted and the judgment of the Court of Appeals is reversed. The case is remanded with
         instructions that it be returned to the District Court for entry of a judgment of
         acquittal.</p>
      <p>It is so ordered.</p>
      <p>MR. JUSTICE STEWART would deny the petition for certiorari.</p>
      <p>MR. JUSTICE WHITE dissents.</p>
      <p>
         <span class="star-pagination">*709</span> MR. JUSTICE DOUGLAS, concurring.</p>
      <p>The charge in this case is of an ancient vintage.</p>
      <p>The federal statute under which petitioner was convicted traces its ancestry to the Statute
         of Treasons (25 Edw. 3) which made it a crime to "compass or imagine the Death of . . . the
         King." Note, Threats to Take the Life of the President, 32 Harv. L. Rev. 724, 725 (1919).
         It is said that one Walter Walker, a 15th century keeper of an inn known as the "Crown,"
         was convicted under the Statute of Treasons for telling his son: "Tom, if thou behavest
         thyself well, I will make thee heir to the CROWN." He was found guilty of compassing and
         imagining the death of the King, hanged, drawn, and quartered. 1 J. Campbell, Lives of the
         Chief Justices of England 151 (1873).</p>
      <p>In the time of Edward IV, one Thomas Burdet who predicted that the king would "soon die,
         with a view to alienate the affections" of the people was indicted for "compassing and
         imagining of the death of the King," 79 Eng. Rep. 706 (1477)&#x97;the crime of constructive
            treason<span class="sup">[1]</span> with which the old reports are filled.</p>
      <p>
         <span class="star-pagination">*710</span> In the time of Charles II, one Edward Brownlow
         was indicted "for speaking these words, that he wished all the gentry in the land would
         kill one another, so that the comminalty might live the better." 3 Middlesex County Rec.
         326 (1888). In the same year (1662) one Robert Thornell was indicted for saying "that if
         the Kinge did side with the Bishops, the divell take Kinge and the Bishops too." Id., at
         327.</p>
      <p>While our Alien and Sedition Laws were in force, John Adams, President of the United
         States, en route from Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to Quincy, Massachusetts, stopped in
         Newark, New Jersey, where he was greeted by a crowd and by a committee that saluted him by
         firing a cannon.</p>
      <p>A bystander said, "There goes the President and they are firing at his ass." Luther Baldwin
         was indicted for replying that he did not care "if they fired through his ass." He was
         convicted in the federal court for speaking "sedicious words tending to defame the
         President and Government of the United States" and fined, assessed court costs and
         expenses, and committed to jail until the fine and fees were paid. See J. Smith, Freedom's
         Fetters 270-274 (1956).</p>
      <p>The Alien and Sedition Laws constituted one of our sorriest chapters; and I had thought we
         had done with them forever.<span class="sup">[2]</span>
      </p>
      <p>
         <span class="star-pagination">*711</span> Yet the present statute has hardly fared better.
         "Like the Statute of Treasons, section 871 was passed in a `relatively calm peacetime
         spring,' but has been construed under circumstances when intolerance for free speech was
         much greater than it normally might be." Note, Threatening the President: Protected
         Dissenter or Political Assassin, 57 Geo. L. J. 553, 570 (1969). Convictions under 18 U. S.
         C. ยง 871 have been sustained for displaying posters urging passersby to "hang [President]
         Roosevelt." United States v. Apel, <span class="citation">
            <a href="/ilnd/aBun/united-states-v-apel/">
               <span class="volume">44</span>
               <span class="reporter">F. Supp.</span>
               <span class="page">592</span>
            </a>
         </span>, 593 (D. C. N. D. Ill. 1942); for declaring that "President Wilson ought to be
         killed. It is a wonder some one has not done it already. If I had an opportunity, I would
         do it myself." United States v. Stickrath, <span class="citation no-link">
            <span class="volume">242</span>
            <span class="reporter">F.</span>
            <span class="page">151</span>
         </span>, 152 (D. C. S. D. Ohio 1917); for declaring that "Wilson is a wooden-headed son of
         a bitch. I wish Wilson was in hell, and if I had the power I would put him there," Clark v.
         United States, <span class="citation no-link">
            <span class="volume">250</span>
            <span class="reporter">F.</span>
            <span class="page">449</span>
         </span> (C. A. 5th Cir. 1918). In sustaining an indictment under the statute against a man
         who indicated that he would enjoy shooting President Wilson if he had the chance, the trial
         court explained the thrust of ยง 871:</p> "The purpose of the statute was undoubtedly, not
      only the protection of the President, but also the prohibition of just such statements as
      those alleged in this indictment. The expression of such direful intentions and desires, not
      only indicates a spirit of disloyalty to the nation bordering upon treason, but is, in a very
      real sense, a menace to the peace and safety of the country. . . . It arouses resentment <span
         class="star-pagination">*712</span> and concern on the part of patriotic citizens." United
      States v. Jasick, <span class="citation no-link">
         <span class="volume">252</span>
         <span class="reporter">F.</span>
         <span class="page">931</span>
      </span>, 933 (D. C. E. D. Mich. 1918). <p>Suppression of speech as an effective police measure
         is an old, old device, outlawed by our Constitution.</p>
      <p>MR. JUSTICE FORTAS, with whom MR. JUSTICE HARLAN joins, dissenting.</p>
      <p>The Court holds, without hearing, that this statute is constitutional and that it is here
         wrongly applied. Neither of these rulings should be made without hearing, even if we assume
         that they are correct.</p>
      <p>Perhaps this is a trivial case because of its peculiar facts and because the petitioner was
         merely given a suspended sentence. That does not justify the Court's action. It should
         induce us to deny certiorari, not to decide the case on its merits and to adjudicate the
         difficult questions that it presents.</p>
      <div type="notes">
      <p>[*] 18 U. S. C. ยง 871 (a) provides: </p>
      <p>"Whoever knowingly and willfully deposits for conveyance in the mail or for a delivery from
         any post office or by any letter carrier any letter, paper, writing, print, missive, or
         document containing any threat to take the life of or to inflict bodily harm upon the
         President of the United States, the President-elect, the Vice President or other officer
         next in the order of succession to the office of President of the United States, or the
         Vice President-elect, or knowingly and willfully otherwise makes any such threat against
         the President, President-elect, Vice President or other officer next in the order of
         succession to the office of President, or Vice President-elect, shall be fined not more
         than $1,000 or imprisoned not more than five years, or both."</p>
      <p>[1] The prosecution in those cases laid bare to the juries that the treasonous thoughts
         were the heart of the matter; "the original of his Treasons proceeded from the imagination
         of his heart; which imagination was in itself High-Treason, albeit the same proceeded not
         to any overt fact: and the heart being possessed with the abundance of his traitorous
         imagination, and not being able so to contain itself, burst forth in vile and traitorous
         Speeches, and from thence to horrible and heinous actions." Trial of Sir John Perrot, 1
         How. St. Tr. 1315, 1318 (1592). "[T]he high treason charged, is the compassing or imagining
         (in other words, the intending or designing) the death of the king; I mean his NATURAL
         DEATH; which being a hidden operation of the mind, an overt act is any thing which legally
         proves the existence of such traitorous design and intention&#x97;I say that the design
         against the king's natural life, is the high treason under the first branch of the statute;
         and whatever is evidence, which may be legally laid before a jury to judge of the
         traitorous intention, is a legal overt act; because an overt act is nothing but legal
         evidence embodied upon the record." Trial of Thomas Hardy, 24 How. St. Tr. 199, 894 (1794).
         And see 84 Eng. Rep. 1057 (1708). </p>
      <p>For a discussion of the adequacy of mere words as overt acts see 3 W. Holdsworth, History
         of English Law 293 (1927).</p>
      <p>[2] "In the Sedition Act cases, the tendency of words to produce acts against the peace and
         security of the community was stretched to its utmost latitude. Likewise, judges and
         juries, in their willingness to presume evil intent on the part of Republican writers,
         largely nullified the safeguards erected by the Sedition Act itself. Criticism of the
         President and Congress&#x97;in which every American indulges as his birthright&#x97;was
         severely punished; yet this practice manifestly has only a remote tendency to injure and
         bring into contempt the government of the United States. In short, much that has become
         commonplace in American political life was put under the ban by the Federalist lawmakers
         and judges of 1798." J. Miller, Crisis in Freedom 233 (1951).</p>
   </div></body>
</opinion>
